<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canaans flovvings, or, A second part of milk &amp; honey being another collation of many Christian experiences, sayings, &amp;c. : with an appendix called The heathen improved, or, The Gibeonites hewing of wood, and drawing of water for the sanctuary / by Ralph Venning.</title>
            <author>Venning, Ralph, 1621?-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12193881</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12193881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55955</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55955)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 441:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Canaans flovvings, or, A second part of milk &amp; honey being another collation of many Christian experiences, sayings, &amp;c. : with an appendix called The heathen improved, or, The Gibeonites hewing of wood, and drawing of water for the sanctuary / by Ralph Venning.</title>
                  <author>Venning, Ralph, 1621?-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 229 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Prinred [sic] by S. Griffin for John Rothwell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] and p. 229.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion --  Quotations, maxims, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:55955:1"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. ſentence 23. <hi>for,</hi> for all, <hi>read</hi> all for. p. 17. ſ. 135. <hi>for</hi> Gods, <hi>read</hi> God. p. 28. ſ. 223. <hi>for over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>read</hi> undervalued. p. 31. ſ 254. <hi>for</hi> fearfull, <hi>read</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. p. 35. ſ. 280. <hi>for</hi> complements, <hi>read</hi> complement, p. 39. ſ. 312. for robs, <hi>read</hi> rob.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Paradoxes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 10. ſentence 49. <hi>for</hi> ye, <hi>read</hi> yea.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55955:1"/>
            <p>CANAANS <hi>FLOVVINGS.</hi> Or a ſecond part of <hi>MILK</hi> &amp; <hi>HONEY;</hi> BEING Another Collation of many Chriſtian Experiences, Sayings, &amp;c. WITH An Appendix called the <hi>HEATHEN IMPROVED;</hi> OR, The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> hewing of wood, and drawing of water for the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RALPH VENNING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſpiſe not ſmall things; you may make much of a little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Prinred by <hi>S. Griffin,</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> at the Fountaine and Beare in <hi>Goldſmiths Row</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55955:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55955:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot tell how to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite thee, becauſe I know not whether the entertainment be worthy of thee; if thou look for dainties, and rarities, <hi>I fear</hi> thou wilt not make a good meal here; if plain fare will be acceptable, <hi>come and welcome,</hi> and much good may it doe thee: <hi>as to my ſelf,</hi> if thou wonder why I write thus, be pleaſed to know that I write not to pleaſe men, or for the praiſe of men; for I am ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſſured, that theſe are not
<pb facs="tcp:55955:3"/>the things, nor this the way, by which I ſhould get glory, <hi>if it were in mine eye:</hi> the beſt of it is, I am afore-hand with all men in this, that none can think more meanly of what I have done, then I my ſelf doe; and <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> I ſhall not think my ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued, though thou put no value upon it; 'tis ſuch <hi>as I believe,</hi> all will not like, nor will all diſlike; <hi>though all will not be pleaſed, yet ſome will not be diſpleaſed to read it.</hi> I call on no man to commend it, but on any <hi>(that finds fault)</hi> to come and mend it, to doe better things then theſe, or theſe things better. <hi>'Tis common and eaſie to find faults in our ſelves and others
<pb facs="tcp:55955:3"/>that are to be mended, but hard and rare to mend the faults that are to be found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Haply ſome would perſwade thee and me to believe, that ſome other things of mine, and writing another way, might be more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable; <hi>have a litle patience,</hi> and if God give life and ability, I may in due time make trial, for I would willingly doe good by any and every talent that God hath given me.</p>
            <p>Theſe are not the firſt, but <hi>(though I have remains)</hi> are very like to be the laſt of my <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venilia,</hi> or youthful collections. Some Scriptures are onely allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to, that <hi>I might give an hint to this,</hi> that the Scriptures
<pb facs="tcp:55955:4"/>a ſtore-houſe, which would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with ſuch variety of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and exemplification, that we need not goe down to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines to ſharpen our axes, nor travel ſo much for Outlandiſh rarities to garniſh <hi>(Sermons and Dicſourſes)</hi> the diſhes of Goſpel-grace withal. I have made ſome application of Heathen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances alſo, <hi>and could wiſh</hi> that many who go under a better name, were but ſo good men, <hi>and that the Iſraelites did the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary as much ſervice as the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites.</hi> Some ſtories are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven, which I hope may paſſe for more then table-talk, and ſerve in better ſtead, then many vain, idle, <hi>ſoul-infecting
<pb facs="tcp:55955:4"/>ſtories,</hi> which are too too often told to paſſe away time, without any tendency to ſpiritual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement. <hi>If it be ſaid,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe things are to bee found elſewhere; <hi>I grant it,</hi> yet many will finde them here, which elſe perhaps had never known they had been elſewhere. <hi>To be ſhort,</hi> if thou think 'twill doe thee any good, goe on; if not, forbear; though I hope thou wilt not place it among thy loſt time, if thou peruſe it; nay, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou wilt allow mee ſome grains for my weakneſſe, when thou perceiveſt that I meant well, and was <hi>(at leaſt)</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe thy ſoul good. If it bee not done now, I will watch
<pb facs="tcp:55955:5"/>and wait, when, and till I can, for <hi>ſurely</hi> I ſhall be a lover of ſouls, and endeavour to doe them good, while I have a bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Auguſt 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>RALPH VENNING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55955:5"/>
            <head>CANAANS Flowings: OR, <hi>More Milk and Honey.</hi> BEING Another Collation of many Chriſtian Experiences, Sayings, Sentences; and ſeverall places of Scripture improved.</head>
            <div n="1" type="century">
               <head>The Firſt Century.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome men <hi>(would Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors did not)</hi> mind this world ſo much as if it would never have an end; and the World to come ſo little, as if it would never have a beginning.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Profeſſors need not be ſo much
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55955:6"/>affected with the goods of this world, <hi>for the beſt is not good enough to make an Heaven:</hi> nor need they be ſo much afflicted with the evils of it, <hi>for the worſt is not bad enough to make an Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Any thing (the beſt) on this ſ'ide Heaven <hi>(compared with that)</hi> is miſery; and any thing (the worſt) on this ſide Hell, <hi>(compared with that)</hi> is mercy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Saints ſhould and doe <hi>(if they doe as they ſhould)</hi> look upon all the commands of God as eaſie and pleaſant; 1. becauſe commanded by God that loves them; 2. becauſe to be obeyed by them that love God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Seeing God doth all things well, we ſhould think well of all things which God doth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Chriſtians ſhould not onely purpoſe to be religious, <hi>but</hi> they ſhould be religious to purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To worſhip God in ſpirit, is the ſpirit of our worſhip; <hi>fleſh</hi> is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55955:6"/>unſuitable, and unacceptable.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If we ſhould be much thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a little mercy, <hi>what a ſhame is it</hi> to be but a little thankfull for much mercy!</p>
               <p n="9">9. Seeing God was ſo willing to put <hi>his ſon</hi> to death for our ſakes; how <hi>(oh how!)</hi> willing ſhould we be to put <hi>our ſins</hi> to death for Gods ſake?</p>
               <p n="10">10. If pleaſures are <hi>(as indeed they are)</hi> diſpleaſing, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.12. (<hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patian</hi> was tired with a triumph) what then are diſpleaſures? if our recreations are toylſome, what are our toyles? if our eaſe be painfull, what is our pain? <hi>on this ſide the enjoyment of God, there is no reſt; for all the reſt is vanity and vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. It behoves Chriſtians to be <hi>often</hi> in ſelf-trial, and to be <hi>alwaies</hi> in ſelf-denial.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Sinners are alive to that which Saints are dead, viz. <hi>ſin:</hi> and dead to that to which Saints
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55955:7"/>are alive, viz. <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Sin may be in his heart who is a Saint, but his heart <hi>(who is a Saint)</hi> cannot be in ſin.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The doctrine of the Goſpel is not onely able to comfort, <hi>but</hi> 'tis a comfortable doctrine.</p>
               <p n="15">15. There are many who hold the truth which they are to do, but doe not doe the truth which they hold; thus holding truth in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, they have the wrath of God reveald from Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, becauſe they received not the love of the truth, which was revealed from heaven to them.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Much is but little, where more is expected; and good is not good, where better is expected.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Some men forget to pray, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers forget what they have prayed, and others forget that they have prayed; ſo little of their heart is in duty, and ſo little impreſſion of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in their heart, that <hi>all comes to nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55955:7"/>
               <p n="18">18. They who deſerve nothing, have <hi>good reaſon</hi> to be content with any thing; and they that deſerve not any thing have <hi>no reaſon</hi> to be diſcontented, though they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p n="19">19. God ſometimes puts his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to a little pain, that he may give them much eaſe.</p>
               <p n="20">20. How deſirable ſo ever the things be which we deſire, we are to ſubmit and ſurrender our deſires to God, <hi>and ſay,</hi> Not my wil <hi>O Lord,</hi> but thine be done.</p>
               <p n="21">21. 'Tis a lovely ſight to ſee a den of thieves turned into a houſe of prayer; <hi>but</hi> tis a lothſome ſight to ſee an houſe of prayer turned into a den of theeves.</p>
               <p n="22">22. The leaſt meaſure of grace is better then the greateſt meaſure of gifts: for the greateſt meaſure of gifts without grace is not, but the the leaſt meaſure of grace <hi>(though without gifts)</hi> is acceptable to God in the diſcharge of duties.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55955:8"/>
               <p n="23">23. 'Tis dangerous ſinning againſt conſcience, for ſuch are in danger to make <hi>(at length)</hi> no conſcience of ſinning.</p>
               <p n="24">24. 'Tis no ſmall mercy to be kept from ſmall ſins; but how great a mercy is it to be kept from great ſins! <hi>Oh Lord, when from all ſins?</hi> in the mean time, happy they who can in ſincerity ſay, 'tis not we that ſin, but ſin that dwelleth in us.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Moſt men can eaſily remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber if they have any thing againſt their brother, that hee may right them: <hi>but</hi> few men care to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber if their brother have any thing againſt them, that they may right him; which is the great command on a great peril, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.23.</p>
               <p n="26">26. In prayer the heart ſhould firſt ſpeak the words, and then the words ſhould ſpeak the heart.</p>
               <p n="27">27. There are two, and but two kind of ſins; the one of commiſſion, in doing what ought not to be done; the other of omiſſion, in not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55955:8"/>doing what ought to be done; for both theſe men ſhall be judged at the laſt day. For ſins of commiſſion, <hi>Jud.</hi> 15. for ſins of omiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41, 42.</p>
               <p n="28">28. God in the Covenant hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to take away the fleſh of the heart, and to give an heart of fleſh.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Many ungodly men have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, yet are not content; godly men are content with what they have, and that's their enough.</p>
               <p n="30">30. A part of the Chriſtians <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> prayer is, that he may not ſleep in his ſin, nor ſin in his ſleep.</p>
               <p n="31">31. When a Saint goes to bed, he ſhould look on himſelfe as buried alive in a grave above ground; and not knowing but that he may ſleep the ſleepe of death, he ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his ſpirit into the hands of God, <hi>praying and hoping,</hi> either for a reſurrection for the better in this world, or for a better reſurrection in the world to come.</p>
               <p n="32">32. A part of the Saints morning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55955:9"/>prayer is, that ſeeing it hath pleaſed. God to renew his life, his life may be renewed to the wel-pleaſing of God.</p>
               <p n="33">33. Wee ſhould labour for reſt, and follow our work while we live; for when we die, <hi>(if in the Lord)</hi> we ſhall reſt from our labour, and our work ſhall follow us.</p>
               <p n="34">34. A Saint doth pray, not onely that the Word of God may ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the creatures to his uſe, <hi>but alſo</hi> that in and for the uſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hee may ſanctifie the God of the word.</p>
               <p n="35">35. A Saint doth pray, not onely that the curſe which ſin brought may be taken away, <hi>but alſo</hi> that the ſinne may be taken away which brought the curſe.</p>
               <p n="36">36. A Saint doth pray, not onely that God would ſhed abroad his love upon the creatures, that they may be ſerviceable to him, <hi>but</hi> hee prayes alſo that God would ſhed abroad his love in his heart, that hee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55955:9"/>may be ſerviceable to God.</p>
               <p n="37">37. Wee ſhould ſhew mercy to the poore, not onely out of pitty to them, <hi>but</hi> out of piety to God.</p>
               <p n="38">38. A Chriſtian wil willingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that he owes his life to the death of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="39">39. Wee ſhould not onely beare the rod, but heare the rod; and did we heare the rod, and him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it, we ſhould the better beare the rod which hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
               <p n="40">40. Time was when hee <hi>(that is now a Saint)</hi> griev'd that he could ſin no more; but now he grieves for that griefe, and that ever he ſinned ſo much; yea, might hee have his next prayer granted, it ſhould be that he might ſin no more.</p>
               <p n="41">41. He that will have his ſecrets kept, muſt keep his ſecrets.</p>
               <p n="42">42. Wee have no reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of, or to be diſcontented with God, how ever he deale with us; for the leaſt good is more then wee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55955:10"/>deſerve, and the greateſt evil is no leſſe, nor no more then we deſerve.</p>
               <p n="43">43. If when we have done all, we are but unprofitable ſervants; how unprofitable ſervants then are we, who doe not doe all, <hi>no nor ſcarce at all,</hi> what is our duty to doe?</p>
               <p n="44">44. Them goods wil doe no man good, with which a man doth no good. Goods are not good as (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) things had, but as (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) things uſed and improved, ſo as to make friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs or deceitfulneſs.</p>
               <p n="45">45. Wel may a Saint ſay that he cannot be without God, for he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wel without God; <hi>vivere eſt valere,</hi> to live is to be well; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide wel being (which is to live, move, and have our being with and unto God) the reſt of our life (though we live, move, and have our being in him) is death, or but little better.</p>
               <p n="46">46. A Saint would willingly be more affected with Gods goodneſs, &amp; more afflicted for his own badnes.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55955:10"/>
               <p n="47">47. A man ſhould apply himſelfe to Chriſt, to be delivered, not onely from ſin, but from ſinning.</p>
               <p n="48">48. Wiſe men, when they have not opportunities will make them; but fooles wil not take opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties when they have them.</p>
               <p n="49">49. Many perſons have the grace of deſire, and doe deſire grace; and yet many times enjoy not the grace of their deſire.</p>
               <p n="50">50. Providences that croſſe our deſignes, are no croſſe providences to Gods deſignes.</p>
               <p n="51">51. Chriſt's ſatisfaction, not our ſanctification, is the ground of our juſtification; and yet where ever he is juſtification, he is ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo; or elſe there could be no ſalvation; for <hi>without holineſs no man ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="52">52. In the good-natured and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred perſon, a little grace wil make a great ſhew; but in an ill-natured and a perſon not wel-bred, a great deale of grace wil make but a little ſhew.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:55955:11"/>
               <p n="53">53. I would not <hi>(ſaith one)</hi> be alwaies buſie and doing, nor ever ſhut up in nothing but thoughts; yet that which ſome would call idleneſs, I would call the ſweeteſt part of my life, and that's my thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king time. <hi>Thoughts are good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, if they be good thoughts;</hi> and ſo a man may be never leſs alone, then when moſt alone; <hi>that is, all alone,</hi> when all is but one.</p>
               <p n="54">54. God many times awakens them at a Sermon, who came to ſleep at a Sermon, ſo that <hi>(I ſpeak it ſeriouſly)</hi> God takes them nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
               <p n="55">55. While we are in this world, we know but part, and but in part; <hi>hereafter</hi> we ſhall know more, and more fully; yet then the fulneſſe wil not <hi>(cannot)</hi> be fully known.</p>
               <p n="56">56. Gods thoughts and purpoſes towards <hi>Sion,</hi> and <hi>Sions</hi> thoughts of Gods purpoſes, are many times clean contrary, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49, 27, 28. My thoughts are not your thoughts,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55955:11"/>nor my waies your waies, <hi>ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſaiah 55.8.</p>
               <p n="57">57. <hi>Paul,</hi> Noble and Publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirited <hi>Paul</hi> became all things to all men, that all men might gaine by him; but many <hi>(and not now adaies?)</hi> baſe ſpirited and ſelf-ſeeking men, become all things to all men, that they may gain by all men. <hi>Paul</hi> ſought the good of other men, <hi>but</hi> theſe ſeek other mens goods.</p>
               <p n="58">58. We are unworthy for whom God ſhould doe any thing, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to doe any thing for God; <hi>but</hi> hee is worthy for whom wee ſhould doe all things.</p>
               <p n="59">59. Though Gods waies are hid from us, yet our waies are not hid from God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.27. Though we know not the way that he takes, yet he knows the way that we take, <hi>Job</hi> 23.8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p n="60">60. Many men rejoyce in the light wherein they ſhould walk, <hi>but</hi> doe not walk in the light wherein they rejoyce.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55955:12"/>
               <p n="61">61. 'Tis not very ſafe to truſt them with too great a power of the ſword in their hands, who have not the power of the word <hi>(which is the ſword of the ſpirit)</hi> in their hearts.</p>
               <p n="62">62. Where ſin abounds, grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds; but where grace abounds, fin doth not abound; for <hi>(ſaith the ſoule)</hi> becauſe God hath been mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to mee who ſinned againſt him, I wil not ſin againſt God who is mercifull to me.</p>
               <p n="63">63. Things done by men have a tendency to bring about Gods ends, though the men that doe the things, doe not intend it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 10.5, 7. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.27, 28.</p>
               <p n="64">64. It ſometimes overthrows men to have done too much good, or too great ſervice, for the <hi>Princes and Grandees</hi> of the world (though they are willing to have others behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them, yet are) unwilling to have themſelves beholding to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:55955:12"/>
               <p n="65">65. Many heare, and love to hear the things which they are to doe; <hi>but</hi> few doe, and fewer love to doe the things which they heare.</p>
               <p n="66">66. In an unregenerate eſtate a man is free from God, and a ſervant to ſin; but in a regenerate eſtate, a man is free from ſin, and is a ſervant to God: his firſt freedom was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſlavery, his ſecond ſervice is perfect freedom.</p>
               <p n="67">67. He is a foole that doth not ſay in his heart there is a God; <hi>but</hi> what a foole is he, that ſaith in his heart there is no God?</p>
               <p n="68">68. 'Tis a ſin not to think that there is a God; but what a fin is it to think that there is not a God? <hi>yet alas!</hi> ſuch wretches there are in the world as doe, if not in words, yet in heart and works deny God to have a being, though in him they live, move, and have their being; <hi>but</hi> though ſuch are <hi>Atheiſts</hi> on earth, yet when they come to hell, they wil not be <hi>Atheiſts</hi> there, where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55955:13"/>they wil <hi>to their coſt and pain,</hi> feele that there is a God.</p>
               <p n="69">69. 'Tis not enough to a Saint that he hath prayed for grace, <hi>unleſs</hi> he have the grace prayed for.</p>
               <p n="70">70. Life-Reformation, without heart-renovation, wil never attain to heaven-ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="71">71. There is ſuch a connection between being in Chriſt Jeſus, being a new creature, faith working by love, and keeping the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, that they are put one for all, as appeares by comparing 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7, 19. What therefore God hath joyn'd together, let no man put aſunder: <hi>he that takes one for all; without all, will finde it nothing at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="72">72. Chriſt doth not onely deliver his people from eternall condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but alſo from a ſinfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; <hi>yea,</hi> he delivers them from a ſinfull coverſation, that he may deliver them from condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55955:13"/>
               <p n="73">73. 'Tis a dangerous thing not to look over our waies; <hi>but</hi> 'tis much more dangerous to overlook our waies.</p>
               <p n="74">74. 'Tis a greater honour to us to ſerve God, then tis to God that we ſerve him. 'Tis not he, but we are happy by it; as <hi>the Queen of Sheba</hi> ſaid of <hi>Solomon's</hi> ſervants, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.8.</p>
               <p n="75">75. The divels believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſo do Saints, for they work out their ſalvation with feare and trembling; <hi>but with this difference,</hi> the divels tremble becauſe of the judgement which ſin wil bring; the Saints tremble becauſe of the ſin which brings the judgement; the divels and wicked men trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble becauſe they have ſinned, the Saints tremble that they may not ſinne.</p>
               <p n="76">76. The head may remember what the heart forgets, <hi>but</hi> the head wil never forget what the heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members. <hi>The ſenſe of mercy is the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55955:14"/>beſt memory,</hi> Deut. 4.9. leſt they depart from thine heart.</p>
               <p n="77">77. Though one ſoule be more worth then a whole world, yet a whole world of ſoules is not worth one Chriſt; <hi>oh how great then is the love of God!</hi> that he would give his only begotten ſon to ſave the ſouls of men.</p>
               <p n="78">78. Though the prayer we make to God cannot, yet the God to whom we make our prayers can change our hearts.</p>
               <p n="79">79. As faith without works is, ſo works without faith are dead alſo; religion is not in believing or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but in believing and doing; 'tis not any one thing, <hi>but things</hi> which accompany or contain ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.9.</p>
               <p n="80">80. A Saint ſhould daily and duely obſerve Gods dealings with him, and his dealings with God.</p>
               <p n="81">81. 'Twere better not to be born, then to be, and not to be new born.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55955:14"/>
               <p n="82">82. How can we expect that God ſhould heare us when we call on him, if we wil not heare him when he cals on us.</p>
               <p n="83">83. A Saint had rather ſuffer for the Goſpel and religion a thouſand times, then that the Goſpel or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould ſuffer once by him.</p>
               <p n="84">84. He that would ſee God in ordinances, when hee comes to them, ſhould ſeek God before he comes to the ordinances.</p>
               <p n="85">85. If we fall in with God, it matters not who fall out with us.</p>
               <p n="86">86. Many men have the things of their peace to conſider of, but <hi>(a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las!)</hi> but few conſider of the things of their peace; they hide their eyes ſo long from the things of their peace, that at laſt the things of their peace are hidden from their eyes.</p>
               <p n="87">87. Men ſhould take heed of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves to laſciviouſneſſe, leſt when they give themſelves over, God give them up to laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and vile affections, as he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55955:15"/>did them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26.</p>
               <p n="88">88. It were to be wiſhed <hi>(provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it croſſe not the calling of God)</hi> that great men were good men, or that good men were great men.</p>
               <p n="89">89. Many perſons as ſoon as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is done have done with the Sermon, and as ſoon as prayer is done, have done with the prayer; <hi>when as</hi> they ſhould then doe the Sermon, and practice the prayer.</p>
               <p n="90">90. A Saint doth good not onely becauſe it pleaſeth him, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſeth God; nor doth he avoyd ſin onely becauſe it diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, but becauſe it diſpleaſeth God.</p>
               <p n="91">91. The work of the Goſpel is to make bad men good, and good men better.</p>
               <p n="92">92. He that's moſt full of God, is moſt empty of himſelfe; and he that's moſt full of himſelfe, is moſt empty of God.</p>
               <p n="93">93. Though all graee be in all Saints, yet ſome grace ſcarce ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55955:15"/>in moſt Saints, and moſt grace ſcarce appears in ſome Saints.</p>
               <p n="94">94. Among them that have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelves ſhepheards, there have been found ſome idle, and ſome idol-ſhepherds.</p>
               <p n="95">95. A gracious heart doth not only hate ſin when tis committed, <hi>but</hi> he hates to commit it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.</p>
               <p n="96">96. We ſhould ſtudy not ſo much what ſhall become of us, as what becomes us; for what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us is among the ſecret things <hi>which belong to God;</hi> but what becomes us is among the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed things <hi>which belong to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="97">97. As <hi>God-love</hi> is the fulfilling of God's law, or the law as to God; and <hi>man-love</hi> the fulfilling of mans law, or the law as to man; ſo <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love,</hi> or <hi>ſin-love</hi> is the fulfilling of the law of ſin: for the whole law is fulfilled in this one word, <hi>love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="98">98. Some would not ſeem evil, and yet would be ſo; and ſome would ſeem good, but would not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55955:16"/>be ſo; but tell me, thou hypocrite (ſaid <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) if it be a good thing to be good, why wilt thou not be that which thou wouldſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be? for that which is a ſhame for a man to appeare to be, is much more a ſhame to be it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: either be therefore ſuch as thou appeareſt, or elſe appeare ſuch as thou art.</p>
               <p n="99">99. Some men had rather be of that religion, and of ſuch opinions in that religion, which wil raiſe them; then be of that religion which wil ſave them: as if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in this life were more worth then a reſurrection unto and an aſcention into eternall life.</p>
               <p n="100">100. <hi>Latimer</hi> ſaith of the Clergy, that they were ſo wiſe, that by their wiſdom, they had almoſt made all the world fooles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="century">
               <head>The ſecond Century.</head>
               <p n="101">101. Man is not (true) as God,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55955:16"/>and therefore not to be truſted; God is not (falſe) as man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be diſtruſted.</p>
               <p n="102">102. The promiſe is as ſatisfying to faith, as performance is to ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="103">103. He that believes every thing that is reported, and reports every thing which he believes, wil report that which ſhould not be believed, and believe that which ſhould not be reported.</p>
               <p n="104">104. He that leaves all things, and denies not himſelfe, forſakes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and he that denies himſelfe, and ſets not his heart on what he hath, forſakes his all, though he keep it all.</p>
               <p n="105">105. The beſt way to enjoy ones wil is to deny ones wil; not to own our wil, when our wil doth not own Gods: and then to be ſure, <hi>he may doe what he wil, that wil doe but what he may.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="106">106. Many men know the good they are to doe, but doe not doe the good they know, to them it is ſin.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55955:17"/>
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.17. others doe they know not what; theſe may doe good, but the good they doe cannot be well done; others know not what they are to doe, but this wil not excuſe them from doing; for every man ſhould learn what he is to practice, and then practice what hee hath learnt. Practice without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is like <hi>Leah</hi> fruitfull, but blear-eyed; and knowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out practice is like <hi>Rachel</hi> faire, but barren; when <hi>Rachels</hi> face, and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> womb, when knowledge and practice meet in the ſame perſon, <hi>then happy is he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="107">107. No man cares for ſorrows, yet nothing works ſorrows more then cares; for they that will be rich, pierce themſelves through with many ſorrows.</p>
               <p n="108">108. We ſhould welcome God not onely when he brings good to us, for that is to welcome God for our own ſake; <hi>but</hi> we ſhould alſo welcome God when he brings evil
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55955:17"/>upon us, for that is <hi>(which is better)</hi> to welcome God for his own ſake.</p>
               <p n="109">109. How much ſoever good men ſuffer, and how ill ſoever it goe with them in this world, if they be found in waies of wel-doing, they ſhall doe wel; for Chriſt will ſay, <hi>Wel done</hi> thou good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant.</p>
               <p n="110">110. <hi>Good Lord!</hi> into how many evils ſhould we fall, didſt not thou keep us from them? and how many evils would fall on us, didſt not thou keepe them from us?</p>
               <p n="111">111. As nothing wil more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet us <hi>(as to publike affaires)</hi> then the conſideration of mans diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly acting, ſo nothing wil more quiet us, then the conſideration of Gods ordering mans actings: for God never ſo leaves the reins on mens necks, but that he keeps them in his own hand.</p>
               <p n="112">112. Inordinate affection brings extraordinary affliction.</p>
               <p n="113">113. 'Tis a great mercy to have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55955:18"/>any good thing in this world; what a mercy then is it to have many good things in this world? <hi>but</hi> what a miſery is it to have all our good things in this world?</p>
               <p n="114">114. The old Saints, or the Saints of old time lived new lives; but alas! the new Saints, or the Saints of new and latter times, live old lives.</p>
               <p n="115">115. 'Tis hard to be conformable to the world in the outward man, and to be conformable to God in the inward man; <hi>'tis hard</hi> to be like a ſinner without, and not to be a ſinner within.</p>
               <p n="116">116. A Saint begs of God that all Gods dealings may have love to him written upon them, and <hi>as heartily begs of God</hi> that all his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings may have love and holineſſe to the Lord written upon them.</p>
               <p n="117">117. A Saint is a man of another world in this, and therefore ſhould live out of the world while in it, &amp; have his converſation in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="118">118. If a man have not an appetite
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55955:18"/>to pray, let him pray for an appetite; for neglect or omiſſion of a duty ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fits, but alwaies unfits for duty.</p>
               <p n="119">119. When the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, I live, he doth not mean, that he liv'd alone without <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and when he ſaith, not I but <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he doth not mean, that Chriſt liv'd alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him: but his meaning is, that by <hi>Chriſt</hi> he is what he is, according to that ſaying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. by the grace of God I am what I am; and that, I laboured more abundantly then they all, yet not I, but the grace of God; as if he had ſaid, I owe not onely this, but my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I owe my life to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the life of my new life.</p>
               <p n="120">120. A Saint doth but little of the good he doth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. and he doth not much of the evil he doth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20. 'tis true he lives and labours, yet not he; 'tis true he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, yet not he.</p>
               <p n="121">121. Meetings are then for the better, when we are the better for our meetings.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55955:19"/>
               <p n="122">122. The image of the firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion makes men excell other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but the image of the ſecond creation makes men to excell men.</p>
               <p n="123">123. Hee that begs of God for daily bread, begs food for his ſoule as wel as his body: <hi>for either</hi> a man ſhould not take more care then need, becauſe God knows we have need of theſe things, and doth give us richly to enjoy not onely for this life, but <hi>(which is better)</hi> for a better life.</p>
               <p n="124">124. What certain hazzards doe men runne for uncertain gain! 'tis uncertain whether men ſhall gaine or no, <hi>all are but adventurers:</hi> 'tis as uncertain whether they ſhall keepe what they have gotten: 'tis certain that if they have gotten much, and have kept it long, yet that they ſhall be taken from it, or it from them. No trade ſo gainfull as god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, if it be cloſely followed.</p>
               <p n="125">125. The beſt and worſt of this world puts us upon longing for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55955:19"/>Heaven; for if the beſt of the world be good, heaven is much better; and if the worſt be ſo bad, who would not long to goe from bad to good.</p>
               <p n="126">126. If a Chriſtian be called to be a Magiſtrate, 'tis not enough for him to be a Chriſtian man, but he muſt be <hi>a Chriſtian Magiſtrate:</hi> he ſhould rather ceaſe to be a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, then ceaſe to be a Chriſtian: 'tis not enough to ſay, he is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and a Magiſtrate, but that he is a <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate:</hi> when God hath conjoynd them, man muſt not disjoyn them.</p>
               <p n="127">127. The moſt <hi>(and moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed)</hi> policy, is little better then circumſtantiall diſſimulation; be ſure therefore not to act the ſerpent without the dove: 'tis better to act the dove without the ſerpent, then the ſerpent without the dove; <hi>'tis better to be pious without policy, then to be politick without piety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="128">128. Its worſe to be heart-tied,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55955:20"/>then to be tongue-tied in prayer; 'tis better to be ſtraitned in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then in affection; if there be much of heart, it matters not how little of art there be in prayer, for <hi>what ſome men moſt admire, God leaſt regards,</hi> viz. volubility of tongue, variety of expreſſion, and ready utterance.</p>
               <p n="129">129. Time was when profeſſors had heart to ſerve God, but wanted time and liberty; but now profeſſors <hi>(and many of the former)</hi> have time and liberty, but want heart.</p>
               <p n="130">130. 'Tis an eaſie matter to teach others what to doe, but 'tis an hard matter to learn our own teaching, and doe what wee teach: Many know to counſel others how to walk, who know not how to walke by their own counſel. To ſuch it may be ſaid more truly then he to <hi>Job</hi> c. 4.3, 4, 5. <hi>Behold,</hi> thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed many, and thou haſt ſtrengthned the weake hands, thy words have upholden him that was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55955:20"/>falling: but now it is come upon thee, and thou fainteſt; it toucheth thee, and thou art troubled.</p>
               <p n="131">131. They that ſtand in ſlippery places <hi>(as all in high places doe)</hi> had beſt be much on their knees, and then they are in no great danger of falling, at leaſt of falling dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly.</p>
               <p n="132">132. Its fitter for youth to learn then to teach, and for age to teach then to learn; yet there are ſome young men old enough to teach, and no old man too old to learn.</p>
               <p n="133">133. Many men love the ſin, that cannot abide the name; they love pride, but it muſt be called decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; love covetouſneſſe, but it muſt be called thrift and good husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry; love flattering and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, but it muſt be called civility, and good breeding: and many times the ſame perſons love the name of grace, but cannot abide the grace; they hate godlines, yet would be called godly; loath Chriſtianity,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55955:21"/>yet would be called Chriſtians: let ſuch know, that <hi>ſin without the name will damne, and the name of grace without grace will not ſave.</hi> Lord, let me be more taken with godlineſſe, then with the name; and not at all with ſinne, though it have not the name.</p>
               <p n="134">134. To be ſo ſorrowfull as to forget our ſelves is weakneſſe, and to be ſo merry as to forget God is wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p n="135">135. A man ſhould not lay up ſo much as to give nothing, that's co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe: nor give ſo much as to lay up nothing, that's prodigality.</p>
               <p n="136">136. A good conſcience alwaies keeps good cheare, for 'tis a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall feaſt, and he that hath it fares wel, though he have no other food: the fatteſt Capons doe not afford ſuch merry thoughts as a good conſcience. <hi>What a ſhame is it then to a Chriſtian,</hi> if he cannot be merry without merriment, nor make me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody without muſick, nor dine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55955:21"/>and ſup without dainties &amp; ſauce? ſhall not the light of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance make us more glad then they that have their corn, and wine, and oyle? Lord, while others are like them in <hi>Job</hi> c. 21. from v. 7. to 16. let me be like-minded to <hi>Habucuk,</hi> c. 3, 17, 18, 19.</p>
               <p n="136">136. If God give us the uſe of mercy to pleaſure us, 'tis but reaſon that we ſhould uſe the mercy to pleaſe him.</p>
               <p n="137">137. If things fall not out as we would have them be, yet let it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent us that they fall out as God would have them be; God attains his end, though we miſſe ours: we know what we would have; but <hi>what we ſhould, is better then what we would.</hi> Can we be better diſpoſed of, then by wiſdom, goodneſſe, and faithfulneſſe it ſelfe? doth not God doe all things wel? he looked upon all that he made, and behold it was good exceedingly. We therefore ſhould not open our mouth <hi>(to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain)</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:55955:22"/>becauſe it is his doing; but in every thing give thanks; for this is the will of God in Chriſt Jeſus concerning us.</p>
               <p n="139">139. Some are fooliſh wiſe men, others are wiſe fools: the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God is wiſer then the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of men, for thats enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. They are wiſe who are wiſe for their ſoules; and they are fools who are not ſo, how wiſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="140">140. Seeing God doth not afflict willingly, we ſhould not ſin wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; ſeeing he delights not to grieve the children of men, the children of men ſhould not delight in any thing that wil grieve him.</p>
               <p n="141">141. All the ſufficiency of the Saints, and the ſufficiency of all the Saints is from Gods alſufficiency; <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> we are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think one good thought: <hi>my grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="142">142. Men ſhould not come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55955:22"/>barely to meet, leaſt their meeting prove but a bare comming together; without true cordial ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere friendſhip to improve ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, ſociety is but a meeting; and without which (though it be good to meet, yet) the meeting wil not be good; ſuch comming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil rather be for the worſe then for the better.</p>
               <p n="143">143. Many men would willingly be Gods ſons, who care not to be Gods ſervants; <hi>but God knows none for ſons, but ſuch as ſerve him:</hi> many would willingly be retainers, and weare Gods livery, that doe not care to wait, and to goe and come at his bidding. 'Twill, <hi>(but alas!)</hi> 'twil be cold comfort to be called ſervant, when it ſhall be ſaid, thou idle and wicked ſervant. <hi>Dives</hi> was never the better that <hi>Abraham</hi> called him ſonne; nor <hi>Judas</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> called him friend. <hi>Titles, when they are but titles, entitle to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55955:23"/>
               <p n="144">144. That preaching is moſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick, which is moſt like the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles preaching; when men come not with wiſdome of words, but with the words of wiſdom; when men come not with excellency of ſpeech, or entiſing words, to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and demonſtrate their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but in the evidence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the ſpirit, to evince Gods teaching; for then the faith of men wil ſtand not in the wiſdom of men, but in the power of God.</p>
               <p n="145">145. A form of godlineſſe and the power of ſin may dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the power of godlineſſe and a form of ſin cannot dwel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, much leſſe the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the power of ſin.</p>
               <p n="146">146. A gracious heart can truly ſay, though I am not what I would be, yet I would be what I ſhould be.</p>
               <p n="147">147. Whom God predeſtinates them he juſtifies, and not one more; and whom he juſtifies and glorifies,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55955:23"/>he did predeſtinate, and not one leſſe.</p>
               <p n="148">148. Though God give us never ſo much, he hath never the leſſe; and how much ſoever we give him he hath never the more.</p>
               <p n="149">149. The ſalvation of man, and the means to attain it, is not only Gods deſigne, but Gods work; <hi>'tis not onely his will that it ſhould be ſo, but 'tis his work that it is ſo:</hi> he doth not only wil that we ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but he doth ſave us; he doth not onely wil that we ſhould be juſtified, but he doth juſtifie us.</p>
               <p n="150">150. At the Supper of the Lord 'tis not man that offers Jeſus Chriſt to God, but God that offers Jeſus Chriſt to man; and therefore by way of thankfulneſſe man ſhould offer up himſelfe to God.</p>
               <p n="151">151. Did wee account of the things of this world as things that we muſt account for in the world to come, we ſhould uſe them, if not leſſe, yet better.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:55955:24"/>
               <p n="152">152. The loweſt thoughts wee have of our ſelves, are not low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; and the higheſt we have of God, are not high enough.</p>
               <p n="153">153. At ſuch times when Gods diſpenſations are doubtfull, mens diſputations about them are full of doubts.</p>
               <p n="154">154. A Saint prayeth that God wil not ſuffer him to take any work in hand but what he wil proſper, and then prayes God to proſper the work he takes in hand.</p>
               <p n="155">155. Many men doe by their Religion as Tradeſmen doe by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation; never goe about it, but when they have nothing elſe to do; give God that time which they know not how elſe to beſtow. Men put off God with any thing, yea with nothing. Offer it to thy Prince, and wil he accept it? we give him but the dregs, when the ſpirit is his due; we would not be ſerved as we ſerve him: we would have God give us the beſt, and we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55955:24"/>
                  <hi>(alas!)</hi> we give him the worſt. <hi>How unjuſt is this!</hi> Lord, I have nothing good enough for thee; my beſt is too bad, mine all is too little; ſuch as I am and have, I give unto thee; the Lord accept it.</p>
               <p n="156">156. 'Tis little leſſe then a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how ſome perſons can be ſo wicked in good families, and how others can be ſo good in wicked families.</p>
               <p n="157">157. When a Saint is fit for a change, and a change fit for a Saint, (whether it relate to place, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or imployment) it ſhal then be: and who would have it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore?</p>
               <p n="158">158. There are many perſons of good quality, who yet <hi>(the more is the pitty)</hi> are perſons of bad, very bad qualities.</p>
               <p n="159">159. If many that ſeek to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven ſhall not be able, what will become of them that doe not ſeek? not any of them ſhall enter; if ſeeking wil not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55955:25"/>ſerve the turn, ſtrive then to enter, put all your ſtrength to it, for ſtraight, very ſtraight is the gate; and narrow, very narrow is the way that leadeth unto life, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <p n="160">160. If God be with us, it matters not who be againſt us, <hi>it will goe well;</hi> but if God be againſt us, it matters not who be with us, <hi>it will goe ill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="161">161. Men many times wil give no more, becauſe they have given ſomething already; but God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his having once given, an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to give again: hee ſhewes mercy, becauſe he hath ſhewn mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and doth good, becauſe he hath done good. Heretofore-mercies are <hi>(to Saints)</hi> good ground of hope for hereafter-mercies.</p>
               <p n="162">162. He that looſeth an hundred pound in the fleſh, and getteth a thouſand pound in the ſpirit, is a gainer by his loſſe: who would not change for the better? who would
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55955:25"/>not become a foole that he may be wiſe? who would not become poor to enrich himſelfe? if a man loſe any thing for Chriſt, he ſhall loſe nothing by Chriſt, he ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid in kind, or <hi>(which is all one, nay which is better)</hi> in kindneſs.</p>
               <p n="163">163. Our ſuperfluities ſhould give way to our brothers conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, and our conveniences to our brothers neceſſities, yea even our neceſſities ſhould give way to their extremity for the ſupplying of them.</p>
               <p n="164">164. A babe in Chriſt is a ſmall thing, yet 'tis no ſmall thing to be a babe, though but a babe in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="165">165. Men ſhould not glory in what they have received, but give glory for what they have received: not onely the talent, but the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the talent is to be attributed to God, <hi>Lord thy pound hath gained ten pound,</hi> Luke 19.16. not onely faith to work, but the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55955:26"/>work of faith; not onely grace, but the actings of grace is to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the glory of God, and not to the power or praiſe of man.</p>
               <p n="166">166. To be evil at good is bad, but to be good at evil is worſe: they are wiſe to doe evil, but to do good they have no knowledge.</p>
               <p n="167">167. While we have any thing to give, and any thing to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, we ſhould be willingly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable.</p>
               <p n="168">168. Adverſity indeed is the more grievous, but proſperity is the more dangerous condition to the ſons of men.</p>
               <p n="169">169. Some ſpeak but little to the purpoſe, others ſpeak but to little purpoſe; Now <hi>as the proverbe ſaith,</hi> as good not at all, as to no purpoſe, or not to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="170">170. God ſpeaks much in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and man ſpeaks but a little in much.</p>
               <p n="171">171. Chriſt was delivered for our ſins, that we might be delivered from our ſins.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:55955:26"/>
               <p n="172">172. A Saint prayeth that he may not be willing to doe any thing which God wils not; and that he may not be unwilling to doe any thing, but willing to do every thing which God wils.</p>
               <p n="173">173. Sorrows lie heavier then ſin on the wicked, but on the godly ſin lieth heavier then ſorrows.</p>
               <p n="174">174. A Saint is more ſorry that he ſhould be diſcontented at any diſappointment, then that he ſhould be diſappointed of any content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or that which we call ſo, <hi>for there is no ſuch thing under the Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="175">175. Many men act grace, when yet grace is not acted; they act hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and ſelf-denial, when humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſelf-deniall are not acted; they doe like <hi>Stage-players,</hi> appeare and make ſhew of another thing then they are: this is the art of grace, rather then the act of grace; and <hi>ſuch perſons are but artificiall Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:55955:27"/>
               <p n="176">176. A believer is beholding to God for the Chriſt which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, and holds by faith; and for the faith whereby he beholds and holds the Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="177">177. Worldly ſorrow breakes hearts, but godly ſorrow heales broken hearts.</p>
               <p n="178">178. Though Chriſt free us from ſin, yet not from ſorrow; hee frees us from the ſin we ſorrow for, but not from the ſorrowing for the ſin he frees us from.</p>
               <p n="179">179. Chriſt is the Son of God, and therefore beloved, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. we are beloved, and therefore the ſons of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p n="180">180. If thou repent with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, God will pardon thee with a contradiction; if thou repent and not reform, <hi>that's repentance with a contradiction;</hi> God wil pardon thee, but ſend thee to hell, <hi>that's a pardon with a contradiction.</hi> Oh be not deceived, God is not mocked.</p>
               <p n="181">181. 'Tis more comfortable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55955:27"/>doctrine to heare that ſome ſhall be ſaved, <hi>as the doctrine of election tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth;</hi> then to heare that its uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whether any ſhall be ſaved, <hi>as the doctrine of free will teacheth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="182">182. The love of God doth not know what 'tis to be idle, and idlers doe not know what 'tis to love God.</p>
               <p n="183">183. A man need not feare nor doubt to ſay, that there is a partial hypocriſie in ſome men at all times, and in all men at ſome times.</p>
               <p n="184">184. They that feare not God and his greatneſſe here, will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of God and his greatneſſe hereafter.</p>
               <p n="185">185. God loves them that love him, and they that ſeek him ſhall finde him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.17. and yet there are ſome who ſhall ſeek him early, but that <hi>early</hi> wil be too late to finde him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.28.</p>
               <p n="186">186. God can ſupply the abſence of any, <hi>yea of all</hi> creatures; but not any, <hi>no not all</hi> the creatures can
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55955:28"/>ſupply the abſence of God.</p>
               <p n="187">187. Though wee are leſſe then the leaſt of all Gods mercies, yet he thinketh not the beſt to be too good for us; <hi>he neither ſpared to ſend his Son, nor ſpared his Son when he ſent him,</hi> but gave him up to death, yea it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him. <hi>This is love!</hi> Oh what a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation, what a commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of love is this! and how ſhall he not with him <hi>as freely</hi> give us all things?</p>
               <p n="188">188. We may ſay that we know no reaſon why we ſhould have ſo many mercies; <hi>and the reaſon is,</hi> becauſe mercy goeth not by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but by grace: and God ſheweth mercy, when, where, and becauſe he will; and that not becauſe the creature, but the mercy pleaſeth him.</p>
               <p n="189">189. Children is ſometimes a name common to all the Saints, to all the ſons and daughters of God; and thus a Babe-ſaint is a child, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55955:28"/>among the children; and a Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaint is but a child, and among the children: but ſometime the name is appropriated to a certain ſort and ſize of Saints; ſo that it may be truly ſaid, <hi>all that are born of God are children, but all that are born of God are not children as ſoon as they are born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="190">190. It was once ſaid of one, <hi>Oh that thy body proſpered as thy ſoule proſpereth;</hi> but it may be often ſaid of many, <hi>Oh that thy ſoule did proſper as thy body proſpers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="191">191. There are many that make good profeſſions, but few that make their profeſſions good, or make good their profeſſions.</p>
               <p n="192">192. If God were at mans diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, what a God would he be! and if man were not at Gods diſpoſe, what a man <hi>(poore miſerable man)</hi> would he be!</p>
               <p n="193">193. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith that the Chriſtians did ſo ſup as if they were to pray, they did it with ſuch
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55955:29"/>vvatchfulneſſe and heavenly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedneſſe: <hi>a good example</hi> for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in our daies, who pray as if they ſup'd with very ſupine and careleſs ſpirits.</p>
               <p n="194">194. If love finde fault, 'tis that there may be no fault to be found: God <hi>on this ground</hi> findes fault with his people, that his people may be without faults.</p>
               <p n="195">195. They are <hi>two choice mercies:</hi> 1. To have a broken heart for ſin. 2. To have the heart broken off from ſin.</p>
               <p n="196">196. How little doe wee make of much mercy, and how much doe wee make of a little miſery! <hi>how little doe we doe for much mercy, and how great and much adoe doe we make about a little miſery!</hi> A little miſery afflicts us much, and much mercy affects us but little.</p>
               <p n="196">196. God hath <hi>two dwelling pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> the higheſt heavens, and the loweſt hearts; <hi>that's</hi> the habitation of his glory, <hi>this</hi> of his grace.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55955:29"/>
               <p n="198">198. The Son of God became the ſon of man, <hi>that</hi> the ſons of men might become the ſons of God.</p>
               <p n="199">199. If we be juſt and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in confeſſing the ſins we would have forgiven, God will be juſt and faithfull in forgiving the ſins we confeſſe.</p>
               <p n="200">200. If men will not doe what grace will have them doe, grace will not doe what men would have it doe; if men will not ſubmit to graces teaching, men ſhall never enjoy graces ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="century">
               <head>The third Century.</head>
               <p n="201">201. To be without many ſins, is the holineſſe on Earth; to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſin, is the holineſſe of Heaven.</p>
               <p n="202">202. The things of this world are <hi>(and who would love ſuch things as are)</hi> ever wheeling; he that was upmoſt but even now, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55955:30"/>undermoſt, as <hi>Haman;</hi> and he that was undermoſt is upmoſt, as <hi>Mordecai:</hi> truſt not then to greatneſſe, for <hi>no man is ſo fixed, but he may fall;</hi> deſpiſe no mans meaneſſe, for <hi>none is ſo low, but he may riſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="203">203. When <hi>Diogenes</hi> heard <hi>Zeno</hi> with ſubtile arguments endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to prove that there was no motion, he ſuddenly ſtarts up and walkes; <hi>Zeno</hi> asking the cauſe thereof, ſaid <hi>Diogenes,</hi> Hereby I confute you, and prove that there is motion. <hi>Walking with God is the beſt way to confute them that think religion to be but a notion;</hi> walking will prove motion.</p>
               <p n="204">204. When we are doing Gods buſineſſe, we ſhould forget our own; our eyes and hearts ſhould be fixed only on him: when we goe to heare, we ſhould not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our eyes, but our eares. <hi>O Lord</hi> pardon the many wanton glances, vain thoughts, wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55955:30"/>eyes and deſires, yea the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deſignes of many, that goe to Sermons, not to hear the Word, but to ſee their Miſtreſſe.</p>
               <p n="205">205. He that's ſure of Gods love to him, is ſure of Gods power for him; what good cannot God doe when he will? and what good will he not doe for them to whom he bears good wil? <hi>They that know his name, may well truſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="206">206. 'Tis not yet with us as well as it ſhould be, if <hi>(though it be ill with us)</hi> we be not content with what we are: for we ſhould learn in all eſtates to be content.</p>
               <p n="207">207. If a man be not converted, he may thank himſelfe; but if he be converted, hee muſt thank God: that he is not converted is from <hi>mans free ill-will:</hi> that he is converted, is from <hi>Gods free good will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="208">208. Religion allows none to be idle; he that will not labour, muſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55955:31"/>not eat; in Religion, as well as any calling elſe, we muſt work for our living: God hath not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to work for them that play. <hi>He is not like to be ſaved, that doth not like to work out his ſalvation.</hi> He that is found a faithfull and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing ſervant, will finde a Well done good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into thy Maſters joy; but of the wicked, ſlothful, and unprofitable ſervant 'tis ſaid, Caſt ye him into utter darkneſſe.</p>
               <p n="209">209. If <hi>Eſau</hi> were ſo much to blame to ſell his birthright for a meſs of Pottage, <hi>which yet was to ſave his life;</hi> how much more are they to blame that <hi>Ahab-like</hi> ſell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to work wickedneſſe, that for a title of Honour, eſteem of men, or for a little white and yellow duſt, which is called Gold and Silver, <hi>(meere vanities)</hi> will ſell their ſouls? alas theſe ticklings will turn into ſtings, and the torment will be the more torment, the more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55955:31"/>the ſin was. 'Twill be but cold comfort for any man to goe to Hell with credit; or that others thinke him gone to Heaven, when he feeles himſelfe in Hell.</p>
               <p n="210">210. 'Tis good to be prepared for that at all times, which may come at any time, <hi>viz.</hi> death: if it come unſent for, yet it ſhould not come unlookt for. <hi>Setting a mans houſe and heart in order, will not make a man die the ſooner: 'twill help a man to die the better.</hi> Hee that when he comes to die hath nothing to doe but to die, may well beg to be diſſolved, for hee can ſay, I am ready to be offered, if the time of my departure be at hand.</p>
               <p n="211">211. A bad great man is a great bad man: for the greatneſſe of an evill man makes the mans evill the greater; ſuch a man will have many ſins to anſwer for which he never committed, becauſe his committing of one made many
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55955:32"/>others to commit many, who haply had never done ſo, had they not been led by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their leaders. <hi>If we take not heed,</hi> other men may have cauſe to be ſorry for our ſins, and we have cauſe to be ſorry for other mens ſins; for they may become <hi>our-other-mens</hi> ſins.</p>
               <p n="212">212. Some men are kind to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but for their own ends, and when they have once attained the end for which they were kind, there's an end of their kindneſſe; <hi>they will ſerve you for their needs, and when you have ſerved their needs, you ſhall obſerve that they will neither ſerve nor obſerve you any longer.</hi> Alas, doe not men ſerve God thus! doth not <hi>rich Jacob</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to pay what <hi>poor Jacob</hi> did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe?</p>
               <p n="213">213. Some men have much to uſe, who make but little uſe of what they have.</p>
               <p n="214">214. Were we as loving as God
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55955:32"/>is lovely, how (Oh how) infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould we love him!</p>
               <p n="215">215. To ſome <hi>(as to Dives)</hi> death is the end of all comfort, and the beginning of all miſery; to others <hi>(as to Lazarus)</hi> death is the end of all miſery, and the beginning of all comfort. <hi>Lord,</hi> let my condition be ſuch, that at death I may paſſe from torment to comfort, and not from comfort to torment.</p>
               <p n="216">216. Every man loves to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and is apt to take pleaſure in this, that others take pleaſure in him; whence that which ought not, doth oft come to paſſe, men comply with mens humours, and that they may not be thought unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil will ſin for company, and to pleaſe others, diſpleaſe God. <hi>Oh Lord,</hi> let me never ceaſe to be a good Chriſtian, that I may be thought a good companion. Let me chuſe rather with <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer reproaches, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55955:33"/>go to priſon with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> then to live a Laplin to the luſt of the eye and the pride of life, or to be lull'd and huſht aſleep by the fawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of this worlds flattery; <hi>Let it be enough to me to bee beloved of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="217">217. Whatever talent, indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or eſtate God hath given thee, improve it not for thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but to pleaſe him; <hi>not to honour thy ſelfe, but to henour him;</hi> for if he have not the glory, thou wilt have the ſhame, and cry out at laſt, <hi>Ino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem me copia fecit,</hi> Oh that I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been rich, my riches have made me poore; Oh that I had never been faire, my beauty made me proud and wanton; Oh that I had never been learned and witty, my wit hath made me a fool: <hi>abuſed good turnes to the greateſt evil.</hi> Let not therefore the wiſe man glory in his wiſdome, nor the rich man in his riches, but let him that glorieth glory in this, that he knoweth and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55955:33"/>loveth, ſerveth and honoureth God.</p>
               <p n="218">218. Hee that promiſeth what hee cannot doe, is a fooliſh man; and he that promiſeth what he meanes not to doe, is a falſe man; the firſt deceives others moſt, the latter deceives himſelf moſt; and he that promiſeth what he may not doe, is while courteous to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, cruel to himſelf; while a friend to another, an enemy to his own ſoul.</p>
               <p n="219">219. A man may meditate of good, and yet his meditation may be evil; and a man may meditate of evil, and yet his meditation may be good: <hi>'Tis good to meditate of good to doe it, and of evil not to doe it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="220">220. If it be good for us to draw neere to God, Oh how good is it when God drawes neer to us!</p>
               <p n="221">221. 'Tis good that a man ſhould wait for God, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.26. for God is good to them that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55955:34"/>wait for him, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.25.</p>
               <p n="222">222. 'Tis better to ſpend ones time in doing good, then in getting goods; for the goods we get we muſt leave, but the good we doe will never leave us: <hi>When we reſt from our labour, our workes ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="223">223. God ſtands in no need of us, for he is bleſſed without us; but we ſtand in need of God, for we cannot be bleſſed without him. <hi>Oh the gracious condeſcenſion of God!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="224">224. If a man cannot be rich with honeſty, he ſhould be content to be poor; for 'tis better to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue poore with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then to grow rich with a bad one.</p>
               <p n="225">225. He that truly deſires hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joyes, or the joyes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which ſhall never have an end, cannot but deſire to have an end of earthly joyes which are but for a ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="226">226. 'Tis great reaſon that we
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55955:34"/>ſhould continue to pray, becauſe ourwants continue; and 'tis as great reaſon that wee ſhould continue to praiſe, becauſe our mercies continue. Who is there ſo full, that wants nothing? and who ſo empty, but hath ſomething? <hi>Let none give over praying, but hee that wants nothing; and let none give over praiſing, that hath any thing.</hi> Is not the mercy we want worth the asking? and is not the mercy we have worth the acknowledging? <hi>'tis ſin and miſery to give over duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="227">227. Hee can be no friend to thee, that is a friend to thy faults; and thou canſt be no friend to thy ſelfe, if thou be an enemy to him that tels thee of thy faults. <hi>Wilt thou like him the worſe that would have thee be better?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="228">228. Chriſt hath commanded us to love our enemies, and to doe good for evill; which if we doe not, we wrong our ſelves more by not doing good to them <hi>(for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55955:35"/>that's our ſin)</hi> then they did by doing us wrong, <hi>for that was but our affliction:</hi> and the evil of ſin is worſe then the evill of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</p>
               <p n="229">229. Some men doe well, and ſay nothing, according to the rule of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.1.-4. others ſay well, and doe nothing, according to the Phariſees, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.3.</p>
               <p n="230">230. 'Tis ſtrange to ſee how the Kingdom of ſin is divided, and yet ſtands; <hi>there are divers Iuſts;</hi> luſts that differ and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree, as covetouſneſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality. <hi>Poore ſinners!</hi> what an hard taske have they that ſerve divers luſts? <hi>that like Tapſters and Drawers muſt anſwer all:</hi> if pride call, here Sir; if luſt call, anon Sir; if covetouſneſſe call, I come Sir; how can, and yet how doth the ſame ſinner ſerve theſe ſeverall maſters? <hi>ſad caſe when men are rul'd by unruly luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:55955:35"/>
               <p n="231">231. To refuſe Jeſus Chriſt, and the tenders of grace and mercy by him, is the ſhorteſt way to Hell; ſome men ride the rode, the high way to Hell, while they drinke, ſweare, lye, whore away their ſoules; but they that re fuſe Chriſt Jeſus, run by way of the plaine, they make a ſhorter cut; <hi>while others goe by the bow, theſe goe by the ſtring:</hi> Lord, what haſte do men make, and what pains doe men take to damne themſelves!</p>
               <p n="232">232. Its better to beg ones bread with <hi>Lazarus</hi> on earth, then to beg ones water with <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves</hi> in Hell. <hi>Better to be tormented with ſores in this world, then to be ſorely tormented in the world to come.</hi> Better to goe from <hi>Lives</hi> doore to <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, then from <hi>Dives</hi> Table to the Divels Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon.</p>
               <p n="233">233. Some men lend, looking for nothing again; <hi>ſuch lending is giving:</hi> others give, looking for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55955:36"/>ſomething again; <hi>ſuch giving is but lending:</hi> others give and lend, for he that giveth to the poore, lendeth to the Lord; <hi>this is putting to uſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out uſury;</hi> this is laying up by laying out.</p>
               <p n="234">234. Many men doe in words confeſs God, who do in works deny God; ſuch men ſhall not be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by their words, but by their works. Satans condemnation will not be the leſſe that he quoted Scripture, and called Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, that he believes, &amp; trembles, and is tranſformed into an Angel of light: nor will it fare the better, <hi>but be far the worſe</hi> with ſuch men as have had a form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and denied the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſeeing they have held the truth in unrighteouſneſſe; 'twil profit nothing to have been a profeſſor of piety, ſeeing they were workers of iniquity: Nay, <hi>their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be the greater,</hi> for ſaying, I goe Sir, but went not. Oh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55955:36"/>if godlineſſe be good, why wilt not practiſe it? if it be evill, why wilt profeſſe it? if thou wilt name the Name of the Lord, depart from iniquity, for what elſe haſt thou <hi>(thou bold brazen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced ſinner)</hi> what haſt thou to doe to take Gods Name into thy mouth, and hateſt to be reformed? Think on this ye that forget God, leſt he teare you in pieces, and there be none to deliver.</p>
               <p n="234">234. <hi>Times Redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis dangerous putting of that to another day, which muſt be done to day, or thou maiſt be undone to morrow. <hi>Now or never, now or never;</hi> if it be not done now, it may never be done, and then thou art undone for ever: <hi>Eternity depends on this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The work thou haſt to doe (viz. <hi>working out thy ſalvation</hi>) is great, thy life at longeſt is but ſhort, and thou canſt call no time thine, but the preſent time. I have read
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55955:37"/>of one <hi>Archias a Lacedemonian,</hi> that while hee was quaffing and ryot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, one delivers him a letter, to ſignifie to him that ſome layd in wait to take his life, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to read it preſently, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas a ſerious buſineſſe; Oh ſaid hee, <hi>ſeria cras,</hi> we will thinke of ſerious things to morrow; but that night he was ſlain. <hi>Oh boaſt not of to morrow, thou knowest not what a day may bring forth:</hi> Why wilt thou talke of many yeeres, when this night thy ſoule may be taken from thee. <hi>Oh what wouldſt thou give for a day, when it may be a day too late.</hi> Conſider therefore in this thy day, to day while 'tis called to day, the things of thy peace, leſt they ſhould he hid from thine eyes, and while thou like a blind Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite doſt grope to finde a doore of hope, fire and brimſtone rain about thine eares.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:55955:37"/>
               <p n="235">235. <hi>Clean contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many men inſtead of uſing the world as if they uſed it not, uſe the things of God as if they uſed them not; when as they ſhould ſerve God and but make uſe of the world, they ſerve the world and doe but make uſe of God; <hi>they doe not love theſe things for Gods ſake, but God for theſe things ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="236">236. <hi>A Part no Portion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The great fallacy with which Satan deſudes many men, is that Logicians call <hi>à bene compoſitis ad male diviſa;</hi> when he gets them to take Religion into peeces and then takes one peece for religion: one cries up Chriſt, another Faith, another love, another good works: but what is God without Chriſt, or Chriſt without faith, and what is faith without love, and what is love without workes? but now, take God in Chriſt by faith which worketh by love and keepeth the commandements of God, this is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55955:38"/>
                  <hi>pure religion.</hi> 'Tis the whole that is the whole of man.</p>
               <p n="237">237. <hi>The new Command.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The command of loving one another, is not <hi>called new</hi> as to the thing to be done, for that was from the beginning, but <hi>as to the manner of doing it,</hi> or the rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which it is to be done. Formerly 'twas love thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelfe, <hi>(there ſelfe-love was the rule)</hi> but here 'tis love one another as I have loved you <hi>(here Chriſts love is the rule)</hi> we ſhould love one another better then we did, becauſe Chriſt loves us better then we our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="238">238. <hi>Greater condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſinning againſt the light of Gods workes had ſo great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, Rom. 1. how great a condemnation will be to them that ſinne againſt the light of Gods words? <hi>and if the law condemned much, the goſpell much more;</hi> for if they eſcaped not, but dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:55955:38"/>mercy, who finned againſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> him that ſpake on earth, much more ſhall not they eſcape, but are worthy of a ſorer puniſhment, who neglect the great ſalvation, and refuſe him that ſpeaks from Heaven, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="239">239. <hi>The Sinner ſpeechleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No man can give any reaſon why he ſhould ſin againſt God; if God ſhould ask men, as he did the man that had not on the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment, <hi>Why cameſt thou bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a wedding garment?</hi> So, why art thou proud? and thou wanton? and thou unclean? and thou covetous, and thou drunk, and why doſt thou ſwear, &amp;c? Men would be as he, that is, <hi>ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe;</hi> they could give no reaſon, for indeed there is no reaſon to give. One may ſay to ſinners as <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſaid to <hi>Huſhai.</hi> is <hi>this</hi> thy kindneſſe to thy friend? Doe ye <hi>thus</hi> requite the Lord, O fooliſh people and unwiſe? What ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55955:39"/>have your fathers, <hi>may God ſay,</hi> or you found in me? What can you lay to my charge? Am not I a lovely and a loving God? Can any bid more for your love then I? Can any doe more for you then I? If you can ſpeed better, and mend your market, go away and leave me; if not, why will ye ſpend your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfieth not? <hi>If you can finde no fault with me, why will you commit ſuch a fault as to leave me?</hi> What cauſe have you to ſay, We will not come to thee? Is it a crime to feed you? Is it a crime to clothe you? Is it a crime to preſerve you? Is it a crime to ſend my Son into the world to ſave you? Is it a crime to beſeech and beg you <hi>(as for an almes)</hi> that you would be reconciled, and be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py? <hi>forgive me this wrong.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be aſtoniſhed, O Heavens, at this, and be horribly afraid, <hi>Jer.</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:55955:39"/>2.11, 12, 13. Why? Whats the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? <hi>the matter!</hi> 'tis this, <hi>My peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have committed two evils, they have forſaken me without a cauſe, and have changed their glory for that which doth not profit.</hi> Oh ſinners, let me ſay to you, as <hi>Saul</hi> to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.7. Hear now ye <hi>Benjamites,</hi> will the ſon of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> give every one of you Fields and Vineyards, and make you Captains of thouſands? <hi>Oh poor Souls,</hi> will ſin, will Satan, will the world give you Heaven and Eternal life? Why will you be ſo unreaſonable to ſin againſt God, and wrong your own ſouls? Oh hear, and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly.</p>
               <p n="240">240. <hi>Come and ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſight <hi>(one ſight)</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt doth more raviſh and overcome a ſoul, then all the reports that can be made of him; <hi>the tongue of men and Angels cannot ſet him forth ſo lively and lovely as a poor ſoul findes him.</hi> Who can believe honey to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55955:40"/>be ſo ſweet, as he that hath taſted it knows it to be? the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> wonder at the daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> when ſick of love, and ſay, What is thy beloved, more then another beloved? Why ſo fond? <hi>Oh ſayes the ſoul,</hi> his mouth is moſt ſweet, yea, he is all deſires —althogether lovely; this is my beloved, this, Oh this is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. When poor creatures come to know him as by himſelf made known to them in his beauty, they then ſay as <hi>John</hi> 4.42. we believe not becauſe of thy ſaying, for we our ſelves have heard him, and know <hi>(aſſuredly)</hi> that this is indeed the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world; yea, they ſay as the <hi>Queen of Sheba</hi> ſaid of, and unto <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.5. (Oh Lord) for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a greater then <hi>Solomon</hi> is here, and therefore let me ſay, <hi>Oh Lord</hi>) ſince I ſaw thy wiſdome, and the houſe that thou haſt built, and the meat of thy Table, and the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55955:40"/>ſitting of thy ſervants, and the attendants of thy Miniſters, and their apparel, &amp;c. there is no more ſpirit in me—to ſay the reſt. Ah 'twas a true report that I heard of thee, when I (poor I) was in mine own (ſelf) Countrey, but I believed not the words, till I came, (oh happy coming) and mine eyes (oh bleſt eyes) had ſeen it: and behold the half was not, no not the half was told me; thou exceedeſt, abundantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeſt the report which I heard. <hi>Happy thy men! happy thy ſervants, which ſtand continually before thee, to hear thy wiſdome, which is able to make wiſe unto ſalvation!</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord thy God which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in thee <hi>(in thee is he well pleaſed)</hi> to ſet thee on the throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom he loved for ever. Oh Lord <hi>ſaith the ſoul,</hi> help me to give, but what? Silver and Gold? Alas, what's an hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty talents of Gold? and of Spices
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:55955:41"/>very great ſtore? and precious ſtones, though as many as the ſand of the Sea? <hi>No, Lord,</hi> 'tis mine heart, ſuch as 'tis, that I would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, for indeed thou haſt raviſh'd me with one of thine eyes: Take it, Lord, 'tis wholly thine, Oh that not a vain thought might lodge in it any more; ſhall it be thus, Lord? then awake my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and thou my ſoul, and all that is within me praiſe the Lord, and bleſſe his holy name. What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and among all, <hi>for that,</hi> for that which is the worth of all, and more worth then all the reſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Herb.</bibl>
                  <l>—<hi>I will doe for that,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alas! my God, I know not what.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But though I cannot fully pay the ſhot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let me not love thee, if I love thee not.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let all the glory of my glory be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To give all glory and my ſelf to thee.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:55955:41"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This is too little, more is due,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I cann't requite it, Lord, 'tis true.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p n="241">241. When a poor ſoul conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders what God hath done for him, in admitting him into communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with himſelf, to eat bread at his Table continually, he cries out (even weeping for admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.8. What is thy ſervant, that thou ſhouldeſt look on ſuch a dead dog as I am! <hi>Such a God, on ſuch a dog!</hi> And when he conſiders from what a low, to what an high eſtate God hath brought him, he ſaith as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Gen.</hi> 32.10. I am leſſe then the leaſt of all thy mercies, and of all the truth which thou haſt ſhewn me, for with my ſtaffe I went over this <hi>Jordan,</hi> and now I am become two bands. And when Jeſus Chriſt tells a ſoul, that he will make him a King, and a Prieſt to God, he humbly ſaith as <hi>Saul to Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.21. Am not I a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55955:42"/>
                  <hi>Benjamite,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the ſmalleſt of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And my family the leaſt of all the families of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin?</hi> Ah Lord, wherefore ſpeakeſt thou ſo to me? Yea, it ſayes as <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> ſaid to <hi>Mary,</hi> the bleſſed Mother of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Jeſus, when ſhe heard the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation, that the babe <hi>(the heart of a poor believer)</hi> leapt within her, and ſhe ſpake, yea, ſhe ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud; Bleſſed, yea bleſſed art thou, whence! <hi>Oh whence is this to me,</hi> that the Mother of my Lord (Oh ſaith the ſoul, that my God) ſhould come to ſee me, even me, poor worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe me! That it fares with them as with them, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.36--42. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſtood in the midſt, and ſaid, Peace be unto you; and they were terrified and affrighted: but he ſaid, Why are ye troubled? it is I; behold my hands and my feet, and <hi>they believed not for joy and wondred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="242">242. <hi>Devils incarnate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perſecuters are called Devils,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:55955:42"/>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. and as they do the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils work, they ſhall have the Devils wages; <hi>they caſt Gods Saints into priſon, and the Saints God will caſt them into priſon,</hi> into an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting priſon and dungeon of outer darkneſſe, unleſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Chriſt will ſay to them at laſt, <hi>as</hi> Gideon <hi>ſaid to</hi> Zeba <hi>and</hi> Zalmunna, <hi>Judges</hi> 8.18, 19. what manner of men were they, whom you ſlew at <hi>Tabor?</hi> and they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, as thou art, ſo were they, each one reſembled the child of a King: then will Chriſt reply as <hi>Gideon,</hi> they were my brethren, the ſons of my father, as the Lord liveth, had you feared me, and ſaved them alive, I would not ſlay you, I would not damn you; but now, away to priſon, away to Hell. Woe <hi>(this woe)</hi> to him that offendeth one of Chriſt's lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones; it were better for him that a mill-ſtone were hung about his neck, and he caſt into ſea; I
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55955:43"/>far better then to be caſt into the bottomeleſſe pit of Hell.</p>
               <p n="243">243. <hi>The ſins of profeſſors quickly ripe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſins of a profeſſing people or Nation, are ſooner ripe, then the ſins of the wilde world, as fruit that growes more in the Sun, they are concocted and come to matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſooner: and therefore <hi>('tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable that)</hi> God bears longer with the world, yea, and (in a ſenſe) deals more gently in their puniſhment. The ſin of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morites</hi> was long (many years) ere it was full ripe; but <hi>Iſraels</hi> was ripe in forty years; and ſeeing they were known of any people of the Earth, therefore God will viſit upon them all their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that to their coſt, they ſhall more intenſely feel his wrath. <hi>How dear was this Iſrael unto God,</hi> by how many ſweet, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and precious appellations were they called? his people, his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:55955:43"/>ſpouſe, his treaſure, his Jewels, his darling, and <hi>yet God caſt them to the dogs.</hi> Oh how ſhould <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hear, and fear, and do no more ſo wickedly, leſt God make a quick diſpatch, and do as by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> remove the Candles and the Candleſticks out of their place.</p>
               <p n="244">244. <hi>The happy Adventure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a poore ſoul begins to be ſenſible of ſinne and its danger thereby, though it lye downe in ſorrow, yet it ſhould not mourne as without hopes; but reſolve as the <hi>Lepers.</hi> 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 7.3. to prefer <hi>(though an uncertaine)</hi> hope, before a certaine death. Say as they, why ſit we here untill we dye? if we enter into the City, the famine is there, and we ſhall certainely dye; if we ſit ſtill here, we dye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: now therefore come, let us fall <hi>(for the hoſt of the Syrians, let the poore ſoul ſay)</hi> into the hands of <hi>God,</hi> if he ſave us alive we ſhall live, if he kill us, we ſhall but dye.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55955:44"/>
                  <hi>Dye?</hi> Oh poore ſouls, never any came to <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but they were ſaved alive; Come to him then for he will not kill you, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he will not. Come to him and ſay as the <hi>Prodigall,</hi> when he came to himſelfe, how many hired ſervants of my <hi>Fathers</hi> have bread enough and to ſpare, and I periſh with hunger. <hi>I will ariſe and goe to my Father &amp;c.</hi> I, doe ſo, ariſe and goe, for there is hope in <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning this thing. See how his <hi>father</hi> had compaſſion on him, how he ran, how he fell on his necke, how he kiſt him, and bid him welcome home. <hi>Say then as Heſter</hi> c. 4.16. I will goe in unto the King, if I periſh, I periſh. What ſoul? periſh ſayſt thou? no, no, the <hi>Golden Scepter</hi> is held out, thou mayſt come and welcome. God will ſay as the King to <hi>Heſter,</hi> c. 5.3. What wilt thou, and what is thy requeſt? it ſhall be given thee, even to the Kingdom; whereupon <hi>Heſter</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:55955:44"/>made a feaſt for the King, but <hi>God</hi> will make a feaſt for thee: <hi>Doſt thou not heare what he ſaith: Luke</hi> 15.22. Bring forth the beſt robe, and put it on him, put a ring upon his hand, and ſhooes on his feet, Kill the fatted Calfe, let us eat and be merry, for this ſoul was dead and is alive, 'twas loſt, and is found; Oh who would not come to thee, thou, O thou lover of ſouls?</p>
               <p n="245">245. <hi>The ſmitting of Amalek.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Saint ſhould doe by his corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Saul</hi> was commiſſioned to doe by <hi>Amalek:</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. Goe and ſmite <hi>Amalek,</hi> and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory all that they have, and ſpare them not, but ſlay both Man and Woman, Infant and Suckling, Ox and ſheep, Cammel and Aſſe; yea he ſhould doe as <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> c. 8. v. 26. who withdrew not his hand untill he had utterly deſtroyed the inhabitants of <hi>Ai. He that's mercifull to ſinne is cruell to his owne ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:55955:45"/>
               <p n="246">246. <hi>Buſie-idleneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mans idle time is the Devils working time, he doth moſt when men do leaſt; for as <hi>Latimer</hi> ſaid, the Devil hath more ſervice done him in one holy-day, then in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny working-dayes.</p>
               <p n="247">247. <hi>The hypocritical deceitful pleaſures of ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The pleaſures of ſin ſay unto us, <hi>as</hi> Jael <hi>ſaid to</hi> Siſera, turn in my Lord, turn in to me, fear not; and if we ask water, they will give us milk, and bring forth butter in a Lordly diſh; but when we are turned in, they (<hi>as ſhe did</hi> Siſera) cover us with a Mantle, and finding us <hi>(by their lullings)</hi> to fall faſt aſleep, they put their hand to the nails, and their right hand to the workmans hammer, and with this hammer they ſmite us, piercing and ſtriking through our temples; at their feet we bow, we fall; where we bow, there we fall down dead, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.18, 19. with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:55955:45"/>5.25, 26, 27. their lips indeed drop like the honey-comb, and their mouth is ſmoother then oyl; <hi>but their end is bitter as wormwood,</hi> ſharp as a two-edged ſword, their feet go down to death, and their ſteps take hold on Hell, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5. with much fair ſpeech they cauſe us to yield, with the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their lips they force us, and little think we, that we go as an Oxe to the ſlaughter, and as a fool to the ſtocks, till a dart ſtrike through our liver, as a bird haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the ſnare, and knoweth not that 'tis for his life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p n="248">248. <hi>Not Heaven, but God in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Saint were in Heaven, and ſaw not Gods face there, he would ſay as <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joab,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.32. Wherefore am I come from <hi>Geſhur?</hi> it had been good for me to be there ſtill, unleſſe I may ſee the Kings face. Though Heaven
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:55955:46"/>be Gods dwelling place, yea, his Preſence-Chamber, yet a Saint could not be at reſt there, if he ſaw not God: 'tis not the Jaſper, nor the Chryſtal, 'tis not the pure Gold wherewith the ſtreets are paved, 'tis not the pearls, nor the precious ſtones that are precious in his ſight, but the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb, who are the light thereof: <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="249">249. <hi>God more then ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Saint cares not how ill it goe with him, ſo it goe well with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; he ſaith, as <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30. yea, let him take all, inaſmuch as my Lord the King is come again in peace unto his houſe. So it may goe well with Gods name, <hi>Moſes</hi> cares not though his be blotted out of the book of life: and ſaid <hi>John,</hi> he muſt increaſe, but I muſt decreaſe, this my joy therefore is fulfilled.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:55955:46"/>
               <p n="250">250. <hi>Little faith in the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman being told that the world and the glory of it was but vanity; 'tis true ſaid ſhe, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid ſo, but he tryed it firſt, and ſo will I. Alas, that we cannot take Gods word, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe till <hi>(nor ſcarce when)</hi> we ſee: the world bewitcheth us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will believe it to be a Witch; we believe it not to be poyſon, till we are poyſoned.</p>
               <p n="251">251. <hi>The cuſtome of the Countrey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath two daughters; the younger, which is Heaven, is fair and lovely, like <hi>Rachel,</hi> and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all; the elder is Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which (with tears) is blear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey'd, <hi>like Leah,</hi> and neglected by moſt: but if men ask, as <hi>Jacob</hi> for <hi>Rachel,</hi> God will anſwer as <hi>Laban</hi> did him, 'tis not <hi>mos loci,</hi> 'tis not the cuſtome of the place to marry the younger before the elder. <hi>He that will not marry the</hi> Leah <hi>of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:55955:47"/>ſhall never have the</hi> Rachel <hi>of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="252">252. <hi>Not my will, but thine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have heard of a good Woman, who when ſhe was ſick, being ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether ſhe were willing to live or dye; anſwered, <hi>which God pleaſeth;</hi> but ſaid one, if God ſhould referre it to you, which would you chuſe? truly ſaid ſhe, if God ſhould referre it to me, I would e'n referre it to him again.</p>
               <p n="253">253. <hi>Plain Preaching.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> Preaching one day very Scholaſtically, the Learned thankt him, but not the godly; but when another day he preacht plainly, the good people came bleſſing God for him, and gave him many thanks, which ſome Scholars wondring at; ah ſaid he, <hi>Heri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bernardum, hodie Chriſtum;</hi> yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day I preacht <hi>Bernard,</hi> but to day I preacht Chriſt; <hi>'tis not Learning, but teaching;</hi> not the wiſdome of words, but the evidence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55955:47"/>of the Spirit, that is welcome to Saints.</p>
               <p n="254">254. <hi>The leſſe of man, the more of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I can (<hi>ſaid Dr.</hi> Twiſſe <hi>of himſelf</hi>) take ſome pains in writing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, but I cannot take pains in making a Sermon; and when I have taken moſt, I finde that I have leſſe edified my people, though perhaps more pleaſed my ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis not mans explication, but Gods application of truth which edifies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="255">255. <hi>Savoury Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Salt is the firſt ſet on, and the laſt taken off the table, that every diſh from firſt to laſt maybe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned. <hi>May not the Apoſtle refer to this,</hi> when he ſaith, let your ſpeech be ſeaſon'd with Salt. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. Let it be Savory, ſuch as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to edifying. Can that which is unſavory be eaten without ſalt? or what taſt is there in the white of an egge? <hi>Sales</hi> without <hi>Sal,</hi> the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:55955:48"/>grace of ſpeaking without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of grace, or a grace in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without ſpeaking grace is but unſavory: would <hi>God</hi> our ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-talke might never want Salt.</p>
               <p n="256">256. <hi>Old men and Babes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath <hi>Saints</hi> of ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and ſiſes, and ſome of them have more <hi>Communion</hi> with him then others: from among the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude he choſe twelve to be with him, from among the twelve, he choſe three <hi>(Peter, Iames, and Iohn)</hi> which were <hi>è ſecretioribus</hi> of the privy councell, from among the three he choſe out <hi>Iohn</hi> as his peculiar darling and boſome favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, of whom it's ſaid <hi>five times,</hi> that he was the diſciple whom <hi>Ieſus</hi> loved. So now to this day, <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>his babes,</hi> who eat milk and nothing elſe; <hi>his Children,</hi> who know their <hi>Father</hi> and are aſſured of his love; <hi>his young men,</hi> who goe out to warre; and the <hi>Fathers in Iſrael</hi> whoſe <hi>gray-headed</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:55955:48"/>and <hi>wiſedome</hi> abounds: for they know him from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>'Tis a great mercy to be one of <hi>Gods,</hi> though but one of his little ones, yea the leaſt of all; to be a <hi>Starre,</hi> though not of the firſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude: to be a <hi>Diſciple</hi> though not a <hi>John,</hi> nor one of the three, nor one of the twelve, nor one of the ſeaventy. But to be a <hi>John,</hi> a dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to leane on his <hi>breaſt,</hi> to lye in his <hi>boſome, Oh how great a mercy!</hi> ti's mercy to be new borne, though one be but newly &amp; as one newly borne, but to grow up to a perfect Stature to be a man in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, Oh how great a mercy!</hi> Lord perfect all that which coneerns thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, yea, that which concerns all thy Servants.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:55955:49"/>
               <p n="257">257. <hi>A Dialogue between</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Abraham: Wherein is evinced
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Abraham's</hi> faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17, 18, 19.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Abraham's</hi> fear, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>He feared <hi>God,</hi> but was not afraid of God: <hi>His faith was all tryed, yet not at all tired,</hi> but rejoyced as a ſtrong man to run his race, which was the more to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if we conſider what <hi>ifs</hi> and <hi>ands,</hi> what put offs and objections, <hi>Abraham</hi> might have made, when God tempted <hi>Abraham</hi> and ſaid.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> my ſervant, my friend, where art thou? Come forth, attend to execute my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>To which he ſaid, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me,</hi> here I am, ſpeake <hi>Lord,</hi> for thy ſervant heareth, I am wholy at thy command and ſervice, doe with me and mine what ſeemeth thee good; If thou bid me go, I
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:55955:49"/>will go; and if thou bid me come, I will come; whatever thou bid'ſt me doe, I will doe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>Then God ſaid, <hi>Take now thy ſon, thine only ſon Iſaac, whom thou loveſt, and get thee to the land of Moriah, and offer him there for a burnt offering, upon one of the Mountaines which I will tell thee of.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>To this, he did not, but might have pleaded; why <hi>Lord,</hi> thou art bleſſed in thy ſelfe, and needeſt not any thing; thou deſireſt not ſacrifice, elſe would I give it thee, and thou delighteſt not in burnt offerings 'tis true, <hi>Lord, thy ſacrifices are a broken and contrite heart,</hi> and that I will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly offer, doe not deſpiſe but accept of that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſaieth <hi>God,</hi> offer thy ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord,</hi> If thou wilt have an offering, all my herds and flockes are at thy ſervice; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>(as long after this Araunah
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:55955:50"/>ſaid to David)</hi> here are Oxen for burnt ſacrifice, and threſhing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and other inſtruments for wood, all theſe things will I willingly give unto the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> my <hi>God</hi> accept it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſaith <hi>God,</hi> I will take no Bullocke out of thine houſe, nor he Goats out of thy fold, <hi>for every beaſt of the forreſt is mine,</hi> and the Cattell on a Thouſand hils; I know all the Fowles of the Mountaines, and the wild beaſts of the field are mine; if I were hungery I would not tell thee, for the world is mine and the fulneſſe thereof; will I eat the fleſh of Bulls, or drinke the blood of Goats? No, <hi>Abraham</hi> No, but offer thy ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord 'tis true, thou art above theſe, and he that offers thee praiſe honours thee; and therefore thou calleſt upon us, to offer unto <hi>God</hi> thankſgiving, and to pay our vowes to the moſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:55955:50"/>high; and <hi>Lord</hi> I am willing to pay my vowes in the great Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Accept of my thanks, and I will thanke thee the more;</hi> receive theſe <hi>Vowes</hi> as part of the debt, and I will vow and pay thee more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſaith <hi>God,</hi> Nothing but thy <hi>Son,</hi> offer, <hi>Abraham</hi> offer thy <hi>Son.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord,</hi> If thou wilt have the fleſh of man to be ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed, and his blood to be powred out, then take one of my ſervants, <hi>Doe not call my ſinnes to Remembrance and ſlay my ſon:</hi> good Lord ſpare my ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſaith God, offer up thy ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord if thou wilt have a ſon take <hi>Iſmael, Spare mine Iſaac, Lord</hi> ſpare mine Iſaac.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſaith God, take thy ſon even Iſaac.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>Lord, he is mine onely ſon, he hath not a Brother, nor are there any more in <hi>Sarahs</hi> wombe,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:55955:51"/>Lord, I begge <hi>onely this,</hi> ſpare mine onely ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſaith God, take thine <hi>onely</hi> ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Lord, I have had him but a little while; if thou wilt take him, yet good Lord, let mine <hi>Iſaac</hi> and I laugh together yet a while.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſaith God, take him <hi>now.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>But Lord, I love him, and ſo, that to take <hi>Iſaac</hi> is to take my life, <hi>which is bound up in the life of the lad;</hi> and if thou take him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, thou wilt bring down my gray hairs with ſorrow to the grave.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſaith God, I know thou loveſt him, but <hi>muſt you not love me better?</hi> offer up this ſon, this onely ſon, this <hi>Iſaac</hi> whom thou loveſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>But Lord, though thou art righteous when I plead with thee, yet let me talk with thee
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:55955:51"/>of thy Judgements. <hi>What will the wicked ſay,</hi> when they ſhall hear that thou delighteſt in blood? and that thy ſervants muſt offer their children unto thee; Lord, who will ſerve thee at this rate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſaith God, I take but mine own, and I may do with mine own what I pleaſe; I that give may take; and therefore <hi>minde not you what the world will ſay, but what I ſay;</hi> and I ſay, offer thy ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>But Lord, haſt thou not commanded me to do no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and muſt I now imbrue mine hands in blood? and in mine own blood too? <hi>Oh happy I, might my blood go for his!</hi> Oh <hi>Iſaac, Iſaac,</hi> my ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> my ſon, my ſon, <hi>would God I might die for thee,</hi> Oh <hi>Iſaac,</hi> my ſon, my ſon! Lord, how can this ſtand with the Law which thou haſt given me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>ſuch things are not firſt juſt, and then wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:55955:52"/>by me, but willed by me, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſt. Abraham,</hi> doe you not know that I can repeal, or make exceptions? <hi>'tis I that ſay it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe it.</hi> Who is this that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth counſel by words without knowledge? gird up now thy loins like a man, ſmite him, kill him; <hi>have not I commanded thee?</hi> be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and a ſon of valour, goe and offer thy ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>But good Lord, thou haſt made this exception, when thou didſt ſhew man what was good, and pleaſing in thine eyes, thou wouldeſt not that he ſhould give his firſt-born for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, <hi>nor the fruit of his body for the ſins of his ſoul,</hi> but to do juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with God; to obey <hi>(thou ſayeſt it)</hi> is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of rams.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then, ſaith God, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and obey, this is to do juſtice,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:55955:52"/>this is <hi>(Oh wonder)</hi> to ſhew mercy; this is to walk humbly with thy God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing I have taken upon me to ſpeak unto the Lord, <hi>I will yet ſay,</hi> Lord, he is the ſon of the promiſe, in whom <hi>(thou haſt ſaid that)</hi> all the nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed; now Lord, if he die, and die a childe without children, where then is the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe thou ſpakeſt of? what will become of the bleſſing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>Well <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>perform you what I command, and I will perform what I promiſe.</hi> What will <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was once not weak in faith, and conſidered not his own body, nor <hi>Sarah's,</hi> when 'twas dead, who ſtaggered not through unbelief at my promiſe, but was ſtrong in faith, and gave me glory, who was fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that what I had promiſed, I was able to perform, and was not diſappointed of his hope, though
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:55955:53"/>againſt hope; will this <hi>Abraham</hi> now call me in queſtion? <hi>haſt thou known my name, and wilt thou not truſt in me?</hi> am not I the Lord who change not? have I ſaid it, and ſhall it not come to paſſe? is there any thing too hard for God? am not I able to raiſe up even out of ſtones, to raiſe up children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham?</hi> Cannot I ſay to dry bones, live? thou haſt received him from the dead in a figure, and were <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the grave, could not I who am the reſurrection from the dead, ſay, <hi>Iſaac</hi> come forth? ariſe and walk, that thy father may receive thee with double joy, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Iſaac</hi> my ſon, who was dead, <hi>(yea, who was twice dead)</hi> is alive. <hi>Abraham,</hi> offer thy ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>My dear Lord, ſeeing I who am but duſt and aſhes, have taken upon me to ſpeak unto thee, Oh let not my Lord be angry, if I ſpeak once more. If I may not prevail to <hi>(Oh that I might prevail to)</hi>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:55955:53"/>ſave <hi>Iſaac</hi> alive, yet let me intreat thee, that I may not be the Prieſt, let not mine hand be upon him, <hi>how can I ſee the death of the childe!</hi> Good Lord, let ſome other doe it, ſurely I cannot lift up my hand, or if I doe, ſhall I not wiſh it may wither, or be turned into a ſtone? will not theſe eyes run down with rivers of tears? Ah, Lord, I can ſpeak no more, mine heart will break, mine hand will ſhake: Send by whom thou wilt ſend, let me, Oh let me not go.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes <hi>thou,</hi> take him <hi>thou,</hi> and goe <hi>thou,</hi> and offer him <hi>thou,</hi> none but <hi>thou.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abraham.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah Lord, yet once more, but this once more, and I have done. I am old and full of daies, <hi>paſt travail,</hi> ſpare me a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, let me not goe ſo far as the land of <hi>Moriah;</hi> let it (if it muſt be, let it) be done at home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>God.</speaker>
                  <p>No <hi>Abraham,</hi> take now thy ſon, thine onely ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:55955:54"/>whom thou loveſt, and get thee into the Land of <hi>Moriah,</hi> and offer him <hi>there,</hi> no where but <hi>there.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>Thus you have ſeen, <hi>if not a faith of Miracles, yet a Miracle of faith,</hi> that one who had ſo much, and more to ſay, ſhould ſay nothing, but riſe up early in the morning (after he had ſlept upon it, <hi>if ſleep he could</hi>) and ſaddle his aſſe, and take two of his young men, and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> his ſon, and cleave the wood, and riſe up and goe to the place; and leſt he ſhould be interrupted by his ſervants, he left them with the aſſes, and laies the wood upon his ſon, his ſon <hi>Iſaac, (he muſt bear his croſſe)</hi> and when this innocent ſoul, this Lamb did open his mouth (not to complain) but to ask for another, he tells him, (<hi>could</hi> Abraham <hi>tell him without a ſigh?</hi>) that God would provide; and what's <hi>Abraham</hi> about to doe now? what to binde him? <hi>Ah,</hi> Abraham, <hi>was thine heart in thy
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:55955:54"/>hand, or thy hand in thine heart?</hi> What, and lay him on the Altar! <hi>Tears, Abraham, tears.</hi> What, and ſtretch forth his hand, and take the knife, to ſlay his ſon! <hi>Oh wonder!</hi> Yet <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſo far from holding or praying to God to hold his hand, that the Lord himſelf cries out, Oh <hi>Abraham,</hi> hold thy hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is Abraham,</hi> of whom God ſaith, now I know thou feareſt (lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt) me, ſeeing thou haſt not withheld thy ſon, thine onely ſon from me. How then with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and adoration, may we ſay to God, now we know thou loveſt us, in that thou haſt not withheld thy ſon, thine onely ſon. <hi>Iſaac was but a ſhadow (and the offering up of</hi> Iſaac <hi>but a ſhadow of the offering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p) of the Son of God.</hi> Oh what a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove-token is this! herein is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve of God manifeſted; in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od commendeth his love, God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> love the world, that he gave <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Son,</hi> and that to death, that his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:55955:55"/>Son might give life to us. <hi>Was ever love like thine!</hi> That thou wouldſt part with a Son, ſuch a Son, ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in himſelf, ſo precious in thine eyes, who was thy Sabbath, thy reſt, in whom thou wert well pleaſed, for ſinners, for enemies, who did wickedly even as they could. <hi>Ah, Lord,</hi> never was there love like thine.</p>
               <q>—<hi>Thy love, Oh Lord, to mee Surpaſſeth that of</hi> Abraham <hi>to thee.</hi>
               </q>
               <p n="258">258. <hi>Boldneſſe in Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God gives all men leave to pray, but he gives his people leave to be bold in prayer; and that not onely for themſelves, to ſay, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> I will not let thee goe, but for others, as <hi>Moſes</hi> for <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, thy will be done. Remarkable is the boldnes which <hi>Abraham</hi> uſed with God, in the caſe of <hi>Sodome, Gen.</hi> 18.23. where he ſeems at the firſt daſh to charge God with a kinde of injuſtice, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:55955:55"/>yet but upon <hi>a peradventure;</hi> ſix times he comes to God, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with but <hi>a peradventure;</hi> he fell <hi>(a great fall)</hi> from fifty to ten, &amp; that but with a <hi>peradventure,</hi> and yet God gives him the hearing; yea, ſeems willing to have taken leſſe, if <hi>Abraham</hi> had but had the boldneſſe to bring his fifty to five.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is God no more Almighty? What is Pray'r?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bold creature, Pray'r becomes God's Conquerour.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rare Stratagem of war! Pray'r wins the field,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet God's not overcome, but God doth yield.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="259">259. <hi>Let not the left hand know what the right hand doth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a Chriſtian is about to perform any duty, he ſhould ſay to himſelf, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid unto his yong men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.5. Abide you here with the Aſſe, and I and the lad will goe yonder and worſhip;
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:55955:56"/>onely let him leave out this <hi>and come again.</hi> Self tarry you here, fleſh tarry you here, I and my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit muſt goe and worſhip; a poor ſoul may ſay many times, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is in him; but oh 'tis glorious when one can ſay, that he is in the Spirit, and can attend upon God without diſtraction.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ah my dear Lord, divorce my ſelf from mee!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then ſingle I will ſingly worſhip thee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet one wiſh more, for better two then one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And 'tis not good for man to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That I may to thee double honor give,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let thine in me, and me in thy Spirit live.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="260">260. <hi>An heavenly uſe of earthly things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Uſe recreations, and that which is more neceſſary, very eating, and drinking, and ſleeping, <hi>not as things
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:55955:56"/>which thou likeſt, but as things which thou lackeſt;</hi> not out of luſt, but neceſſity: Look on all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world, either <hi>as ſins or ſnares,</hi> and then thou wilt not take too much pleaſure in this world. Uſe all Earthly things <hi>as thou doſt a pair of ſtairs,</hi> by which thou goeſt up to thy chamber, but ſtill keepeſt them under thy feet; though thou put forth thine hand, yet keep in thine heart, and be ſure that while the things of earth have thy body, the things of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven may have thy ſoul: though all things be lawfull to thee, yet come not under the power of any. <hi>Let not thy ſervants be thy maſters:</hi> thou wert not made to ſerve thine eſtate, thy body, and thy ſenſual appetite, but they were made to ſerve thee. Uſe thine eſtate then to ſerve thy bodily-occaſions, and thy body to ſerve thy ſoul-occafi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thy ſoul to obſerve Gods Commandements; thus all thou
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:55955:57"/>doeſt will be a glory to thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all that's thus done <hi>(decently and in order)</hi> is done to the glory of God: and thus while others <hi>turn their ſervice of God into a bodily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, thou maieſt turn thy bodily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe into the ſervice of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="261">261. <hi>Improvement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were men but as wiſe for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as they are for time, and did they ſpiritually improve their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural principles for their ſouls, as they do naturally for their bodies and eſtates, <hi>what precious Chriſtians might men be;</hi> for inſtance.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Principle.</hi> To believe good news well grounded. Why then is not the Goſpel <hi>(which is the beſt and beſt grounded news in the world)</hi> believed?</item>
                  <item>2. To love what's lovely, and that moſt which is moſt lovely. <hi>Why then is not Chriſt the beloved of mens ſouls, ſeeing he is altogether lovely?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. To fear that which will hurt them. <hi>Why then are not men afraid
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:55955:57"/>to ſin, ſeeing nothing is ſo hurtful to them as ſin?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Not to truſt a known decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; <hi>why then doe men truſt</hi> 1. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the old Serpent, the deceiver of the world? 2. The world, and its deceitful riches. 3. Their own hearts, which are deceitful above knowledge. <hi>Alas!</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. To lay up for a rainy day; for old age. <hi>Why then doe not men lay up for eternity, treaſures of faith and good works againſt the day of death and judgement?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. He that will give moſt ſhall have it. <hi>Why doe not men give their love and ſervice to God then? Doth not he bid moſt?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. Take warning by others harms. <hi>Why do not men take heed of ſinning from the ſufferings and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which others undergoe for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. To have ſomething to ſhew under mens hands, becauſe they are mortal. <hi>Why then will not men
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:55955:58"/>have ſomething to ſhew under Gods hand for their ſecurity to ſalvation,</hi> ſeeing not God, but they are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall? Ah, if men did but walk by their own rules, and improve ſuch and many others of their own Principles, what an help would it be to godlineſſe. <hi>But alas,</hi> God may complain of men as of his people of old, my people doe not conſider, men do not conſider.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="262">262. How bad ſoever they are who profeſſe the truth, yet the truth which they profeſſe is never the worſe; if they offend and wrong their ſouls, doe not thou be offended and wrong thine owne ſoul.</p>
               <p n="263">263. We many <hi>(alas too many)</hi> times have to doe with God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confidering what we have, or with whom we have to doe.</p>
               <p n="264">264. Some good things come to the <hi>Saints</hi> in this life, but the reſt and the beſt is reſerved for the life to come.</p>
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:55955:58"/>
               <p n="265">265. <hi>Recreation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some men are ſo much at, and ſo much in recreations, that they loſe the recreation of recreation, let it be but ſhort and 'twill be the ſweeter, <hi>eſpecially if thou preſerve thine heart, to be as free to goe off as to come on;</hi> elſe 'tis to be fear'd, that if thou worke at thy play, thou wilt play at thy work; for he that makes his recreation a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, will thinke his buſineſſe a toile; and if once thy calling be a wearines, thou wilt ſoon be weary of thy calling, and then ther's roome made for the next <hi>luſt</hi> that <hi>offer's it ſelfe to thy ſervice, that thou mai'ſt offer thy ſelfe to 'its ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="266">266. <hi>The day of Judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The day of judgement will be to many <hi>dies deceptionis</hi> a day of deceipt, not that it will deceive any, but make it appeare that many have deceived themſelves with vaine hopes of heaven, of which they will then be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:55955:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Many that have paſt mans day of approbation, may at that day meet with reprobation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many that have beene looked upon, and have looked like gold here, may be found droſſe then, yea reprobate ſilver will he call them.</p>
               <p n="266">266. <hi>The teachings of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some duties God teacheth us by precept, <hi>as ſaith and repentance;</hi> others he teacheth us by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>as love mercy</hi> &amp;c. many are taught both theſe wayes, which yet are not taught of God, becauſe they learne not what they are taught. <hi>Men are then properly taught when they are powerfully &amp; effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught,</hi> ſo as that they learne the truth as it is in Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="267">267. Surely he that love's him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will not hate his brother, for while he is out of charity with his brother, God is out of charity with him; and he loſeth more for want of Gods Love, then his brother
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:55955:59"/>loſeth for want of his love.</p>
               <p n="269">269. As he that provid's not for the reliefe of his owne family is worſe then an infidel, and hath denied the faith; ſo he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not them that are naked and deſtitute of dayly food, hath alſo denied the faith. <hi>James</hi> 2. <hi>The true believer therefore ſhould ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his owne family, as that he may relieve others &amp; ſo relieve others, as not to wrong his own family;</hi> for though charity ſeek not her own, yet without offence or offending, charity may begin at home.</p>
               <p n="270">270. He that repents of a good act, turnes good into evill.</p>
               <p n="271">271. Many, <hi>becauſe</hi> they can hide their ſin from men, are apt to thinke that their ſin can be hid from God; <hi>becauſe</hi> they ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puni'ſht, that ſin hath no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>becauſe</hi> they can ſin with eaſe, that 'tis an eaſie thing to ſin: but ah when God ſhall reprove them, and ſet their ſin in order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:55955:60"/>their faces, <hi>and when</hi> the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſin, which is eternal death, ſhall be their portion, <hi>and when</hi> the gnawing worm ſhall ever live as a ſting in their conſciences, they will then know how they have been deceived and hardned through the deceitfulneſſe of ſin, that they might not be ſenſible what an evil &amp; bitter thing it was that the fear of God was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes.</p>
               <p n="272">272. Many men go about to mince, mitigate and leſſen their ſin, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of it as <hi>Jonathan in another caſe,</hi> I have taſted but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle honey on the top of a rod, and I muſt die. I have ſtoln, I have lyed, I have taken a bribe, I have us'd falſe weights and meaſures, I have diſſembled and equivocated, but 'twas but for a little, and muſt I die? Alas, <hi>they that ſin for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, will not finde their ſin little;</hi> nay, the ſinne is the greater that men would tranſgreſs the good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:55955:60"/>of the great God for ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. <hi>The leſſe the temptation, the greater the ſin;</hi> if thou canſt finde it in thine heart to ſin ſo high at ſo low a rate, at what a rate wouldſt thou ſin for more? If thou canſt ſell Chriſt for thirty pieces, what wouldſt thou do for a greater price?</p>
               <p n="273">273. A man ſhould not hate the perſon for the ſins ſake, nor love the ſin for the perſons ſake.</p>
               <p n="274">274. 'Tis good to take the changes of this world without changing, not to be exalted when we are exalted, nor to be caſt down, when we are caſt down; but to carry it with an even frame towards God and man, as <hi>having learnt how to abound without pride, and how to want without murmuring.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="275">275. Be not curious nor buſie in enquiring after other mens bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; he that mindes the doing of his own buſineſs, will finde bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs enough to do.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:55955:61"/>
               <p n="276">276. Some men never forſake their ſin; till their ſin forſake them, they do wickedly as they can, and as long as they can, and were their power as much as their will, they would neither leave ſin, nor ſuffer ſin to leave them: <hi>they will as much as they have power to do, though they have not power to do as much as they will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="277">277. A drunken and an angry man do both agree in this, that they ſpeak they know not what, and afterward they know not what they ſpake.</p>
               <p n="278">278. There's little difference in Religion, between not giving to the poor, and taking from the poor, btween not ſaving and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, between not doing good, and doing evil; for in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. the ſentence of condemnation is paſt, not for oppoſing, or taking from, or killing, but for not relieving the poor; 'tis paſt-on ſins of omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe indeed <hi>the omiſſion of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:55955:61"/>good is the commiſſion of evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="279">279. I have heard of a woman, that did grudge to give her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band obedience and honour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as ſhe ſaid he was unworthy; to whom it was anſwered, that <hi>how unworthy ſoever he were, yet the command of God was worthy to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed;</hi> whatever ſhe had to ſay againſt her husband, ſhe had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay againſt the command of God, which is holy, juſt, &amp; good.</p>
               <p n="280">280. When a Chirurgeon comes to let us blood, we bid him wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, we thank him, <hi>and give him a fee beſide:</hi> and ſhall we not wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come God, when he comes by any affliction to let us blood, and to cut out our dead fleſh? <hi>eſpecially</hi> when we may ſay as a Maid, who lay under a Surgeons hand, and being aſk't how ſhe could endure ſuch lancing, &amp;c. ſhe replied, 'twas her father, who loved her, and did it to do her good. <hi>They verily for a few daies chaſten us after their own
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:55955:62"/>pleaſure, but he for our profit, that we may be partakers of his holineſs.</hi> And ſhall we not bleſſe him?</p>
               <p n="281">281. A Miniſter living neer to a Philoſopher, did often perſwade him to become a Chriſtian; Oh but ſaid the Philoſopher, if I turn Chriſtian, <hi>I muſt or may loſe all for Chriſt:</hi> to whom, and to which the Miniſter replyed, <hi>if you loſe any thing for Chriſt, he will repay it an hundred fold:</hi> I but ſaid the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, will you be bound for Chriſt, that if he do not pay me, you will? Yes, that I will ſaid the Miniſter: So the Philoſopher be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Chriſtian, and the Miniſter entred into bond, and became a ſurety for the Surety of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. When this new-Chriſtian-Philoſopher was on his ſick and death-bed, he held this bond in his hand, and ſent for the Miniſter, to whom he gave up the bond, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt hath paid all,</hi> there's nothing for you to pay, take your
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:55955:62"/>bond. Surely though a man ſhould be a loſer for Chriſt, he ſhall be no loſer by Chriſt, he will make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for all, <hi>Matthew</hi> 19.21.</p>
               <p n="282">282. When we know not what to do, we ſhould not be diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, nor diſcontent, but have our eyes to God; for <hi>though we are at a loſſe, yet God is not,</hi> he is where he was, when we know not where we are; though other men may maſter us, yet God is more mans maſter, then man is ours, yea, when wee are in our enemies hands, we are not out of Gods hands. <hi>Wait quietly on him, and he will bring it to paſſe,</hi> delight thy ſelf in him, and he will give thee thine hearts deſire; in all thy waies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, and he ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thy path.</p>
               <p n="283">283. <hi>A ſtumbling block removed.</hi> Many men ſtumble at this ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſtone, that thoſe who teach well, live ill; <hi>the good Lord remove the offenders, and the offence:</hi> Tuſh
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:55955:63"/>ſay they, we know them too well to think they are in earneſt. Alas! alas! indeed 'tis true, they that Preach the Goſpel of truth, ſhould practiſe the truth of the Goſpel; but <hi>if they will not, wilt not thou?</hi> is the truth the worſe, becauſe they are bad? the Doctrine which they Preach, may ſave thee, if thou believe it, and do it, though they that Preach the Doctrine may not be ſaved themſelves. If they be ſo bad to go to Hell, wilt thou be ſo mad to follow them there? What ſaid our Saviour of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, <hi>(bad men in good employment)</hi> after their ſayings do ye, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. and <hi>as the Proverb ſaies,</hi> do as they ſay, and not as they do, unleſs they do as they ſhould do; 'tis not ſo much the Preachers Practiſe, as the Preachers Doctrine, that thou art to minde; <hi>if they teach what they ſhould, that's to thee, if they do not, what they teach, that's to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> But oh all you that ſpeak
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:55955:63"/>in the name of the Lord, let me beg you, that we may all be living and walking Goſpels; <hi>Our work is not onely to be Heavenly in the Pulpit:</hi> Shall we Preach Chriſt to others, and be without proof of Chriſt living in us? Shall we make our ſelves tranſgreſſors, by deſtroying the things that we build? How can we think that others will learn of us, if we will not learn our ſelves? Do we think to go Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven any other way? Shall it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be ſaid in reproach, <hi>that when in the Pulpit, 'tis pity they ſhould come out; but when out, 'tis pity they ſhould come in?</hi> What! ſhall wee bring up an evil report upon the good Goſpel? ſhall we take his name into our mouth, and not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? ſhall we that ſay to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, live <hi>holily,</hi> live wick ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? ſhall wee that teach Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-faith, not believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? ſhall we that call upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to have their converſation
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:55955:64"/>in Heaven, minde Earthly things, and become enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt? ſhall we that make our boaſt of the Law, through break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law diſhonour God? for <hi>by this the name of God is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among men.</hi> Oh that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may be an example of the believers, not onely in word, but in converſation, in charity, in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in faith and purity, and ſo take heed to our ſelves, and our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that we may ſave our ſelves and them that hear us. <hi>And you</hi> dear ſouls <hi>that are offended,</hi> let me beſeech you in the bowels of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, not to think the worſe of Preaching, if Preachers be bad, nor to think that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel preacht is faulty, becauſe the Preachers are in fault. Oh let your profiting be known to all men, do not refuſe an Heavenly treaſure, though in an Earthly Veſſel; nor think the worſe of the Goſpel, though <hi>Judas</hi> be a Preacher. <hi>As
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:55955:64"/>thou loveſt thy ſoul, do not be offended with that which is without offence, though he that brings it do offend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="284">284. He that gives <hi>moſt</hi> may do moſt good to others; but he that gives <hi>beſt,</hi> doth moſt good to himſelf.</p>
               <p n="285">285. Some perſons paſſe their few daies here in an uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; weariſom ſadneſſe of ſpirit, and come to Heaven ere they are aware; others paſſe their daies in a golden dream of jollity, &amp; drop into Hell afore they think of it. <hi>Its better to dream of Hell, and when one awakes to finde himſelf in Heaven, then to dream of Heaven, and when one awakes, to finde himſelf in Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="286">286. Its better to be a childe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> though called dog <hi>as the woman was;</hi> then to be a dog, and yet to be called a childe <hi>as</hi> Dives <hi>was.</hi> Empty titles have but em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty comforts; <hi>Judas</hi> was more a Devil, though and when Chriſt called him friend, then <hi>Peter</hi> was though and when Chriſt called him Satan. <hi>Peter</hi> though called
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:55955:65"/>Satan, was Chriſt's friend, and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> though called friend, was Chriſt's enemy. <hi>Peter</hi> though bid to get behinde, was not caſt off, and <hi>Judas</hi> though kiſt, was not embrac'd. <hi>Minde not names, but things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="287">287. <hi>Who gives more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God out-bids ſin and Satan, and therefore ſurely if hee that will give moſt ſhall have us, we ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lords. Satan at moſt and beſt could <hi>(to Chriſt which was for all mankinde at once)</hi> but ſay, all this will I give thee. This? <hi>Is this all?</hi> This all is nothing at all to what God offers. God offers not onely theſe things, but greater and better things then theſe: for <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe hath the promiſe of this life, and of that to come.</hi> Who can bid more? Doth ſin bid pleaſures? God bids more and better; ſins pleaſures are but for a ſeaſon, but at Gods right hand are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; <hi>ever and more.</hi> Do ye bid Crowns? God bids a Crown im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:55955:65"/>which fadeth not away. Do they bid a Kingdome? Chriſt bids Kingdome and Glory. <hi>Oh for ſhame,</hi> let us not deny God our ſouls, ſeeing he bids moſt and beſt for them.</p>
               <p n="288">288. <hi>Praiſe diſpraiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that riſeth early to praiſe his friend with a loud voice, it ſhall bee a curſe to him: when the Phariſees came to tempt Chriſt, they praiſed him: <hi>If they that praiſe thee to thy face, come not to tempt thee, yet a temptation comes with the praiſe:</hi> Be thou therefore ſo civil to thy ſelf, as to begge thy friend that he would not be ſo ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to thee; its better that thou by ſpeaking ſhouldſt ſilence him, then that thou ſhouldſt be ſilent, while he is ſpeaking: for <hi>though thou hear no ill, yet he doth not hear well, that hears his own praiſes.</hi> He doth thee more hurt that praiſeth thee, though there be cauſe, then hee that diſpraiſeth thee when
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:55955:66"/>there is no cauſe; the one is thine enemy, though he be thy friend; the other is thy friend, though he be thine enemy.</p>
               <p n="289">289. <hi>Partiality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſtrange to ſee how ſome ſtrain at G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and ſwallow Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels; make conſcience of Tithing, Mint, and Cummin, and yet make none of neglecting the weightier things of the Law: Swear they will not, <hi>yet make no bones</hi> of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſſembling, doing to others what they would not have others to doe to them; of ſelfe-ſeeking, though to the breach of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and to the hurt of others: <hi>Herod</hi> would not diſpenſe with his Oath, but could diſpenſe with his Conſcience, and commit mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a ſcruple. Many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons make conſcience of obſerving all Ordinances, <hi>(as they phraſe it)</hi> which make little or no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of neglecting many duties, or doing them negligently, without
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:55955:66"/>ſenſe or feeling: <hi>Dinah's</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren cannot in conſcience marry their ſiſter to an uncircumciſed man, yet can without conſcience marry their own ſouls to revenge and murther. Many cannot in conſcience keep communion and maintain fellowſhip with ſuch as they acknowledge godly, <hi>becauſe they are not of their opinion,</hi> and in their way, who yet can maintain communion with ſuch as they judge not godly, <hi>being of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> and in their way. <hi>Is this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular conſcience?</hi> True conſcience is univerſal conſcience; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Davids Prayer,</hi> make mine heart ſound in thy ſtatutes, that I be not aſhamed, may well be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with, and expounded by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids Principle,</hi> then ſhall I not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, when I have reſpect to all thy Commandements. Surely <hi>if thou be not aſhamed of thy partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, thy partiality will bring thee to ſhame;</hi> the wiſdome that's from
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:55955:67"/>above is not onely without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, but without partiality.</p>
               <p n="290">290. Wretch that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death? <hi>Even he</hi> whoſe body was delivered unto death, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came death by dying.</p>
               <p n="291">291. There are <hi>two</hi> ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereby to oppoſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſin. The firſt and the greateſt is this, <hi>how ſhall I do this wickedneſſe, and ſin againſt God?</hi> Who can finde it in his heart to diſhonour his God? The ſecond is like unto it, <hi>how ſhall I doe this wickedneſſe, and wrong mine own ſoul?</hi> What, ſhall I be a ſelf murtherer? get behinde me Satan, though thou wilt have to doe with me, yet what have I any more to do with thee?</p>
               <p n="392">392. 'Tis no wonder that the world care's not for Saints, for the ſaint is a man of another world in this; <hi>were he of the world, the world would love 'its owne:</hi> and 'tis no
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:55955:67"/>wonder that the ſaints care not for this world; For what ſhould ſtrangers, ſojourners and pilgrims load themſelves with bagge and baggage for? no, they declare <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> that <hi>they</hi> ſeeke a countrey, and <hi>would not alwayes ſtay in the world, for all the world.</hi> The world is crucified to me, and I unto the world.</p>
               <p n="293">293. <hi>Saying of prayer without praying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many men ſay the Lords-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which doe not pray it; they <hi>(as Auſtine before Converſion when he prayed for Chaſtity)</hi> are afraid leſt God ſhould heare them; they doe not care that God ſhould ſay A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or ſo be it, though they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs wil ſay ſo; they ſay, <hi>Our father,</hi> but if he be their father, where is his honour? they ſay, <hi>which art in heaven,</hi> but did they believe it, how durſt they ſin as they doe on earth? they ſay, <hi>hallowed be thy name,</hi> yet take Gods name in vain; they ſay, <hi>thy kingdome come,</hi> yet oppoſe
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:55955:68"/>the comming of his Kingdome: they ſay <hi>thy will be done on earth as it is heaven,</hi> yet will not ſtand to their words, for this is the will of God their ſanctification, but they will none of that. They ſay, <hi>give us this day our daily bread,</hi> yet minde not the feeding of their ſouls with the bread <hi>(Chriſt Jeſus)</hi> which came downe from heaven. <hi>They ſay forgive us as we forgive others,</hi> but alas, if God ſhould take them to their word, how undon were they, whoſe hearts burne with malice &amp; revenge, even while they pray, or ſay thus; for forgiveneſſe they ſay, <hi>lead us not into temptation,</hi> yet run into it, and tempt the divell himſelf to tempt them. They ſay, <hi>deliver us from evill,</hi> and yet deliver themſelves to evill, and give up themſelves to fulfill the wills of the fleſh, &amp;c. yea, <hi>it hath bin obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> that they ſin moſt againſt this prayer, who ſtickle moſt for the ſaying of this prayer.</p>
               <pb n="227" facs="tcp:55955:68"/>
               <p n="294">294. <hi>Much from a little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians ſhould be very ſhy of the occaſions of evill, and take heed of the wine when 'tis red in the glaſſe, and have an eye to their eye when they looke on a maid. <hi>Dinah</hi> out of a gadding curioſity muſt needs viſit the daughters of the land, and while ſhe goeth to ſee the daughters, the ſon ſaw her, <hi>viſamque cupit,</hi> and having ſeen her, he tooke her; having taken her, he lay with her; having layn with her, he defiled her; <hi>the report whereof comming to Jacobs ſons,</hi> they were grieved; being grieved, they were wroth; being wroth, they meditate revenge; meditating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, they ſpeak deceitfully; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king deceitfully, they deceiv'd; having deceived, they ſlew; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſlain, they ſpoil'd: ſee <hi>how great a fire a little matter kindleth,</hi> what great evils there iſſue forth from ſmall beginnings. Take heed then.</p>
               <p n="295">295. Riches are called thornes,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:55955:69"/>ſuch riches may be touch'd, but not reſted upon; <hi>can'ſt thou ſet thine heart upon a thorne,</hi> without pierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy ſelfe through with many ſorrowes.</p>
               <p n="128">128. <hi>Selfe oondemned in another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We many times condemne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and therein paſſe ſentence againſt our ſelves; <hi>thus Judah ſaid of Tamar,</hi> bring her forth, and let her be burnt, not conſidering that he ſpake the word againſt his owne ſoul: <hi>thus David to Nathan,</hi> the man that hath done this thing ſhall dye; not conſidering that he was the mau. <hi>Lord</hi> wherein I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, helpe me to pull out mine owne beame, before I judge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his moate; and wherein others have ſinned, helpe me ſo to junge their frailties, as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelfe leaſt I alſo ſhould be tempted, and then I ſhould as much need their pity, as they now need mine.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:55955:69"/>
               <p n="297">297. <hi>Fiekle inconſtancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ah Lord, how much have we to do with our ſelves, poor way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, peeviſh, froward we are, not well either full or faſting: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther its too hot, or too cold, too wet, or too dry, we would, &amp; then we would not. <hi>We are diſcontented if we have not, and not contented with what we have;</hi> if we have health, we would have wealth; if wealth, we would exchange it for health; when in company, wee have a minde to be alone; when alone, we would we were in company;
<q>
                     <hi>Romae Tybur amo, ventoſus Tybur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Romam.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The City is too full of company and cloſe, the Countrey is too ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and open aired.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod petit, ſpernit, repetit quod nuper omiſit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeſtuat, &amp; vitae diſconvenit ordine toto.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="230" facs="tcp:55955:70"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh! how I like, diſlike, deſire, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Repel, Repeal, loath, and delight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My ſelf I follow, and my ſelf I fly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beſide my ſelf, and in my ſelf am I.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My ſelf am not my ſelf, another ſame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlike my ſelf, and like my ſelf I am.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Self-fond, ſelf-furious,</hi> and thus wayward elf,</l>
                  <l>I cannot live without, nor with my ſelf.</l>
               </q>
               <p>We e'ne put God to it to know what to do with us; and if he did not croſſe us, 'twould be a curſe to us; <hi>'tis well for us that 'tis all with us;</hi> if it were not bad, it would be worſe; there's ſcarce any thing <hi>(though we ſcarce think it ſo)</hi> that we are more beholding to God for, then for croſſing us; for woe to us, if he let us alone, <hi>'tis ten to one</hi> but hearts deſires and lean
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:55955:70"/>ſouls would go together.</p>
               <p n="298">298. <hi>Moderation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A moderate minde will be content with a moderate eſtate, and nothing more conduceth to moderation then to know that the time is ſhort, and the Lord is at hand; <hi>he that thinks ſeriouſly of theſe two, can neither be careleſſe nor covetous:</hi> let us then be careleſly careful, and carefully careleſſe: let us be careful of to day, and careleſſe of to morrow, for ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the day is the evil thereof.</p>
               <p n="299">299. 'Tis hard to be chearfull without levity, or ſerious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out melancholy; <hi>we verge to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes.</hi> In conveniences and ſnares attend all conſtitutions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions (and like Syllogiſmes <hi>ſequimur deteriorem partem.</hi>) Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe is moſt like to do the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy good, and the ſoul hurt, and ſeriouſneſſe is moſt like to do the ſoul good, and the body hurt, <hi>if we take not heed;</hi> that therefore
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:55955:71"/>ſoul and body may receive good, and no hurt, let us <hi>be cheerfully ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and ſeriouſly cheerful;</hi> while cheerfulneſſe is the ſall, let ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe be the ballaſt of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; if we want ballaſt, we may move too ſwiftly; if we want ſails, we ſhall move too ſlowly.</p>
               <p n="300">300. <hi>'Tis not in man to direct his way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis hard to know what courſe to take to obtain an end, to be <hi>compos voti,</hi> and to enjoy ones de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: for that which ſometime is to ſome the onely help, at other times is to others the onely hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance. Some denials had never been given, had it not been for the importunity of them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted, and ſome requeſts had never been granted, if the reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had not been importunate. <hi>Fabius (Cunctator)</hi> conquer'd by delaies. <hi>Caeſar</hi> by expedition and quick diſpatch. 'Twas but <hi>Veni, Vidi, Vici.</hi> There is uncertainty in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:55955:71"/>wiſdome as well as folly. The courſe we take to ſave us, kills us, and that which we fear will bee our undoing, proves our ſafety. What a ſimple thing is man! <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom alſo is vanity.</hi> In all thy ways acknowledge God, and he ſhall direct thy paths.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="century">
               <head>The third Century.</head>
               <p n="301">301. God afflicts Saints, becauſe he loves them; the Devil afflicts them, becauſe he hates them; If God did not love them, he would not; if the Devil did love them, he would not afflict them. <hi>God afflicts them for their gain, that they may be ſanctified and ſaved; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil afflicts them for their loſſe, that they may ſin and be damned:</hi> But this is their comfort, that God loves them more then the Devil can hate them, and that Gods love will doe them more good, then the Devils hatred can doe them
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:55955:72"/>hurt; and that God is better able to bring about his ends, then the Devil is able to bring about his. <hi>Lord,</hi> let me be a Saint, though an afflicted one, and loved of thee, though the world and the Devil hate me. <hi>Sanctifie;</hi> I do beſeech thee, <hi>the Devils temptations, and mine own corruptions to me;</hi> I ſhall then know that all things work together for my good, when I am the better; and that they are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to me, when I am the more ſanctified.</p>
               <p n="302">302. Death.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>—<hi>He that would try</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What is true happineſſe indeed, muſt dye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The good mans end is ſurely the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of his true joy, cauſe 't puts an end to ſinning.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>There were three Saints, <hi>Job, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> and <hi>Jonah,</hi> deſiring to dye out of diſcontent, two Saints, <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> content to deſire death,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:55955:72"/>and two other Saints <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> not diſcontented, yet not content to dye: Lord, let me rather be content to dye, then be diſcontented to live; for though having with <hi>Simeon</hi> ſeen thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, I deſire to depart in peace; and with <hi>Paul,</hi> long to be with Chriſt, which is farre better; yet I dare not out-face thee as <hi>Jonah</hi> did, to ſay 'tis better for me to dye then to live; <hi>Surely 'tis not good to dye in anger, nor well to be angry unto death.</hi> Let this be the care of my ſoul, that while I live, I may live to thee, and then when I dye, I ſhall live with thee. So thou mayeſt be magnified, its no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whether it be by life or death; yet ſeeing (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſaid) 'tis the living praiſe thee, Oh (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> pray'd) ſpare me a little, and give me ſtrength <hi>(to do thy will)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I go hence and be no more ſeen.</p>
               <p n="303">303. We obtain nothing by the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:55955:73"/>merit, but many things by the means of prayer.</p>
               <p n="304">304. 'Tis eaſie to tell a Lye, 'tis hard to tell but a Lye; 'tis hard to commit one fin, and but one ſin.</p>
               <p n="305">305. While others fret at the proſperity of the wicked, and are envious at the fooliſh, becauſe they abound in goods; <hi>my prayer for them ſhall be this,</hi> much good may they doe with it, and much good may it doe them; the firſt is the duty, the next is the bleſſing; if the duty be not done, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing will not come. <hi>If they doe not doe good, 'twill doe them no good.</hi> For not what one hath, but what one doth with what one hath, maketh happy or miſerable.</p>
               <p n="306">306. Some men can ſay, as <hi>Eſau;</hi> I have enough, or rather as 'tis in the Hebrew, <hi>I have much;</hi> but few can ſay, as <hi>Jacob,</hi> I have enough, or (as 'tis in the Hebrew) <hi>I have all,</hi> or God is all to me, he is mine all. <hi>He hath not enough how much
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:55955:73"/>ſoever he hath, that hath not God for his portion; and he that hath God for his portion, hath enough, how little ſoever he hath.</hi> 'Tis not happy are the people that are in ſuch (a plentiful) caſe, but happy are the people whoſe God is the Lord.</p>
               <p n="307">307. <hi>The Alphabet or Croſſe-row.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.24. is the Chriſtians Alphabet or Croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: We learn that firſt which we muſt alwaies uſe, <hi>as our letters and our vowels, we can ſpell no word without them.</hi> This leſſon of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial muſt be firſt learnt, becauſe alwaies to be practis'd; for <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it we can doe nothing,</hi> that is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſing to God, or profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our ſelves: <hi>he that denies himſelf, doth himſelf moſt good, and he that ſeeks himſelf, doth himſelf moſt hurt.</hi> The reaſon we are ſuch bad ſcholars, and non-proficients, is becauſe we are ſo long in taking out this firſt leſſon, <hi>dimidium facti qui bene coepit habet.</hi> He is more then
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:55955:74"/>half way, that learns this firſt line of Religion; till that be learnt, a man cannot proceed to take up the Croſſe, and follow Chriſt; if therefore we would be Chriſt's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, let us deny our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="308">308. <hi>Compariſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Few men judge themſelves happy or unhappy, according to what they are, but by comparing themſelves with others; <hi>where all goe naked, none are aſhamed:</hi> Many augment their miſery, by ſeeing others more happy; and yet think themſelves happy when they ſee others more miſerable. <hi>We many times gather our ſorrowes from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers joyes, and our joyes from others ſorrowes.</hi> We bleſſe our ſelves, when we ſee them below us, and yet think all we have to be no bleſſing, when we look on them that are above us. <hi>Lord,</hi> let not me think my good the leſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others have more; or my evil the more, becauſe others have
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:55955:74"/>leſſe; but let me learn in all eſtates to be content, and to welcome the will, come how it will.</p>
               <p n="309">309. Some men while they are wits in jeſt, are fools in earneſs; for commonly they are <hi>the trifling things of the world,</hi> whom ſerious men have to doe withal, when they have nothing elſe to doe: their greateſt buſineſſe is to laugh, and their reward to be laught at.</p>
               <p n="310">310. We are to labour for what the Son of man giveth, and God will be ſought for that which he will doe for the houſe of <hi>Iſrael; Gods promiſes and our prayers are middle things</hi> between Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and our attainments.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—<hi>God expecteth we ſhould crave</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The mercy he intendeth we ſhould have.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p n="311">311. Gods being ſometimes better then his word, (in doing that which he never engaged himſelf by promiſe to doe, and ſo doing above, exceeding abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:55955:75"/>above all that we were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ask or think, in being found of them that ſeek him not) is no indulgence to idleneſſe, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation from duty: <hi>We are not to minde what God can do, or doth do, but what God hath ſaid he will do, and the way wherein:</hi> if ever we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to enjoy what's promiſed, we muſt doe what's commanded; <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boranti &amp; ſperanti Deus dabit:</hi> Though God have promiſed to give to them that ask, yet he hath not promiſed to give without ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and ſeeing 'tis but ask, and have; we may not blame God for not giving, but our ſelves for not asking; and if we ask, and miſſe, we may blame our ſelves for ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amiſſe.</p>
               <p n="312">312. The moſt things in the world are perfectly imperfect; and the beſt things in the world are but imperfectly perfect.</p>
               <p n="313">313. Saints have ſo learned Chriſt, and of Chriſt, as not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:55955:75"/>to reſtrain their hands from hurting, but their hearts from hating their very enemies.</p>
               <p n="314">314. <hi>Prayer is the ſould in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the ſenſe of the ſoul enlarged and explained, 'tis the ſoul ſpeaking its mind, and mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it ſpeaks to God; and a gracious heart never thinks it wel done, but when every confeſſion hath its weight of ſorrow, and every petition its fill of grace.</p>
               <p n="315">315. Am I become your enemy becauſe I tell you the truth? <hi>What turn-coats are theſe?</hi> But awhile ſince they would have pulled out their eyes for <hi>Paul,</hi> and now they would have pulled out <hi>Pauls</hi> eyes, who told them the truth. Light is pleaſant, yet offenſive to ſore eyes; honey is ſweet, but it makes wounds to ſmart; truth is moſt wholeſome, but diſtaſteful to diſtempered pallats: <hi>Lord, let me never hate them which tell me the
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:55955:76"/>truth, nor the truth which they tell me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="316">316. <hi>A miſtake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The world hath alwaies had thoughts of Religion clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what it is and doth. Moſt men are ſo mad as to think a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious life madneſſe; as if Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did but make men melancholy and dull their ſpirits, and make them look wrinkled with ſorrow and care long before they are wrinkled with age; as if it did but depreſſe mens ſpirits, put an end to all their joyes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and incapacitate men to be great and glorious in this world: inſomuch that <hi>he who makes conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his waies, is lookt upon, but as one of God Almighties fools.</hi> Alas, what a miſtake is this! Can there be greater and better joy then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in the Lord, joy in the holy Ghoſt, unſpeakable and full of glory? Can there be better chear then a good conſcience? If
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:55955:76"/>Saints mourn and are ſorrowful, 'tis becauſe they are no better, <hi>and they are the better for that;</hi> for god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow worketh repentance to ſalvation, never to be repented of; <hi>Religion takes no man off from any thing that is good; and is it not good to be taken off from evil?</hi> Is it cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe to be afraid of ſin? Bleſſed is he that ſo feareth alwaies: Is not he ſtronger that overcometh himſelf, then he that overcometh a City? Is it folly to be wiſe to ſalvation? Is it loſſe to be godly? When as indeed godlineſs is the great and onely gain. Is it not better to be poor with honeſty, then to be rich by knavery? To which of the Saints will ye turn? <hi>Surely they that condemn Religion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were religious.</hi> Ask <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. if the waies of God be not pleaſantneſs, and his paths peace; if his yoke be not eaſie, and his burthen light? <hi>Ah Lord, whatever</hi> others call wiſdome, let this be
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:55955:77"/>mine to fear thee, and to depart from evil; let godlineſſe be my gain; while others take care to be great, let me take care to be good: while others ſeek Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts over men, let me fight the good fight of faith, whereby I may conquer the world, and <hi>the evil man</hi> my ſelf; and if this be to be vile, let me be more vile; if this be to be a fool, let me be a fool. <hi>Dear Lord,</hi> if none will love thee, yet let me love thee. 'Tis better to goe to Heaven, though alone, then to goe to hell with company: as long as I am happy, I care not though the world think me miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p n="317">317. Worldly riches are like Nuts; many clothes are torn in getting them, many a tooth bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in cracking them, but never a belly filled with eating them.</p>
               <p n="318">318. Love in deſcent is ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then love in aſcent: hence <hi>(they ſay)</hi> parents are more loving to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:55955:77"/>their children, then children to their parents: I am ſure 'tis true between God and us, his deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and condeſcending to love us is ſtronger then our aſcending love to him.</p>
               <p n="319">319. Every variation from uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is a ſtep to nullity; and when men goe from one Religion to all, they are in the ready way to goe from all to none.</p>
               <p n="320">320. Whatever God gives to us, he gives freely, and whatever he takes from us, he takes juſtly; therefore where God is free to give, let us be juſt to uſe; and where God is juſt to take, let us be free to reſign.</p>
               <p n="321">321. The Scriptures are to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in an unknown tongue, though in their own tongue.</p>
               <p n="322">322. Indirect means may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times proſper, but its never bleſt.</p>
               <p n="323">323. Though a man ſhould be ſo honeſt as to be plain, yet he
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:55955:78"/>ſhould be ſo diſcreet as to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing when he reproves.</p>
               <p n="324">324. He ſpeaks himſelf a fool, that doth that, which reaſon tells him is unreaſonable; hence ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners call'd fools.</p>
               <p n="325">325. <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſinus</hi> tells us of one <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus Lullus,</hi> who was ſo raviſh'd with love, that being askt any thing, he would anſwer nothing but love: where dwelleſt thou? <hi>with love.</hi> To whom belongeſt thou? <hi>To love.</hi> Whence comeſt thou? <hi>From love.</hi> Whither goeſt thou? <hi>To love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh that we were thus taken with the love of our lovely and loving God!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis likewiſe ſaid of <hi>Mary,</hi> that by ſtrength of love, ſhe was dead to all the objects of the world; ſhe had her thoughts ſo employ'd on her Jeſus, that ſhe was almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible: She had eyes, and ſaw not; ears and heard not; ſenſes and felt not; <hi>ſhe was not where ſhe
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:55955:78"/>was, for ſhe was wholly where her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was, though ſhe knew not where he was:</hi> She knew no are but that of Love; all in her turned to the love of him whom ſhe loved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh thus to love dear Jeſus, is worth the name of Love: how cold and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen is ours!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="326">326. <hi>Hope againſt hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many men have been deſtroyed by hoping againſt hope, and ſome have been preſerved by it: hope undoes moſt wicked men, but the good may ſay, we are ſaved by hope.</p>
               <p n="327">327. <hi>The evil of evil company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By being in ill company we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer both in our names and our ſouls; 'tis both diſgraceful and dangerous: if we could keep our ſouls free, yet our names will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; and if we could keep our names ſafe, yet our ſouls are in danger.</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:55955:79"/>
               <p n="328">328. <hi>The Gull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> reports of <hi>Cato,</hi> that he wondred how Sooth-ſayers could forbear laughing, when they met with one another, becauſe they knew that they gull'd the people; and well might he jeer the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger, that told him he had caſt his nativity, and would tell him what ſhould befall him; <hi>tuſh ſaid he,</hi> I have been new-born, ſince I was born.</p>
               <p n="329">329. Its unnatural to hate them that love us; 'tis natural to love them that love us; but 'tis ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall to love them that hate us.</p>
               <p n="330">330. <hi>The Religion that proceeds from an humour, is but an humorous Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men uſually expreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves &amp; carry it in religion accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their naturall humor, and are apt to miſ-judge others if they comply not with their temper: <hi>Some are ſo pitifull that they could
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:55955:79"/>ſave the damned, others ſo Cholericke that they could damne the ſaved:</hi> hence the melancholy chriſtian is offended with the cheareful, and the chearefull with the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly: ſo that not onely the world but ſaints themſelves put falſe conſtructions, upon the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of ſaints. The melancholly man lookes on <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> as a choiſe man, becauſe of great abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and auſterity, as well in cloths as diet. For ſuch humors are apt to thinke that religion conſiſts much in ſadneſſe <hi>(Chriſt ſay they wept often, but we read not that he laught at all)</hi> and ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſe will they believe him a good Chriſtian, that is not ſomthing <hi>Hypocondriacall:</hi> yet the world paſſeth a cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſentence, and ſay he hath a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell. The more ſociable ſort of cheerefull ſaints, provided they they keep <hi>decorum,</hi> and be of Chriſts ſpirit, as well as chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, doe doubtleſs moſt adorne
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:55955:80"/>and advantage religion: chriſt did not onely rejoyce in ſpirit, but was popular and diſdained not the tables and converſations of the greateſt ſinners, for which the wicked world judg'd him as a wine-bibber, a great friend <hi>(and indeed he was)</hi> to Publicans and ſinners. Now we ſhould take heed, 1. <hi>That we take not our naturall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and humour for religion:</hi> a man may be moderate by the heavines of his Phlegme, and zealous from the heat of his choler; our care therefore ſhould be that our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, moderation and auſterity on the one hand, and our joy, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and zeale on the other hand, be truely ſpiritual and chriſtian. 2. <hi>we ſhould take heed not to condemne other ſaints, that are not of our natural humor;</hi> not to thinke the ſociable and cheerfull to be but good fellows and geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al-jovial blades; or to thinke the more depreſt, ſad dejected, and
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:55955:80"/>retired ſpirits to be diſcontented. God hath ſeverall ſorts of ſaints which he exerciſeth <hi>(as ſeverall members of the body or ſeverall veſſels in an houſe)</hi> moſt to that end to which they are appointed, his Beanerges's and his Barnabas, his Iohn and his Paul, every one in their owne place according to the gift and grace received <hi>(yea the ſame ſaint is ſometimes in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of one grace, at another time in the exerciſe of another grace, ſometime moſt in ſelfe-abaſing, at other times rejoycing in Chriſt Jeſus, ſometime in hope at other times in feare.)</hi> Now it may be his zeale doth beſt for him, and thy moderation for thee; his cheerfulneſſe beſt for him, and thy ſadnes beſt for thee: <hi>that which it may be is an occaſion of ſin to thee, is none to him, and that which would be an occaſion of ſin to him, is none to thee;</hi> judge not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another by thy ſelfe, nor thinke that every one muſt be caſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:55955:81"/>in thy mould.</p>
               <p n="331">331. We cannot give a reaſon of infinite things though <hi>(and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed becauſe)</hi> there is infinite reaſon for them: 'tis not becauſe ther's want of reaſon or too little, but becauſe ther's ſuch exceſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or too much for our capacity.</p>
               <p n="332">332. A pure conſcience is the ſafeſt ſafeguard in time of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>—<hi>hic murus aheneus eſto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>nil conſcire tibi, nulla palleſcere culpa.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Mine innocency ſhall be my brazen wall, the faultles man need not for fear looke pale.</p>
               <p n="333">333. Surely if we thought that God were good to us in every condition, we ſhould have good thoughts of God in every condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="334">334. They that would avoid the evill of occaſions, muſt avoid the occaſions of evill, as <hi>Solomon</hi> inculcates by foure ſeverall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:55955:81"/>in one verſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.15. <hi>That you may not enter into the path of the wicked,</hi> and not goe in the way of evil men, 1. Avoid it: 2. Paſs not by it. 3. Turn from it, 4. And paſs away. <hi>They that play with wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, are like to play the wantons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="335">335. Gods diſpenſations are ſo checquer-wrought with blacks and whites, that many times a Saint hath cauſe to rejoice, but yet with trembling; and at other times to tremble, but yet with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing.</p>
               <p n="336">336. It was a deſperate ſaying of one <hi>(a Lawyer)</hi> that as he that will not adventure his body can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be valiant, ſo he that will not adventure his ſoul cannot be rich. <hi>Men had better lay down their trades, then live by ſinning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="337">337. Surely <hi>goods ill gotten will never be good;</hi> 'tis better a man ſhould be able to ſay <hi>(as a good man once on his death-bed to his wife)</hi> I ſhall leave thee no great eſtate, but
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:55955:82"/>I ſhall leave thee a good eſtate; an eſtate well gotten, then to ſay, wife, or child, I ſhall leave you a great, but not good, becauſe an ill-gotten eſtate. <hi>To have an eſtate with a curſe, is to be miſerably rich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="338">338. <hi>Heaven and Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which makes <hi>Heaven</hi> ſo full of joy, is, that <hi>Heaven</hi> is above all fear; and that which makes <hi>Hell</hi> ſo full of terror, is, that <hi>Hell</hi> is below all hope: <hi>Heaven</hi> is a day which ſhall never ſee any approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings of night; and <hi>Hell</hi> is a night that ſhall never ſee any dawnings of day.</p>
               <p n="339">339. Did we conſider that both our good and evil were from God, it would make our good to be the better, and our evil not to be ſo bad.</p>
               <p n="340">340. A wiſe mans heart com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his tongue, but a fools tongue commands his heart.</p>
               <p n="341">341. Succeſſe at firſt doth many times undo men at laſt; <hi>many may
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:55955:82"/>ſay,</hi> that they had never been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, if they had not been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie,</p>
               <p n="342">342. A Chriſtian ſhould not care much for what he hath, and he ſhould care nothing for what he hath not: for what he hath, may not be, and what he hath not, may never be his.</p>
               <p n="243">243. Mans Preaching is but voice without power; but Gods is power without voice; <hi>Mans is word without work, Gods is work without word;</hi> man doth but ſpeak, but God ſpeaks and doth, every one of Gods words end in works; <hi>he ſaid,</hi> Let there be light, and 'twas ſo.</p>
               <p n="344">344. God ſpeaks of things that are to be done, and yet to come, as if they were already come and done. <hi>Many Propheſies of things to be, run in the Preſent Tenſe, as if they were in being. Babylon</hi> is fallen, it ſhall as certainly fall, as if it were fallen: by hope we are ſav'd; we
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:55955:83"/>are as ſafe as if we were ſaved, and are kept ſafe that we may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. He that believes not, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already; for he ſhall be as ſurely condemned, as if he were already in Hell. Them whom he predeſtinated, he called, juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and glorified; they ſhall be as ſurely called, juſtified, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, as if 'twere done.</p>
               <p n="344">344. All the glory of the world hath a ſtain, and all the beauty a ſpot; there is nothing that is all deſires, altogether lovely but Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He is, but time denies to tell you what,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sum all perfection up, and he is that.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>The praiſes of all others are with a but, and an exception. <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was a mighty man, <hi>but</hi> a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; ſuch an one, ſo and ſo, <hi>but</hi> &amp;c. fair, <hi>but</hi> fooliſh; ſerious, <hi>but</hi> ſubtle: Let us lay out our hearts then, not on that which is lovely but in part, but on him who is lovely in every part.</p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:55955:83"/>
               <p n="346">346. Contentment.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſo in preſent ſtate himſelf can rightly bear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath neither ill that's paſt, nor fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ill to fear:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The one which is no more, ought now no more to fray us,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th'other which is not yet, as little can diſmay us.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Not he that hath but little, but he that covets more,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Not the contented, but covetous man is poore.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The man who hungers not, he needs not bread I think,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The man that never thirſts, hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver need of drink.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="347">347. We are ſo far from meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by our works of mercy, that our works of mercy ſtand in need of mercy.</p>
               <p n="348">348. We can <hi>(alas we can)</hi> goe from heavenly things, to earthly things, and carry our hearts with us; but how ſeldome is it that we can goe from earthly things to
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:55955:84"/>heavenly, and carry our hearts with us?</p>
               <p n="349">349. Men appoint walls &amp; bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks for ſalvation, but God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points ſalvation for walls and bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks: Salvation is often with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out walls and bulwarks, and walls and bulwarks are often without ſalvation. <hi>Salvation is the ſafer ſafeguard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="350">350. Saints deſire not onely to receive the word into their liking, but to be received into its likenes; not onely to love it, but to live it.</p>
               <p n="351">351. God knowes the names of all the men in the world, and yet he knowes but few men by name.</p>
               <p n="352">352. To be a <hi>ſervant,</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time put for a ſin, as to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of ſin, or ſervant of men; <hi>ſometime</hi> 'tis put for a curſe, as ſervant of ſervants ſhalt thou be, ſaid <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>Cham: Sometime</hi> 'tis put for an honour, when a man is called, and is the ſervant of God.</p>
               <pb n="259" facs="tcp:55955:84"/>
               <p n="353">353. As there is joy in Heaven at the converſion of a ſinner, ſo there is a kinde of joy in Hell, when one ſins that is converted.</p>
               <p n="354">354. Its a great piece of wiſdom ſo to order our condition and converſation in this world, that we may be able to attend upon God without diſtraction; <hi>a diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted man can do but little, and that little cannot be well done:</hi> duties are well done, when done with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and ſutable frame of heart, but the diſtracted man hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="355">355. The fear of man makes men to ſin, but the fear of God keeps men from ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5. Your eyes ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, and ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing good and evil.
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His eyes indeed were o'pe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And then he had the skill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To know the difference</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Between the good and ill:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:55955:85"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then did he know how good</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Good was, when he had loſt it,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And evil too he knew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ah how dearly coſt it?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="356">356. Lawful things are often the occaſion of unlawful things: we ſhould uſe them then <hi>(for of them it may be ſaid, as the Apoſtle of the Law, the Law is good, if a man uſe it)</hi> lawfully. The ſins of the old world are deſcribed, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.27, 28. not by unlawful, or things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in themſelves, but becoming ſuch by the abuſe. They did eat and drink, &amp;c. which things are neceſſary to preſerve life, and yet by theſe they loſt their lives; <hi>they in theſe things ſinn'd away their lives from the earth, and their ſouls into bell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="357">357. Feaſting times are too too often ſinning times; 'tis true, <hi>its not ſinful to feaſi, if our feaſting be not ſinful;</hi> which that it may not be, we ſhould not ſpend too much care like <hi>Martha,</hi> nor too much
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:55955:85"/>coſt and time like <hi>Dives,</hi> who fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red deliciouſly every day: while we are eating and drinking, wee may be dying, <hi>(in remembrance whereof the Egyptians us'd to ſerve in a deaths head at their feaſts)</hi> and therefore in eating and drinking, we need be holy, and do that, and all to the glory of God.</p>
               <p n="358">358. That we might not think riches evil, God gives them to thoſe who are good, yea, to the choiceſt, the chiefeſt, the very beſt of good men, <hi>to whom he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gives any thing that is in it ſelf evil:</hi> and leſt we ſhould think ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the chiefeſt good, the beſt good, God gives them to them that are evil, <hi>to whom he never gives the chiefeſt good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="359">359. Love of pleaſure, and fear of ſuffering, are the two great things, which keep men from minding that which is their chiefe good; which if enjoy'd, would either free them from ſuffering, or
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:55955:86"/>fill them with pleaſure in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and make them ſay, as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, quam ſuave eſtiſtis ſuavitatibus carere,</hi> how ſweet is it to want the worlds ſweets.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>True reſt is not attain'd by ſpending of the yeer</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In pleaſure ſoft, ſweet ſhades, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds, and dainty cheer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe leave the ſoul as empty of content,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As doth a dream, when time of ſleep is ſpent.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There's more true joy in godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes tears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then in ſins pleaſures; he that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fears</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The God of Heaven, and humbly walks with him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He, he's the man that hath an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven within.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="360">360. It will much aggravate the condemnation of ſome, that they have been ſo careful of their bodies, and ſo careleſs of their ſouls; they are ſo taken up with
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:55955:86"/>the things of this world, <hi>(which are but half goods, for they reach but half, and the worſe half of man)</hi> that ye riſe early, go to bed late, and eat the bread of carefulneſs, for their bodily accommodations, when their poor ſouls may ſink or ſwim, that's left at ſix and ſeven, the ſoul is not in all their thoughts. <hi>One ſaid he had ſo much buſineſſe to do, that he muſt truſt God with his ſoul, he could not look after it.</hi> Moſt men are like the woman, who when her houſe was on fire, ſo minded the ſaving her goods, that ſhe forgate her childe, and left it burning in the fire; at laſt being minded of it, ſhe cries out, <hi>oh my childe, oh my childe!</hi> So men ſcrabble here for a little pelf, and let their ſouls be conſumed with the fiery heat of cares, and at death cry out, <hi>oh my ſoul, oh my ſoul!</hi> how (ah how) mad are moſt, that while they pamper their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſtarve their ſouls, for ſo much
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:55955:87"/>eating and drinking takes away their ſtomachs to ſpiritual things. What care and pains do men and women take to clothe and neatifie the body, when the poor ſoul go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth naked and bare, and hath not one rag of righteouſneſſe to cover it. So curious and nice about their dreſſing, and keeping their houſe, that there muſt not be one haire out of place, nor ſo much as a ſpot in a rubb'd room, yet ſo negligent of their ſouls, that that goes in its night-clothes, <hi>(undreſt)</hi> all the day long; that many times under a ſilken and ſattin ſute, there's a very courſe ſoul; in a clean neat houſe, a ſluttiſh ſoul; under a beautiful face, a deformed ſoul; under a fair out-ſide, a foul in-ſide; <hi>Would thou that readeſt beeſt not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Ah dear hearts, if the body be more worth then raiment, ſurely the ſoul is more worth then the body. Oh what a weight doth the Scripture lay upon this word <hi>Soul,</hi>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:55955:87"/>'tis the emphaſis of the Text where 'tis: Hear, and your <hi>ſoul</hi> ſhall live; He that ſinneth, wrongeth his own <hi>ſoul;</hi> Fear him that can kill the body, and throw the <hi>ſoul</hi> into Hell. What will it profit a man to gain the world, and loſe <hi>his ſoul?</hi> Soul-mercy is the <hi>greateſt mercy;</hi> Soul-promiſes <hi>the moſt precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes;</hi> Soul-ſalvation <hi>the greateſt ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> and therefore to neglect <hi>the ſoul,</hi> is the greateſt neglect; and that men and women will know at that day, when they ſhall cry out, woe unto us, we have rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded evil to our own <hi>ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="361">361. There is ſcarce any one thing whereof men and women are more proud <hi>(at leaſt wherein and whereby they ſhew their pride more)</hi> then apparel; though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there's no one thing <hi>(ſin it ſelf excepted)</hi> that we have more cauſe to be aſham'd of then our apparel, for they tell us that we are ſinners: <hi>Adam and his wife were
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:55955:88"/>naked, and were not aſhamed.</hi> Our ornaments are but badges of our ſin and ſhame; and 'tis to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe obſervable, that the ſame word in the Hebrew which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a garment, ſignifies treachery and prevarication, to ſhew that wee have committed treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, elſe there had not been need of a fig-leafe-apron to cover our nakedneſſe. <hi>Who now can be proud of being a ſinner?</hi> Who can finde in his heart to be proud of that, which tells him, that he hath loſt his innocency? Surely <hi>he that hath ſinned himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhame, ſhould be aſhamed of his ſin:</hi> and though it be a ſhame, and a ſin to go naked, yet when we are clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with our garments, wee ſhould be clothed with ſhame as with a garment.</p>
               <p n="362">362. He that will have his mind ſatisfied with earthly things, muſt not thinke to attaine it ſo much by increaſing the things he
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:55955:88"/>deſires, as by decreaſing his deſire to the things. <hi>Latius regnes, avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum domando ſpiritum, quam, &amp;c.</hi> mortificaton is the beſt way to ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="363">363. Few men get good, though moſt get goods by great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, many men grow much the worſe, and I never read but of onely one <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> that was the better, <hi>ſolus imperantium veſpaſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus mutatus in melius. Magiſtratus jndicat virum.</hi> Of how many may it be ſaid, as Tacitus of Galba, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium conſenſu capax imperii niſi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraſſet,</hi> no man ſitter to be an <hi>Emperour,</hi> if he had not been an <hi>Emperour;</hi> how many have been good common-wealths men, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Patriots, till they came to be ſtates men; as if men minded goodneſſe onely to make them great, and then <hi>nuncium mittunt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti,</hi> bid it farewell, as he that all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had a fiſhing net ſpread on his table <hi>till he got a Biſhopricke,</hi> and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:55955:89"/>then cauſed it to be laid aſide, ſaying he had what he fiſhed for.</p>
               <p n="364">364. All men came into the world alike, <hi>the poore as well as the rich,</hi> and all men ſhall goe out of the world alike, <hi>the rich as well as the poore;</hi> nothing more certaine then this, that we brought nothing into the world, nor ſhall we carry any thing out of this world: if therefore we have food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let us be content; for godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with a comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tency <hi>(we read it with contentment)</hi> is great gaine.</p>
               <p n="365">365. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy happineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some men are ſo unhappy in having happy wits, that they make their wit their happineſſe, jeaſting themſelves out of all that is earneſt, and like fooles make ſport of every thing, <hi>even ſin it ſelf;</hi> alas! what pitty 'tis that men ſo witty, ſhould have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o more wit then to deſtroy themſelves! <hi>a jeſting lie or a lie in jeſt may make a man lye in hell in earneſt.</hi> Though
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:55955:89"/>ſuch men looke on religion but as a nicety and an impertinent curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, as that which impriſons their genius, yet they will one day finde to their coſt and ſorrow, what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant things the pleaſures of ſin are, and that it will be no brave thing to have ſinn'd in braverie.</p>
               <p n="366">366. All temporall things are troubleſome, If they be good it's trouble to forgoe them, and when we ſee that they muſt be parted with, either we wiſh that they had not beene ſo good, or that we had never injoyed them; <hi>as ſome did of Auſtine when he dyed.</hi> If they be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, their preſence is troubleſome; and ſtill we wiſh either that they were good, or that we were eaſed of them. <hi>Good things are trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the event, and evill things in then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> they in the future, becauſe they ſhall come to an end, theſe in preſent, becauſe they doe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> men would looke to things which are Eternall, for
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:55955:90"/>they are good here, and will be better hereafter.</p>
               <p n="367">367. What a madneſſe is it in men to trouble themſelves and the world about the <hi>Orthographie</hi> of a word, as whether we ſhould write <hi>Faelix</hi> or Felix, and never ſtudy to be happy: to trifle away their precious houres about noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and dye fooles. <hi>They are but frivolous,</hi> idle and triviall writings, which are onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact and held together with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite choiſe words, and ranged to juſt ſmooth cadencies, unleſſe they be ſtuft full of notable ſaiyngs and wiſe ſentences, by which a man doth become not onely more eloquent, but more wiſe, which teacheth us not onely to ſpeake well but doe to well.</p>
               <p n="368">368. <hi>Philoſophy no religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was accounted among many purely true, and truely pure Philoſophy, <hi>for a man to know him ſelfe,</hi> to enjoy himſelfe, to center in
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:55955:90"/>himſelfe. But I am ſure 'tis true and pure religion, <hi>to know God,</hi> to to enjoy God, to center in God, ſo to live in contemplation of him, and in converſation with him, as if there were nothing elſe in the world to know: as if there were none to thinke of us, or for us to thinke upon; <hi>none to love us or for us to love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="369">369. All the Lords doings, but eſpecially his doings in our hearts, ſhould be marvelous in our eyes. According to the day of grace it ſhall be ſaid, what hath God wrought?</p>
               <p n="370">370. The Hebrews have a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>deus magis delectatur adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biis quam nominibus,</hi> God is more delighted in adverbs then in nounes: 'tis not ſo much the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that's done, but the manner how 'tis done that God minds. <hi>Not how much, but how well.</hi> 'Tis the well doing that meets with a well done. Let us therefore
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:55955:91"/>ſerve God not nominally or verbally, but adverbially.</p>
               <p n="371">371. We thinke it a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be knowne of a man and wiſh't well, <hi>and yet</hi> thereby we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neither white nor blacke, the better or worſe, rich or poore, for our knowledge is ſmall in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, limited in effects and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efficacious in operation: but 'tis not ſo with Gods Knowledge. <hi>Happy they that are knowne of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="372">372. Science in moſt, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the reſt make all cry out, there is a God.</p>
               <p n="373">373. There is no truer miſery then falſe joys.</p>
               <p n="374">374. Chriſtians many times ſin moſt when leaſt tempted, and ſin leaſt when moſt tempted.</p>
               <p n="375">375. 'Tis puniſhment as well (or indeed as ill) to take away the good which was formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, as to inflict an evill which was not formerly ſuffered.</p>
               <p n="376">376. He is an happy man that's
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:55955:91"/>beaten when the ſtroake is a ſtroake of love.</p>
               <p n="377">377. Though God would have ſinners hearts broaken, yet ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is he that he would not have them breake their hearts, nor be ſwallowed up with over-much ſorrow.</p>
               <p n="378">378. The good mans beſt and the bad mans worſt is to come: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3.9. I will ſay to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous it <hi>ſhall</hi> be well with them, they ſhall eat the fruit of their doings: ſay to the wicked, woe, it <hi>ſhal be</hi> ill with them, for the reward of their hand <hi>ſhall be</hi> given them. Oh this <hi>ſhall be;</hi> how ſweet will it be to the godly, and how bitter to the ungodly! men that like ſins work, will not like ſins wages, they that are content to ſin on earth will not find content in hell.</p>
               <p n="379">379. Man diſcovers himſelfe to be a ſinner by covering his ſin.</p>
               <p n="380">380. He that ſeeks Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy in Divinity ſeekes the dead
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:55955:92"/>among the living, and he that ſeeks Divinity in Philoſophy ſeekes the living among the dead; I may ſay as the Angel of Chriſt, religion is not here, ſhe is riſen.</p>
               <p n="381">381. Surely they doe not love God, who love any thing more then God; or, they love not God at all, who doe not love him more then all.</p>
               <p n="382">382. The love of God to any ſoul is good ground of glorying here, and to expect glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="275" facs="tcp:55955:92"/>
            <head>THE HEATHEN <hi>IMPROVED.</hi> OR, <hi>The</hi> Gibeonites <hi>hewing of wood and drawing of water for the Sanctuary.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>SCipio</hi> made his boaſt, that there was not one of his ſouldiers but would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture their lives for him, if it were to leap into the ſea, or to caſt themſelves down an high towre, if he required it. <hi>How much them ſhould Chriſtians be at Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and not love their lives unto the death,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing all his commands are holy, juſt, and good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When newes came to <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ageras</hi> of the death of his ſon, at
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:55955:93"/>which they thought he would have been much troubled, he ſaid, I begate him mortal. <hi>Should not Chriſtians much more quiet themſelves at the loſſe of children,</hi> which though they beget mortal, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of immortality.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Philoſopher walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, found a woman weeping, and asking her the reaſon, alas ſaid ſhe, <hi>I have broken my Pitcher;</hi> and walking another day, found ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther woman weeping, and asking her the reaſon, ſhe told him, <hi>her ſon was dead.</hi> He preſently ſayes, did that woman think that an earthen Pitcher would not break? and this woman, that a mortal man would not dye? <hi>Should we not expect that changeables will change?</hi> That the faſhion of this world will paſſe away? Wee ſhould ſo uſe creature-enjoyments, as if we were taking leave of them. Our mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of joy and ſorrow ſhould be known, becauſe the end of all things is at hand.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:55955:93"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Socrates</hi> when the Tyrant did threaten death to him, told him he was willing; nay, then ſaid the Tyrant, you ſhall live againſt your will: nay, but ſaid <hi>Socrates,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you do with me, it ſhall bee my will. And a certain Stoick ſpeaking of God, ſaid, <hi>quid vult volo, quid non vult nolo, vult ut vivam vivam, vult ut moriar, moriar.</hi> What God will, I will; what God nills, I will not; if he will that I live, I will live; if it be his pleaſure that Idye, I will dye. <hi>Ah how ſhould the will of Chriſtians ſtoop and lie down at the foot of Gods will;</hi> not my will, but thine be done.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Epiſtle Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory to his wife, on the death of a childe, among many other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments hath this. <hi>We muſt alwaies think well of what the Gods doe.</hi> And ſhall not Chriſtians think well of what God doth, and ſay as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> good is the word, and good is the work of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="278" facs="tcp:55955:94"/>
            <p n="6">6. A Roman ſervant knowing that his Maſter was ſought for to be put to death, put himſelf into his Maſters clothes, that he might be taken for him, and ſo was, and put to death, in memory whereof his Maſter erected a brazen ſtatue. <hi>Oh what Monuments ſhall we erect for Chriſt, who when we were to be put to death would die for us!</hi> for a good man ſome would dare to die, and greater love then this cannot be ſhown, then that a man may lay down his life for a friend; but behold, herein God manifeſteth and commendeth his love to us, that while we were yet ſinners, <hi>yea enemies,</hi> Chriſt dyed for us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Phoeion</hi> an <hi>Athenian</hi> Captain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemned to death, &amp; ſeeing one <hi>Cnippus</hi> conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to the ſame death, but very fearful, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts him with theſe words, is it not enough to thee that <hi>thou art to dve with Phocion?</hi> Should it not comfort us in our ſuffering, <hi>that we dye with Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="279" facs="tcp:55955:94"/>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Antonius</hi> after <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> was ſlain, brought forth his coat all bloody, and laid it before the people, ſaying, loe <hi>here is the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours coat.</hi> Whereupon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cryed out, ſlay the murtherers. <hi>Shall we not ſay ſo of ſin, which ſlew our Lord Chriſt, and would have ſlain us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Numa</hi> held, that the ſervice of God was greater honour then to be a King; and <hi>ſhall not Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans think ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Alexander</hi> diſtributing very large gifts, was askt what he would keep for himſelf? hee anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d hope; <hi>by hope are we ſaved.</hi> He hath a great deal who hath not ſo much hope of good, as a good hope.</p>
            <p n="11">11. 'Twas the ſaving of an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, <hi>Condo &amp; compono quae mox de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>romere poſſum;</hi> I lay in, and lay up, that I may lay out; and ſhall not Chriſtians do ſo?</p>
            <p n="12">12. When <hi>Pericles</hi> went into the
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:55955:95"/>Pulpit to make Orations to the people, he would make his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the gods, that nothing might goe out of his mouth, but what might be to the purpoſe; <hi>a good example for Preachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Phocions</hi> wife having many Jewels ſhewn her by a Lady, ſaid, <hi>all my Jewels are there,</hi> pointing to her husband; and <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Gracchi,</hi> his ſons coming in when a Lady was ſhewing her Jewels, <hi>hi ſoli ſunt ornamenta mea,</hi> theſe are mine ornaments; much more ſhould a Chriſtian point to Chriſt, and ſay, <hi>Chriſt is my all in all?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. It was the ſaying of <hi>Metellus,</hi> that to do evil was a thing too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, to doe good without danger, was a thing too common; but to doe good with danger, was the part of an honeſt and religious man.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Mans nature (ſaith <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi>) cannot bring forth any
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:55955:95"/>fruit, which hath not ſome ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Its ſaid of <hi>Cato,</hi> that no man ſaw him to be changed, though he liv'd in a time when the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth was ſo often chang'd; <hi>he was the ſame in every condition, though he ran through variety of conditions:</hi> O that it could bee ſaid of the Chriſtians, that they were <hi>Catoes</hi> in our dayes; that they did exerciſe &amp; exert the like gracious, humble, and heavenly frames and acts in theſe times of their proſperity and advancement, as they did, or ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe in the dayes of their adverſity, when they were under the feet of them that are now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The <hi>Mahometans</hi> live in ſuch an exemplary concord, that they ſeldome break into ill lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; but if they do ſo, a third man will reprove him, with a <hi>fie muſſul-man,</hi> fall out! and all is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd. Were it not to bee wiſht
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:55955:96"/>that the <hi>Mahometans</hi> were Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and <hi>in this</hi> that Chriſtians were <hi>Mahometans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſaid to <hi>Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> asking an unreaſonable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of him, thou canſt bee to good Poet to ſing againſt the rule of Muſick, nor I a good Governor to do any thing againſt the Law. <hi>Juſtice muſt be preferred before cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Ariſtides</hi> 'tis ſaid was never the prouder for any honour, nor thought himſelf diſgrac'd by any overthrow, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing alwaies of this minde, that it was the duty of an honeſt Citizen to be ever ready to offer his body and life to doe his Countrey ſervice, without reſpect and hope of reward of money, or for honour and glory. <hi>'Tis good to live above encouragements and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, and to minde nothing ſo much as our duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. A poor Scholar <hi>(Aeſchines)</hi> having nothing to give his Tuto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="283" facs="tcp:55955:96"/>
               <hi>(Socrates)</hi> for his pains taking with him; when others gave gifts, Sir, ſaid he, I have nothing to give you, but if you will take me, I will beſtow my ſelf upon you. Wilt thou ſo, ſaid <hi>Socrates,</hi> nay, then I will give thee thy ſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo inſtructed him in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. <hi>Chriſt hath taken more pains for and about us, and ſhall we not give our ſelves to him?</hi> Who will give us our ſelves better again, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us in Divinity to the ſaving of our ſouls.</p>
            <p n="21">21. A great man having injur'd a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his ſervant to intreat or charge him that hee would not write againſt him; by whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e return<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d this anſwer, <hi>that he was not at leiſure to think of him.</hi> Oh ſweet living, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries intermeddle not with the ſoul, but it can enjoy it ſelf, and employ it ſelf without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Valerius Maximus,</hi> tells us of
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:55955:97"/>a young Noble man that attended on <hi>Alexander</hi> while he was ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and while he held the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer for Incenſe, there fell a coale upon his fleſh, and burnt it ſo, as the very ſent of it was in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of all that were about him; and yet becauſe he would not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb <hi>Alexander</hi> in his ſervice, he did not ſtir to put off the fire from him, but holds ſtill his Cenſer. <hi>What care ſhould we take then that we may attend upon the true and living God without diſturbance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> deſired of his gods nothing in this world to make his life happy, but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that was content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be able to bear any wrong or injury, and to continue in a quiet temper of ſpirit whatever befell him. <hi>Oh if Chriſtians had but the ſpirit,</hi> I will not ſay of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> but of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> oh how happy might they be in all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions!</p>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:55955:97"/>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Marius Curio</hi> ſitting at home at dinner with a diſh of Turnips, ſome of <hi>Romes</hi> adverſaries ſent him many bribes and promiſes of great rewards, to have made him unfaithful to his Countrey; but ſaid he, <hi>that man that can be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſuch fare as I have, will not be tempted with your rewards.</hi> Could we be content with a little, the temptations of much, would not much tempt us.</p>
            <p n="25">25. One ſaying to a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, Couldſt thou but pleaſe <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius,</hi> thou need'ſt not eat herbs and roots; the Philoſopher an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, could'ſt thou but eat herbs and roots, thou needeſt not to pleaſe <hi>Dionyſius.</hi> To the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-minded, temptations of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are no great temptations.</p>
            <p n="26">26. When <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> deſign'd war againſt the Romans, one <hi>Cineas</hi> ſaid to him, if we overcome the Romans, what benefit ſhall wee have of the victory? We ſhall then
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:55955:98"/>anſwer'd <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> overcame all the reſt of <hi>Italy</hi> with eaſe; but ſaid <hi>Cineas,</hi> when we have won <hi>Italy,</hi> what ſhall we doe then? Why then ſaid <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> we will paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Africa,</hi> and conq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er <hi>Carthage;</hi> but ſaid <hi>Cineas,</hi> when we have all in our hands, what ſhall wee doe then? Why then ſaid <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> we will be quiet, and take our eaſe, and make merry: and why ſaid he, may we not do ſo now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further travel and trouble? Many perſons deſign theſe and theſe things, and then give their ſoul a <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> a writ of eaſe. But <hi>he that cannot be quiet in his preſent ſtate, cannot promiſe himſelf quiet in a future ſtate;</hi> we many times goe from quiet for quiet, and from reſt for reſt, and loſe what we have for hopes of more. <hi>Why not quiet now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of a certain people, that to manifeſt their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking and diſdaining of men o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-much dejected by any afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:55955:98"/>did condemn them in token of diſgrace to weare womens clothes: <hi>Seeing they did unman them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they ſhould go as women.</hi> If thou faint in the day of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thy ſtrength is ſmall; too many Chriſtians I fear would come under the condemnation and diſgrace of this Law.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Seneca</hi> hath this ſimilitude to ſet out the great evil of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring under ſmall afflictions. Suppoſe, ſaith he, a man to have a very fair houſe to dwell in, with very fair Orchards and Gardens, ſet about with brave tall Trees, for ornament; <hi>what a moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable thing were it in this man to murmure,</hi> becauſe the wind blows a few leaves off the Trees, though they hang full of fruits. <hi>If God take a little, and leave us much, ſhall we be diſcontent?</hi> If he take our ſon, and give us his own; if he cauſe the Trees to bring forth fruit, ſhall we be angry if the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:55955:99"/>winde blow away the leaves?</p>
            <p n="29">29. Since God, ſaid <hi>Socrates,</hi> is ſo careful for you, what need you to be ſo careful for your ſelves? How like is this to that of Chriſt, Take no thought, &amp;c. for your heavenly Father knowes that ye have need of theſe things: <hi>let your converſation be without care,</hi> for God careth for you.</p>
            <p n="30">30. When <hi>Socrates</hi> in a diſpute did bitterly fall upon one of his Familiars, ſaid <hi>Plato</hi> to him, it had been better to have ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe things in private; and replyed <hi>Socrates,</hi> ſhouldſt not thou alſo have told me ſo in private? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prcofes are not very like to take,</hi> when in reproving we commit the evil which we condemn.</p>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Socrates</hi> wittily rebuked the pride of <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> when he proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boaſted how much land he had that lay together, by bringing him a Map of the world, ſaying, pray <hi>ſhew me where your Land lyeth
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:55955:99"/>here?</hi> One prick of a pin would have deſcribed it all. <hi>Alas, why doe we boaſt?</hi> The whole world is nothing to Heaven, and that which we have, is nothing to the whole. Shall we be proud of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes and duſt?</p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>Cato</hi> among other things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of this, that ever he ſpent 1 day idle. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the elder be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded, if he had nothing to doe, <hi>God forbid,</hi> quoth he, that ever it ſhould be ſo with me. <hi>Scipio</hi> the elder, ſaid, that he was never leſſe alone, then when moſt alone, when he was at leiſure, he had the greateſt buſineſſe. <hi>What a ſhame is it to Chriſtians to be found idle,</hi> and trifling away that time, which Heathens made ſo much of? <hi>Heu perdidt diem.</hi> Alas, I have loſt a day, ſaid <hi>Titus Veſpaſian,</hi> of the day wherein he had done no good.</p>
            <p n="33">33. <hi>Tully</hi> thought him not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the name of a man, that ſpent
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:55955:100"/>a whole day in pleaſures of the fleſh. And <hi>Socrates</hi> had ſuch a vile eſteeme of ſin, that he thought it one of the greateſt torments of men in another life, to be bound to the ſins they moſt delighted in in this life. And <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid of himſelfe, I am too great, and borne to greater things then that I ſhould be a ſlave to my body. <hi>Oh Chriſtians what doe you doe more then others?</hi> will not you live above the fleſh and deeds thereof.</p>
            <p n="34">34. Remember ſaid one to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus</hi> that thou art ſon to a King, and that will keepe thee from baſe courſes. And when <hi>Philip</hi> would have <hi>Alexander</hi> (who was wery ſwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t on foot) to run in the <hi>Olympicke</hi> games, I could be well content quoth he, provided they were Kings and Princes to run with me. <hi>Let Chriſtians then ſtand on their birth and name,</hi> to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing below the ſtate of Kings ſons, nothing unbecomming ſuch
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:55955:100"/>as are heaven-borne. Is it for Kings ſons <hi>O Lemuel?</hi> is it for Chriſtians to be vaine, proud, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous? &amp;c. <hi>Vellem ſi non eſſem Imperator,</hi> ſaid Scipio.</p>
            <p n="35">35. When <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaw an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant great danger neare him, now ſaye's he here's a danger or tryall fit for the mind of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Chriſtians ſhould ſay of the greateſt tryals, <hi>here's a tryall for a Chriſtian.</hi> As 'tis ſaid of <hi>Ignatius</hi> that when he felt his fleſh and bones begin to be ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the teeth of wild beaſts, now ſays he <hi>I begin to be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> For as Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſaid in priſon, the ſkill of a Pilot is beſt knowne <hi>in a tempeſt,</hi> the valour of a Captaine <hi>in a battel,</hi> and the worth of a Chriſtian <hi>in time of tryal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">36. When the Senators had wounded <hi>Caeſar</hi> with many ſore wounds, <hi>Brutus</hi> alſo gave him a a ſtabbe, with that he lookes upon him and ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; what! <hi>and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:55955:101"/>thou my ſon?</hi> all the wounds that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> receive from the world goe not ſo much to his heart as when his children wound him, <hi>what and you my ſons and daughers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">37. When <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaw <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> ſo well content with a little, he ſaid to thoſe that mockt at his condition, if I were not <hi>Alexander,</hi> I would wiſh to be <hi>Diogenes.</hi> Many could be almoſt Chriſtians; <hi>were it not</hi> for this honour, theſe riches and pleaſures, I would be a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="38">38. When <hi>Alexander</hi> on a time ſung and played curiouſly on an harpe at a banquet, his father <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> ſaid to him, art not thou aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>to have skill in theſe trifles?</hi> Ah how many chriſtians borne to better and more noble imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then dancing and playing, have <hi>(alas have)</hi> more ſkill in ſuch things then in better. But are ye not aſham'd? &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="39">39. <hi>Alexander</hi> when he ſate in
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:55955:101"/>judgement, would ſtop one of his eares to heare the other party withall. <hi>Our tale is good till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is told;</hi> we ſhould not condeme one report but heare both ſides. He that condemnes a man till he heare him, doth unjuſtly, though there be juſt cauſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn him.</p>
            <p n="37">37. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Fabricius,</hi> that he was ſo juſt, as you might ſooner turne the courſe of the Sun, then turne <hi>Fabricius</hi> from doing juſtice. And <hi>Ariſtides</hi> was ſo famous for juſtice, that he was called by the name of <hi>Ariſtides</hi> the juſt. When two came before him, ſaid he that accuſed the other, <hi>Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> this man did you ſuch an jniury at ſuch a time, to which and whom <hi>Ariſtides</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Friend I ſit not here to heare what he hath done againſt me, but what he hath done againſt thee. Oh that Chriſtians were ſo famous for holineſſe, and juſtice, that
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:55955:106"/>it might be ſaid, <hi>there's ſuch an one the humble,</hi> ſuch an one <hi>the meek,</hi> ſuch an one <hi>the holy,</hi> ſuch an one <hi>the juſt,</hi> ſuch an one <hi>the patient:</hi> it could have been ſaid of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Moſes, Job,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>why not of us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">41. When the Tyrant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> ſhould be put into a mortar, and beaten to pieces with an iron peſtle, hee cryes out to his perſecuters, you doe but beat the veſſel, the husk of <hi>Anaxarchus,</hi> you do not beat me. Men may kill the body, and they can do no more.</p>
            <p n="42">42. <hi>Agrippa</hi> having ſuffered im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment for wiſhing <hi>Caius</hi> to be Emperour, was the firſt that was preferr'd by <hi>Caius</hi> when he came to be Emperour, and had a chain of gold given him as heavy as the chain of iron that was on him in priſon. <hi>If we ſuffer for Chriſt, we ſhall alſo reign with him;</hi> and if our afflictions abound, our conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:55955:106"/>ſhall abound much more; for our light affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding eternal weight of glory. Men may ſuffer for Chriſt, but they ſhall not loſe by it.</p>
            <p n="43">43. The <hi>Gauls</hi> when they had taſted the ſweet wine of <hi>Italy,</hi> askt where the Grapes grew, and would never bee quiet till they came there: they that taſte the ſweet wine of heavenly conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, will never be quiet till they come to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="44">44. <hi>Alexanders</hi> body was of ſuch an exact and excellent conſtitution, that it gave a ſweet ſent like to a perfume. <hi>So ſhould a Chriſtians converſation,</hi> be a ſweet ſmelling ſavour to God and men.</p>
            <p n="45">45. 'Twas a ſad and lamentable expreſſion of <hi>Lyſimachus,</hi> who had loſt his Kingdome for one draught of water, <hi>O dii, quam brevis volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis gratia ex rege me feci ſervü:</hi> Oh for
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:55955:107"/>what a ſhort pleaſure, have I made my ſelf of a King a ſlave. Alas, for what poor and ſhort enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, doe men run the hazard of loſing the Kingdome of God and their ſouls.</p>
            <p n="46">46. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> told <hi>Mark Antonie,</hi> 'tis not for you to fiſh for Gudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but for Towns, Forts, and Caſtles. 'Tis below Chriſtians to look after low and little things, <hi>ad majora nati,</hi> they are born, that is, new-born, to look after the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="47">47. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> that he accounted it below his ſtate to ſtoop to take up the ſpoils <hi>(though chains of gold)</hi> which the enemy had ſcattered in the way, but ſaid to one of his followers, thou maiſt, for thou art not <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles.</hi> 'Tis for worldly ſpirits, 'tis below the ſtate of heaven-born ſpirits to ſtoop to earthly things. Worldlings may, <hi>they are not The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles,</hi> they are not Saints.</p>
            <pb n="197" facs="tcp:55955:107"/>
            <p n="48">48. 'Twas accounted ſo great an honour to be free of <hi>Rome,</hi> that who ever was free of that City, was not to be free of any other. Shall not Saints think it honour enough to be free Denizens of the City, the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above?</p>
            <p n="49">49. When one preſented <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater</hi> King of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> with a a book that treated of happineſſe, his anſwer was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am not at leiſure. How many are there that cannot find leiſure to receive the book and word of happineſſe ſent by Chriſt to ſave their ſouls?</p>
            <p n="50">50. <hi>Cato</hi> was ſo grave and good a man, that none would ſin in his preſence: whence it grew to a proverbial Caveat among them one to another, <hi>Cave tibi, ſpectat Cato;</hi> take heed what you doe, <hi>Cato</hi> ſees you. O how ſhould we ſtand in awe of the All-ſeeing God, and ſay to our own hearts, and one another, <hi>Cave tibi, Deus</hi>
               <pb n="290" facs="tcp:55955:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="291" facs="tcp:55955:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:55955:105"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:55955:105"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:55955:102"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:55955:102"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:55955:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:55955:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:55955:108"/>
               <hi>ſpectat,</hi> take heed, for God looks on.</p>
            <p n="51">51. <hi>Seneca</hi> to <hi>Lucilius.</hi> Live with men, as if God ſaw thee; and pray to God, as if men heard thee.</p>
            <p n="52">52. When King <hi>Demetrius</hi> had ſacket and razed the City of <hi>Megoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> to the very foundation, he demanded of <hi>Stilpo the Philoſopher,</hi> what loſſes he had ſuſtain'd? none at all, ſaid <hi>Stilpo,</hi> for warre can make no ſpoil of virtue; and 'tis ſaid of <hi>Bias,</hi> that his Motto was, <hi>Omnia mea mecum porto,</hi> I carry all my goods with me, <hi>viz.</hi> his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Ah how ſhould Chriſtians live above theſe things, &amp; like <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakkuk,</hi> rejoyce in the Lord, and the exerciſe of a gracious ſpirit, and a good conſcience, when there is nothing but loſs and want on every ſide.</p>
            <p n="53">53. <hi>Ariſton</hi> ſaid, that neither a bath, nor an Oration doth any good, unleſs it purifie, the one the skin, the other the heart;
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:55955:108"/>
               <hi>that's good, that doth good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="54">54. When <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> was to marry his daughter, there were two ſutors, the one rich and a fool, and the other wiſe, but not rich; and being aſkt which of the two he had rather his daughter ſhould have, he anſwered <hi>mallem virum ſine pecunia, quam pecuniam ſine viro.</hi> I had rather ſhe ſhould have a man without money, then money without a man. The beſt of marriage is in the man or the woman, not in the means, or the money.</p>
            <p n="55">55. <hi>Ariſtides</hi> to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant, demanding his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in marriage, ſaid, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee her burnt then married to a Tyrant. <hi>'Tis better not to marry, then not to marry in the Lord.</hi> 'Tis poor honour to be married to a wicked man of honour.</p>
            <p n="56">56. When one aſkt <hi>Alexander</hi> how he could ſleep ſo ſoundly and ſecurely in the midſt of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:55955:109"/>he told him that <hi>Parmenio</hi> watcht; he might not well ſleep when <hi>Parmenio</hi> watcht. Oh how ſecurely may they ſleep, over whom he watcheth, that never ſlumbers nor ſleeps? I will, ſaid <hi>David,</hi> lay me down and ſleep, for thou <hi>Lord,</hi> makeſt me to dwell in ſafety.</p>
            <p n="57">57. <hi>Xenophanes</hi> when one <hi>Laſus</hi> call'd him coward, becauſe hee would not play at dice with him, ſaid, I confeſs I am a very coward in theſe things that are evil, for I dare do nothing at all. <hi>'Tis better to be reproacht for not doing evil, then to do evil to avoid reproach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="58">58. <hi>Pericles</hi> being requeſted by a friend to bear falſe witneſſe in his behalf, and to binde it with an Oath, told him, I am your friend <hi>as far as the Altar,</hi> as if he had ſaid, ſaving my conſcience, and duty to the gods, when any would have us ſin, let's tell them, your friend, or your ſervant, <hi>uſque ad
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:55955:109"/>aras,</hi> I will do any thing to pleaſe and pleaſure you, except diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God and my conſcience.</p>
            <p n="59">59. When <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> his own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would have had him give ſentence in a cauſe contrary to the Law; father, quoth he, your ſelf have taught me from my very childhood, to obey the Laws; I will therefore bee obedient to your good precepts, and paſſe no judgement againſt the Law. In ſuch caſes wee ſhould know no man after the fleſh, but be as <hi>Levi,</hi> who knew not his own father.</p>
            <p n="60">60. <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> ſcoffing at the great number of Sophiſters in his dayes, ſaid, that in old time hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly could there be found ſeven wiſe men throughout the world; but in our dayes, quoth he, much adoe there is to finde ſo many fools: <hi>'tis a bad age when men are wiſe in their own eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="61">61. One attempting to kill <hi>Prometheus</hi> the Theſſalian, run him
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:55955:110"/>ſo deep with his ſword into an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume, that he let out the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and ſaved his life; ſo ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> a reproachful ſpeech deliver'd in anger, or evil will, is the cauſe of healing ſome malady in the ſoul, which before was hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or neglected.</p>
            <p n="62">62. <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was wont to ſay, that wee were then in beſt caſe, when we did approach unto the Gods, and worſhip them; <hi>'tis good for us to draw near unto God,</hi> yea ſo good, that 'tis never well with us but when we are with God.</p>
            <p n="63">63. When newes was brought <hi>Zeno,</hi> that his ſhip with all the fraught and merchandiſe therein was caſt away; thou haſt done well, O fortune, ſaid he, to drive us to our ſtudying Gown, and our Philoſophers life again. We ſhould look upon loſſes and afflictions, as that which is to <hi>draw or drive us nearer unto God</hi> in holineſſe of life.</p>
            <p n="64">64. When <hi>Alexander</hi> came to
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:55955:110"/>
               <hi>Diogenes,</hi> and aſkt him if he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any thing, and would requeſt any thing of him, nothing ſaid he, but that thou wouldeſt ſtand out of the Sun. <hi>To a gracious heart there's nothing comparable to the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Son of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="65">65. A <hi>Perſian</hi> King had one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, whoſe place and office it was, to ſay unto him every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as he entred into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; ariſe my Lord, and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe affairs for which <hi>Meſoromaſdes, i. e.</hi> the great God would have you to provide. <hi>Wee ſhould bethink us every night what we have done, and every morning what we have to doe</hi> for and in obedience to the great God.</p>
            <p n="66">66. God, ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> hateth and puniſheth thoſe, who will ſeem to imitate him in Thunder, Lightning, and Sun beams; but thoſe that be followers of his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and goodneſs, he loveth and advanceth. <hi>An admirable obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:55955:111"/>and ſutable to the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="67">67. <hi>Nicias</hi> a Painter was ſo affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately bent to his art, that he often forgate himſelf, and would ask his ſervants whether he had dined or no? The intentneſs of <hi>Archimedes</hi> alſo is famouſly known. Oh that we could be, if but now and then ſo intent at me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="68">68. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the younger us'd to ſay, that he kept and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many Learned men, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did eſteem them ſo much, <hi>but</hi> for that he deſir'd to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their ſake. May we not fear that many entertain Preachers and Miniſters on the like account and for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p n="69">69. After <hi>Dioniſius</hi> was depos'd from his royal dignity and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, one aſkt him what good <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> and all his Philoſophy had done him? this benefit I have thereby, ſaid he, that I have learned to bear with patience this change
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:55955:111"/>and alteration of my fortune. And when one judged <hi>Socrates</hi> by his Phyſiognomy to be of a churliſh ſullen, froward, and dogged diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, for which the people were ready to beat him, knowing <hi>Socrates</hi> to be one of the meekeſt and ſereneſt ſpirited men that could be; <hi>Socrates</hi> himſelf ſaid, 'tis true, my diſpoſition is as he hath ſaid, <hi>but Philoſophy hath made the alteration.</hi> Ah! ſhall they ſpeak more of the efficacy of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, then Chriſtians of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity? <hi>God forbid.</hi> Oh that Chriſtians would make it appear that they have learned the truth as 'tis in Jeſus, and that the grace of God hath appeared to, and taught them, by holding forth the word of life, and ſhewing the virtues of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who excelled all that did vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
            <p n="70">70. When word was brought to <hi>Alexander,</hi> that at a feaſt there
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:55955:112"/>was one that did miſ-call him and revile him, 'tis ſaid he a rovall and Kingly act to ſuffer blame for well-doing. <hi>When ye doe well and ſuffer for it and take it patiently, this is acceptable unto God.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p n="71">71. After <hi>Antigonus</hi> had bin a long time ſicke of a lingring diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and well recovered againe, he ſaid, we have gotten no harme by this long ſickeneſſe; for this hath taught us not to be ſo proud, by putting us in mind that we are but mortall. <hi>'Twas good for me that I was aflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="72">72. <hi>Paedaretus</hi> being not choſen one of the great councell conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of three hundred men, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with joy, ſaying, I am glad that in the city of <hi>Sparta</hi> there are found three hundred better men then my ſelfe. <hi>We ſhould rejoyce in common good, though carried on by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and we our ſelves have no hand in it.</p>
            <p n="73">73. <hi>Endamedas</hi> ſeeing <hi>Zenoerates</hi>
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:55955:112"/>an old man ſtudying philoſophy with young ſchollars in an Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy, demanded of one that ſtood by what he was, and being told that he was one that ſought after virtue, ſaid he, if he be ſtill ſtudying and ſtill ſeeking it, when will he uſe and practiſe it. Alas <hi>how many are there that are ever learning, but never come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="74">74. When <hi>Hepheſtion</hi> quarrelled with <hi>Craterus, Alexander</hi> reproved him thus: what power haſt thou of thy ſelfe? what couldſt thou doe, and where wouldſt thou be, if a man ſhould take <hi>Alexander</hi> from thee. Some men looke high, who are upheld by others counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and power, or elſe muſt be as low as the earth they tread on.</p>
            <p n="75">75. <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> the great being aſkt how a man might gaine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the greateſt name and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if (ſaid he) <hi>a man ſay well and doe better.</hi> No ſuch good
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:55955:113"/>name as that which good workes doe get.</p>
            <p n="76">76. <hi>Alexander</hi> Commanded his treaſurer to give <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> whatſoever he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and when his traſurer brought him word that he craved an exceſſive ſum, <hi>viz.</hi> an hundred talents, The man ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> doth very well, knowing as he doth that he hath ſuch a friend of me as both can and will beſtow ſo much upon him. <hi>We may aſke great things of the great God,</hi> being aſſured that he both can and will make good his promiſes. <hi>He will give like a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="77">77. When the Pilot of <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> his owne Gally came to him and told him that the enemie had a farr greater number of ſhips then they, ſaide hee, being here in perſon, <hi>for how many ſhips doeſt thou reckon me?</hi> how many ſoever and how ſtrong ſoever our enemies be, yet having <hi>Chriſt</hi> with us, there is
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:55955:113"/>more for us, then there is againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nil deſperandum Chriſto duce &amp; auſpice Chriſto,</hi> if God be with us, who can be againſt us? they ſhould never deſpair nor fear, that have God on their ſide.</p>
            <p n="79">79. One day when <hi>Phocion</hi> had deliver'd his advice among a great aſſembly of people, and ſeeing that with one accord they all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved his ſpeech, he was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and turning toward his friends, ſaid, What, have I ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſome words that are not good, that this people ſpeak wel of it? <hi>A good man may in ſome caſes be jealous of himſelf when the bad ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves him.</hi> Woe unto you when all men ſpeak well of you.</p>
            <p n="80">80. One asking <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> the great, what children ſhould learn when they were young? anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that which they were to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe when they were grown up. <hi>Teach a childe the trade of his way,</hi>
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:55955:114"/>and when he is old he will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it.</p>
            <p n="81">81. 'Tis ſaid of the <hi>Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that they never aſkt how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny their enemies were, but where they were. So ſhould Chriſtians fall on and fight the good fight of faith, without conſidering the numbers that come againſt them.</p>
            <p n="82">82. <hi>Alexander</hi> being aſkt why he did not gather money and lay it up in a publick treaſury? for fear ſaid he, leſt being keeper thereof, I ſhould be infected and corrupted thereby. <hi>A good Caution for them that love to bear the bag.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="83">83. A Philoſopher being askt why rich men attended not the gates of Philoſophers? becauſe ſaid he, they know not their need of Philoſophy. The reaſon ſo few attend at wiſdomes gates, is becauſe they know not the need they ſtand in of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="84">84. <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid of them that would put him to death, they
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:55955:114"/>may take away my life, but they cannot hurt me. <hi>Men may kill Saints, but they cannot hurt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="85">85. When there were commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Caeſars</hi> Army, the very name of <hi>Quirites</hi> huſht them. Oh that <hi>the name of Chriſt</hi> might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail to huſh the commotions that are among profeſſors, who bite and devour one another, and doe themſelves more hurt then their enemies could.</p>
            <p n="86">86. <hi>Polemon</hi> coming into the ſchool of <hi>Zenocrates,</hi> with his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken company crown'd with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands purpoſely to out-face him and his Philoſop hy; <hi>Zenocrates</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs went on with a lecture of temperance, preſſing it ſo far, that it wrought much upon <hi>Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> yea ſo much, that he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately abandoned his former courſes, and became his diſciple, and proved the ſtricteſt of the whole Sect. <hi>How many have been thus caught at Sermons,</hi> and of vile
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:55955:115"/>ſinners become ſtrict Saints?</p>
            <p n="87">87. One of King <hi>Cyrus</hi> Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and a great Favorite, having but little eſtate, when he was to marry his daughter, was aſkt, Sir, where will you have a portion for your daughter? he anſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Cyrus</hi> is my friend. Saints may ſay much more, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord is my friend.</p>
            <p n="88">88. <hi>Furius Camillus</hi> was alwaies like himſelf, the ſame man, not pufft up by being dictator, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dejected when forbidden his Countrey. The Chriſtians Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhould be that of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths, ſemper eadem,</hi> alwaies the ſame; not to be lifted up, when lifted up, nor caſt down, when caſt down.</p>
            <p n="89">89. Its written that <hi>Timotheus</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> after he had in the account he gave to the ſtate of his Government, often interlaced this ſpeech, <hi>in this fortune had no hand,</hi> he never proſpered after in
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:55955:115"/>any thing he undertook. See <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.12, 13. <hi>VVhen men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own God, God diſ-owns men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="90">90. <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> being aſkt what he had got by Learning? Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he could talk with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he could live alone, he need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to go abroad, and be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to others for delight: Much more may he ſay this, <hi>yea and much more then this,</hi> who hath learned Chriſt, and the truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="91">91. Either we muſt not come to great perſons, or coming ſeek to pleaſe them, ſaid <hi>Aeſop</hi> to <hi>Solon;</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we muſt not come to them at all, or coming tell them the truth, and counſel them for the beſt, ſaid <hi>Solon</hi> to <hi>Aeſop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="92">92. <hi>Zenophon</hi> tells us, that when <hi>Cyrus</hi> gave <hi>Artabaſus</hi> one of his Courtiers, a Cup of Gold, he gave <hi>Chryſantas</hi> his Favourite nothing at that time but a kiſſe, which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned this ſpeech from <hi>Artabaſus</hi>
               <pb n="214" facs="tcp:55955:116"/>to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> Sir, the Cup you gave me was not ſo good gold as the kiſſe you gave <hi>Chryſantas.</hi> God gives wicked men many times <hi>gold, but without kiſſes,</hi> and godly men <hi>kiſſes, but without gold;</hi> yet the godly may ſay, there's more gold in their kiſſes, then in the others gold.</p>
            <p n="93">93. There was a long feud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> but being both employed in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for their Countrey, <hi>Ariſtides beſpake Themiſtocles thus,</hi> If we be wiſe, its high time we ſhould now leave off this vain envy and ſpite we have a long time born each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that we ſhould enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another ſort of envy more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and profitable; I mean which of us two, ſhall doe his beſt endeavour to ſave <hi>Greece.</hi> To which <hi>Themiſtocles made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,</hi> I am ſorry, <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your honeſty appeareth no greater then mine; but ſeeing it is ſo that you have deſerved the
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:55955:116"/>honour in beginning and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch a commendable ſtrife between us, I will henceforth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to exceed you in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing this your deſire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh that Saints would learn from Heathen, to lay aſide their particular differences, to mind publick advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi> Shall, alas! ſhall Heathens be better at ſelf-denial then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</p>
            <p n="94">94. <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> ready to periſh with thirſt, was conſtrain'd to drink puddle-water, of which he profeſt that he never drank wine with more delight. <hi>To the hungry ſouls, every bitter thing is ſweet.</hi> In times of ſtraits, a little is much, and that that's very bad, is very good.</p>
            <p n="95">95. When <hi>Archimedes</hi> had found out the reſolution of a queſtion in the Mathematicks, he cries out as one raviſht <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I have found it, I have found it: So when a ſoul that hath been ſick of love
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:55955:117"/>for Chriſt Jeſus, meets with him, ſhe raviſh'd with joy, cries out, I have found him whom my ſoul loveth.</p>
            <p n="96">96. Said one, and I ſuppoſe a <hi>Roman,</hi> it is unbecomming a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſpirit, to cry out, I am undone, while <hi>Caeſar</hi> is ſafe. <hi>Oh how unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Chriſtians to cry out I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, while Chriſt and their intereſt in him is ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="97">97. <hi>Galienus</hi> the Emperour, when the report came to him that <hi>Aegypt</hi> was loſt, what then, (ſaid he) cannot I live without the flax of <hi>Aegypt?</hi> And when word was brought that a great part of his Dominions in <hi>Aſia</hi> was waſted, what then (ſaid he) cannot I live without the delicacies of <hi>Aſia?</hi> Oh for Chriſtians to ſpeak thus of any of their loſſes, from a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of acquaintance with and enjoyment of God, is excellent. <hi>'Tis like, very like, yea very much like that of Habakkuk,</hi> c. 3.17. though
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:55955:117"/>the fig-tree ſhould not bloſſome, neither ſhall fruit be in the Vines, the labour of the Olive ſhall fail, the fields ſhall yield no meat, the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no herd in the ſtalls, yet I will rejoyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my ſalvation. <hi>What?</hi> cannot I live and rejoyce without the flax of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and the delicacies of <hi>Aſia?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="98">98. God, ſaid <hi>Socrates,</hi> will be worſhipped with that kinde of worſhip onely which himſelf hath commanded; and he will not be worſhipped, ſaid <hi>Cicero,</hi> with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, but with piety. Oh that Chriſtians would hear and learn!</p>
            <p n="99">99. When <hi>Caeſar</hi> was about 25 years of age, he wept, that he had lived ſo long, and done no great exploits; when as <hi>Alexander</hi> at that age, had conquer'd almoſt all the world. How many ſouls
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:55955:118"/>that have lived <hi>to twenty five, yea to thirty five, it may be fourty five, and more yeares,</hi> and have not yet done any thing to the conquering of the world, the ſubduing of ſin, the working out the ſalvation of their precious ſouls.</p>
            <p n="100">100. It's a moſt ſhamefull thing <hi>(ſaid Seneca)</hi> to ſpeake one thing and thinke another. Let not thine heart reproach thy tongue, when thou ſpeakeſt to God or Man.</p>
            <p n="101">101. <hi>Epictetus</hi> complain'd that there were many who would be Philoſophers as far as a few good words would goe, but were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for practiſe.</p>
            <p>Such as ſay well and doe well are to be imbraced, <hi>ſaid Ariſtotle,</hi> but their very profeſſion is to be ſuſpected who back it not by a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table practice. <hi>'Tis not names, but things, not words, but works.</hi> What pity 'tis to conjoyne drunkard or ſwearer, or proud or covetous
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:55955:118"/>with Chriſtian; <hi>when the drunkard goes to hell, what will then become of the Chriſtian?</hi> men joyne what God hath ſeparated, and God will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate what men hath joyn'd. 'Tis no leſſe an abomination to put a good name upon a bad man, then to put a bad name upon a good man.</p>
            <p n="102">102. It's ſtoried of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he never ſaid to his ſouldiers <hi>ite,</hi> go on, but <hi>venite,</hi> come on, or follow me. <hi>Chriſt</hi> gives his people no command to obey, but he ſhewes them the way, <hi>follow me,</hi> is his word of command.</p>
            <p n="103">103. <hi>Phocion</hi> after he had done many notable ſervices for the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> was put to death by the; but a little before his death he charged his ſon never to wiſh ill to the <hi>Athenians</hi> for what they had done to him. <hi>Wiſh them well, that wiſh you ill,</hi> love and be a friend to your enemies, pray for and curſe not them that doe deſpightfully uſe you.</p>
            <pb n="220" facs="tcp:55955:119"/>
            <p n="104">104. When <hi>Flaminius the Roman Generall</hi> had ſet the Greekes at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty they ſo cried out <hi>Soter, Soter,</hi> Saviour, Saviour, that the very birds aſtoniſht at the noiſe fell to the earth. Oh with what ſhout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhould <hi>Saints</hi> cry out of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, Soter, Soter,</hi> Saviour, Saviour, ſeeing he hath ſet them at liberty from Satan ſin and wrath to come?</p>
            <p n="105">105. <hi>Crates</hi> threw his Gold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Sea,</hi> ſaying, <hi>ego perdam te, ne tu perdas me.</hi> I will deſtroy thee, leſt thou deſtroy me. <hi>If men doe not put the love of the world to death, the love of the world will put them to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="106">106. One of the Emperours ſaid of <hi>Rome, inveni lateritiam, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morcam reliqui,</hi> I found it built of bricks, but I leave it of marble: <hi>Chriſt always makes us better then he finds us.</hi> He finds us a lump of dyrt dunghill, a ſinke of ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, but he purgeth us from dead workes and builds us up an
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:55955:119"/>holy (which is the moſt glorious) temple unto God.</p>
            <p n="107">107. <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaid of two of his Courtiers, that the one loved the King, but the other loved <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander.</hi> May not <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſay of profeſſors, that ſome love <hi>Jeſus,</hi> but few love <hi>Chriſt. Vix diligitur Jeſus propter Jeſum, Jeſus</hi> is ſcarce loved for his own ſake. 'Twas <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his complaint.</p>
            <p n="108">108. A certaine ſtranger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on embaſſage to the Senators of <hi>Rome,</hi> and colouring of his hoary haire and pale cheekes with vermilion, hue a grave Senator eſpying thedeceit, <hi>ſtood up and ſaid</hi> what Sincerity can we expect, at this mans hand, whoſe lockes and looks and lippes doe lie? think the ſame <hi>(ſaith one)</hi> of all painted hypocrites.</p>
            <p n="109">109. <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> would never fore-acquaint his ſouldiers of any ſet time for removall or onſet, that they might be alwaies in
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:55955:120"/>readineſs. Be <hi>ye alſo ready,</hi> for ye know not the time when the <hi>Son of man</hi> will come.</p>
            <p n="110">110. <hi>Socrates</hi> when he ſaw one drnuke or diſcompoſed, and out of order, would ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, am not I ſuch a one? by the ſight of others ſins, men may learne to bewaile their owne ſinfulnes and heart of corruption. As <hi>Maſter Bradford,</hi> (commonly called holy <hi>Bradford</hi>) when he ſaw any drunke or heard any ſweare, &amp;c. would railingly complaine, <hi>Lord</hi> I have a drunken head, <hi>Lord</hi> I have a ſwearing heart. And the diſciples fear'd themſelves each man rather then another, and therefore ſaid <hi>Lord</hi> is it I? but <hi>Judas (he alters the word, being the bag-bearer and a meere hireling)</hi> he ſayes, <hi>Maſter</hi> is it I?</p>
            <p n="111">111. <hi>Magnus eſt animus qui ſe Deo tradidit,</hi> ſaid <hi>Seneca.</hi> He is of a truly great ſpirit, who reſignes up himſelfe to God: Puſillanimous
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:55955:120"/>and low ſpirits ſtrive and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord, truſt him, and he ſhall bring it to paſſe,</hi> Pſal. 37.5.</p>
            <p n="112">112. When the Senate inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Auguſtus</hi> of what ſome had ſaid of him, tuſh, ſaid he, <hi>non tantum habemus otii,</hi> we are not at leiſure to liſten to every ſlander that's raiſed of us. A Chriſtian ſhould be (as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Severus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour) carefull of what is to be done by him, but careles of what is ſaid of him.</p>
            <p n="113">113. When <hi>Pyrrhus, Councellor to Sultan Selimus,</hi> perſwaded the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> to beſtow the great wealth which he had taken from the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Merchants</hi> upon ſome notable Hoſpitall for releife of the poore, <hi>nay rather</hi> ſaid he, let it be reſtored to the right owners, and ſo it was. <hi>Ill-gotten goods given to the poor is no charity, reſtitution is the beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage can be made of ſuch gaine.</hi> Would there were more <hi>Zacheus</hi>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:55955:121"/>Chriſtians in the world, for though by reſtitution they might be poorer in goods, yet they would be richer in goodneſſe. <hi>A little good eſtate is better then a great bad one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="114">114. After that <hi>Socrates</hi> was put to death at <hi>Athens, Ariſtophanes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed a Tragedy of his concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Palamedes</hi> who had been exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the <hi>Grecians</hi> long before at the ſiege of <hi>Troy,</hi> in which tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy were theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye have ſlaine, ye have ſlaine of Greeks the very beſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>— that never any did infeſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>At the hearing whereof the people were ſo moved, that they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell upon the Authors of <hi>Socrates</hi> his death and drew them forth to puniſhment. Oh that (as one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes it) we could be as nimble to apprehend and to be avenged of our ſinnes, who put <hi>Chriſt</hi> to
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:55955:121"/>death who was without ſin, who never did any hurt, but good all his dayes.</p>
            <p n="115">115. <hi>Contemno minutulos iſtos deos modò Jovem habeam propitium,</hi> ſaid a heathen man; I contemne and deſpiſe all thoſe petty gods, ſo <hi>Jupiter</hi> be my friend. So <hi>Chriſt (ſaith the heavenly man)</hi> be my mediator and interceſſor, I care not for the petty advocates which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> adore.</p>
            <p n="116">116. <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> forbad the <hi>Romans</hi> to believe that God had the forme of beaſt or man; and it was from the beginning of <hi>Rome</hi> an hundred and ſeventy yeares that they had no Image of God, either painted or graven. <hi>Plut. in vit.</hi> Rome-Heathen more Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, then Rome-Chriſtian, or rather Anti-chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="117">117. God, <hi>whom juſt men deſire to be like unto,</hi> doth excell all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature in 3 ſeverall things; in immortality, in power, and
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:55955:122"/>virtue; of which three, virtue is the moſt honourable and precious thing. <hi>Plut. in vita Ariſtidis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="118">118. <hi>Plato</hi> aſking <hi>quid fuit, quod ſemper erit, et nunquam fiebat,</hi> what that was, that always was, and never was made, <hi>et quid fuit quod ſemper fiebat et nunquam fuit,</hi> what that was, that was alwaies made, and yet never was, received this Anſwer: The firſt is God, the ſecond is a creature.</p>
            <p n="119">119. <hi>Phocion</hi> ſaid to one that requeſted an ulawfull thing of him, thou canſt not have me for a friend and a flatterer both. <hi>He is the trueſt friend that will doe nothing but what conſiſts with the trueſt friend-ſhip, and a good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="120">120. This was <hi>the nobleſt glory</hi> that could be among men, when a man bore the bell and praiſe, not that he was the ſwifteſt among the ſwift, or the ſtrongeſt among the ſtrong, but honeſt among the honeſteſt. <hi>Plut. in Lycurgo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="272" facs="tcp:55955:122"/>
            <p n="121">121. When <hi>Philip</hi> askt <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus,</hi> if he did not fear to loſe his head? he ſaid, no, for if he took away his head, the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> would give him one immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, he ſhould be ſtatued in the Treaſury of eternal fame. So <hi>Ovid.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Me tamen extincto fama perennis erit.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Should not Chriſtians then live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove fear of ſuffering, and ſay as the Apoſtle 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 17.</p>
            <p n="122">122. <hi>Numa Pampilius</hi> put ſo much confidence in the gods, that one day when it was told him, that his enemies were in arms againſt him, his anſwer was, and I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. <hi>Plut. in vit.</hi> Thus ſaid <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 109.3, 4. They ſought againſt me without a cauſe, but I gave my ſelf unto Prayer.</p>
            <p n="123">123. <hi>Brutus</hi> viſiting <hi>Ligarius,</hi> and aſking him, what, ſick, <hi>Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius?</hi> no, <hi>Brutus,</hi> ſaid he, if thou
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:55955:123"/>have any noble enterpriſe in hand, I am well: So ſhould a ſoul ſay for Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="124">124. Some write of <hi>Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> a famous Theban, and ſome of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> that after high and unexpected Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they became <hi>(in their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance at leaſt)</hi> very ſad, more like Mourners then Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphers, for no other reaſon then for fear of ſome eminent diſaſter; for they held it omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous among the Ancients, to have long proſperity: One of them hath this good ſaying, though ill enough meant by him; <hi>God will not endure that any ſhould think well of himſelf, but himſelf.</hi> 'Tis much according to Scripture-diſcovery, that when men glory in their pride, God ſtains the pride of their glory.</p>
            <p n="125">125. When one wiſht <hi>Pythagoras</hi> (as I thinke) that the gods would give him whatſoever he deſired,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:55955:123"/>nay rather ſaid he, that I may deſire but what they will give. <hi>Gods will is better for us, then ours for our ſelves,</hi> 'tis not for us to preſcribe, but to ſubmit to God.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA in the <hi>Milk and Honey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>S.</hi> for ſentence, <hi>l.</hi> for line.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sentence</hi> 96. line 3. <hi>for becomes of,</hi> r. <hi>becomes us,</hi> S. 258. <hi>for thy will,</hi> r. <hi>my will be done.</hi> S. 294. r. <hi>much from a little.</hi> S. 295. r. <hi>ſuch thorns may be toucht.</hi> P. 250. lin. <hi>ult. for be preſt,</hi> r. <hi>depreſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Heathen Improved.</p>
            <p>S. 7. l. 3. <hi>for</hi> Cenippus, <hi>r.</hi> Eunippus. P. 193. l. 3. <hi>for our</hi> r. <hi>one tale.</hi> P. 200. l. 2. <hi>leave out</hi> not, <hi>and</hi> r. <hi>he might well ſleep.</hi> S. 82. <hi>for</hi> Alexander, <hi>r.</hi> Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander. S. 93. <hi>leave out</hi> no, <hi>and</hi> r. <hi>appeareth greater.</hi> S. 110. <hi>for railingly,</hi> r. <hi>wailingly complain.</hi> Ibid. <hi>for a drunken head,</hi> r. <hi>heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
